Welcome to Part 1 in the module that
provides an overview of the JAWS web
server case study.
In this part of the module we'll be
providing an overview of the
pattern-orientated design of the JAWS web
server.
Let's first spend a little time talking
about what a web server does.
The goal, of course, of a web server is to
download content in a scalable, efficient,
and robust way, to clients.
Now let's kind of walk through some of the
major elements, architectually, in a web
server.
It starts off with some kind of
user-interface control on the client side.
Either a command line or some kind of
dialogue or window view that allows users
to enter in the urls for the content they
want.
This then works with some kind of
requester to convert this into a get
request or some other type of request
that's then sent across the network using.
The TCP/IP protocol, running through the
operating system device drivers and
networking protocol stacks.
And when it comes up on the other side, on
the server side, there's some kind of
event dispatcher component that reads the
request out of a socket, or some other
type of network endpoint.
Converts it into a get message.
And it passes it up to the appropriate
protocol handler, be it HTTP1.0 or HTTP1.1
and so on and that protocol handler does
its thing understands what the request is
for and avails itself for some kind of
file cache to locate the content required
and requested by the client and then to
pass it back as a stream of data.
Through the TCP/IP connection.
There's of course some kind of parser on
the receiver side that reads the request
and then displays the message in whatever
format is designated in the message
headers.
There's a number of requirements we're
going to focus on in our case study.
The first of which is to be able to make
it possible to support.
Multiple operating systems, with different
capabilities and different
characteristics.
We want to be able to run our server on
Windows, different versions of Unix,
real-time operating systems, and so on and
so forth.
We also want to be able to support many
different types of design alternatives.
We want to be able to support different
kinds of concurrency models, different
kinds of event management, and event
synchronization models.
Different kinds of file caching models,
and so on and so forth.
We'd also like to make sure that we can
take maximal advantage of whatever the
operating system or the hardware provides
us.
If we have multi-core or multi-processor
or hardware, we want to make sure that,
that is taken advantage of.
If the operating system supports efficient
asynchronous I/O we want to make sure
that, that works effectively.
And finally we'd like to be able to make
sure that our system is going to be robust
even in the face of accidental or
malicious access.
By clients.
So these, these are some of the
requirements that will drive and guide the
design that we're looking at.
In order to accomplish this we're going to
be focusing on a specific example, which
is a web server framework called JAWS.
Jaws is a pattern oriented web server
implemented using ACE, and you can
download both ACE and JAWS from the UR,
URL shown at the bottom of this slide.
We're going to be focusing in on the
server portion, and really a key portion
of the server architecture for JAWS.
And let me describe for you briefly what
those component elements are.
The first part we'll talk about.
And this will be the bulk of our focus.
Is on the event dispatcher component.
The purpose of the event dispatcher is to
accept Connections from clients, receive
the various get requests using the HTP
protocol and then perform the various
event demultiplexing and concurrency
processing and synchronization necessary
to move the incoming requests up to the
appropriate protocol handling.
The protocol handler then performs the
various parcing and processing of the HTTP
requests and along the way, it leverages
some kind of file cache.
And the file cache is used to make sure
that we don't have to go to disk for
frequently accessed content.
We want to be able to get this content as
quickly as possible out of memory.
And we'll be using various techniques and
tricks like memory mapped files and so on
in order to maximize the performance of
this portion of our web server
architecture.
There's a number of different sources of
variability in JAWS.
And our pattern oriented solution, and the
frameworks we apply, have to take into
account these various sources of
variability.
Try to make them as common and pluggable
as possible.
Some of the different sources of
variability include different concurrency
models.
Do we use thread per connection?
Do we use various thread pool models?
Do we use a reactive approach, and so on?
We'd like to make those as easy to plug
and play as possible.
As another set of variability or what kind
of caching protocols and caching
strategies do we use?
Do we use least frequently used caching,
least recently used caching and so on.
We'd like to be able to make those
pluggable and tuneable for different run
time environments.
Another issue is what type of event the
multiplexing model has to be used.
Synchronous event the multiplexing which
is very common and UNIX's environments, do
we use asynchronous event handling which
is very common in windows and we want to
be able to understand the trade-offs
between the various approaches to pick the
right one for the context in which we
happen to be executing.
Some other sources of variability include
which transfer protocol are we using.
Http 1.0, 1.1 or something else, because
we could have the protocols be pluggable
as well.
Another source of variability is the
operating system API and the transport
protocol APIs.
We'd like to be able to run our, the bulk
of our web server logic without change
Irrespective of the platform we're running
on.
And moreover we'd like to do this in a way
that maximally leverages key operating
system transfer protocol of the hardware
characteristics, where all, we can,
wherever we can.
Patterns and frameworks are crucial to
being able to support Variation-oriented
design.
We had talked about variation-oriented
design in the overview of patterns portion
in section two of the course and here is
just a quick recap in the context of JAWS
and web servers.
So variation-oriented design is a, is a
process or a method that works as follows.
You start out by understanding a set of
patterns and frameworks.
Look carefully at the patterns and
frameworks to understand the benefits and
applicability and limitations.
And armed with this knowledge you're then
able to perform various kinds of trade off
analysis to figure out which pattern and
framework components.
Work most effectively in the context in
which you're running.
And based on this analysis.
That then guides the design and
implementation process.
Figuring out in a particular environment
for a particular set of requirements in a
particular context.
Which of these patterns and frameworks to
apply, and how to compose them.
And of course, we use this knowledge to be
able to go and help implement and
integrate.
Our solutions leveraging patterns and
frameworks wherever possible.
And this of course is a feedback loop, and
it goes back around again as we get
smarter about the patterns and
frameworks,we can do a better job of
implementing our solution and so on and so
forth.
This is also a good example of where we
will be applying throughout this section
the notions of commonality and variability
analysis which had talked about earlier.
As part of the core for how you design
effective object oriented systems.
Looking for common interfaces that we
could have stable reliance upon to build
our architecture.
Looking for places of canonical
variability, where we could build stable
interfaces to variability, making them
easier to plug and play.
And you'll see many, many examples of this
as we look through JAWS.
So to summarize this part of the module,
JAWS is a pattern oriented, open-source
web server that's been optimized for a
variety of different mechanisms and
techniques, that are known to make web
servers run effienctly.
For example, it has a variety of different
kinds of lightweight concurrency models,
using different threading strategies It
also is used to minimize locking, where we
don't have many locks.
There's really only a handful of locks in
the critical path to protect the, the file
cache when we access it from multiple
threads of control from our pool of
threads.
We also apply various file caching and
memory mapping techniques to avoid having
to go to disk when we access very
frequently ac, frequently utilized and
frequently downloaded content.
We use gather write I/O mechanisms in
order to be able to minimize domain
crossings between user and kernel space
and to be able to work around some
limitations with the various congestion
control algorithms like nagle's algorithm.
We also are clever about minimizing
logging by trying to put the logging in
thread specific storage, pre-compute.
Http messages that are common so we don't
have to build them on the fly.
Minimize the number of times we use the
time system call to get time stamps.
And finally, optimize the various settings
in the transport interface to make sure we
can get the maximum Throughput in a given
environment.
If you take a look, you'll find that JAWS
is available in a couple of different
implementations in the ACE release and
this will give you a chance to look and
see how JAWS and it's pattern-oriented
approaches evolved over time.
And if you take a look at the URL at the
bottom of this slide You'll see a number
of papers and more information that
describes the architecture and pattern
oriented design of the JAWS web server.