Welcome to part three in the module that
provide a discussion of patterns and
frameworks for sevice access and
communication.
In previous parts of this module we
summerized the accidentl complexities With
the sea level programming interfaces
available on most operating systems.
We then talked about how we can apply the
wrapper facade pattern to alleviate a
number of these complexities.
We're now going to spend a little time
describing the ACE C++ socket wrapper
facades, which are open source
encapsulations of the underlying socket
functions that run port-ably on many, many
different operating systems.
The ACE socket wrapper facades define a
set of C++ classes that work together to
address some of the limitations with
sockets.
They define building blocks for higher
level of abstractions, you can plug and
play these different wrapper facades for
sockets or what various types of sockets.
Other kinds of interprocess communication
mechanisms.
Using parameterized types or inheritance.
And make it easy to build and plug and
play these larger constructs out of
smaller pieces.
You can also simplify common use cases.
If you take a look at the normal socket
interface it causes, there's a number of
different functions that have to be called
in order to set up a socket in passive
mode or active mode.
We can do those things in one fell swoop
with a single call by using abstraction.
This, the wrapper facades that ACE
provides are also more type safe, you just
can't do certain types of error prone
operations that you might do with the low
level C interfaces.
And finally, we can also provide
portability to many different operating
systems, whereas before we'd have to
wrestle with those types of issues in each
of our applications 1 at a time.
These classes of course are designed with
the wrapper facade pattern in mind.
And that'll help to explain and justify
and document some of the design deciscions
we have here that we'll be covering.
There's a number of different classes that
are part of the C++ wrapper facades in
ACE.
One of the classes is called ACE_INET_Addr
and that provides an encapsulation of the
internet domain addressing functions and
data.
We also have something called an
ACE_SOCK_Stream, which is the primary unit
that's used to communicate sending and
receiving data across connections between
peers.
There's also a factory called an
ACE_SOCK_Connector that's used to connect
an ACE_SOCK_Stream with a remote server so
it can begin to communicate.
And then finally we have another factory
that's called the ACE_SOCK_Connector and
that's used to passively accept
connections and initialize a
ACE_SOCK_Stream so it can carry out
communication, interaction with its
connected peer.
Take a look at this URL for more
information about how these various
classes work together.
You take a look at the socket wrappers of
ACE, you'll see that they're intentionally
designed to be much more clearly aligned
with the various design dimensions of
programming both local and remote
communication.
We're going to talk through some of those
dimensions here.
One of the dimensions is the type of
communications service.
Are we using datagrams?
Are we using streams?
Are using something odd called a connected
datagram.
These kinds of things are factored away
into the manner in which we design the
classes.
Another key theme here is connection role
versus communication role.
There's a pair of connection roles, active
connections, passive connections.
And then you have communication that takes
place once things are, are connected.
Once again, these things are baked into
the design of the classes.
Yet another role is the communication
domain.
Is it Internet domain, which is meant to
use TCP/IP across address spaces, across
networks or across hosts on different
networks or is it intended to be used for
local domain, local communication, local
sockets, the so-called Unix domain
communication?
Where the processes reside on the same
host machine, but they run in different
processes.
So the nice part about the wrapper facades
is that by using the wrapper facade
pattern, ACE is able to encapsulate these
different types, roles, and communication
domains in the object oriented design.
It's easy to tell at a glance by looking
at the names of the, The classes, what
role they play in the overall
communication paradigm.
As a simple example of this, if you take a
look at the wrapper facades you'll see
that we have a set of classes that are
called the SOCK classes and these are the
ones that embody the internet
communication domain.
There's a separate set of classes called
the LSOCK classes.
And they embody the local body or UNIX
main communication.
And it's easy again, to tell at a glance,
how these different classes work just by
reading the names.
Ace also provides many wrapper facades for
other kinds of communication that are not
as common, but are very popular and
powerful for things like broadcast,
multicast, and various kinds of unicast
mechanisms for data-grams as well.
So let's talk a bit about the classes, and
we'll talk a bit more about the class
design.
One of the key classes you use when you
program with a socket wrappers is, the
ACE_SOCK_Stream Class.
And this class essentially encapsulates
data transfer between connected piers.
It has methods in there that allow you to
send and receive up to N bytes of data, as
well as exactly N Bytes of data so no more
confusion with short reads and short
writes.
It supports scatter, read, and gather
write operations which allow you to do
very efficient domain crossing
interactions to send groups of data or
receive groups of data in one fell swoop.
And it also makes it easy to perform
blocking.
...nonblocking and timed I/O with a very
simple, similar interface.
Another capability you'll see throughout
all the different wrappers in ACE is the
concept of c-plus-plus traits, which makes
it much easier to provide generic
programming, providing generic algorithms
and generic containers and using the
traits in, in interesting ways.
In this particular case, you see this...
(End of transcription.) Ace sock stream
has something that's called a PEER ADDR
which is a trait.
Just a little digression on traits.
Traits are powerful design pattern that
are applied to C++, used very commonly in
the C++ standard template library.
And they're used to be able to allow
classes to indicate explicitly what their
dependencies are on other classes.
In a generic way.
So, for example, all the inner process
communication wrapper facades in ACE
define various traits, like peer Addr and
peer stream.
And those things are then mapped to the
appropriate specific dependency on
specific classes in that particular.
Wrapper for such family, for example here
is an illustration how we can have the
same trade name for both the socket
wrappers as well as the TLI wrapper which
is another kind of wrapper around a kind
of IPC metalets and you commonly find on
many Linux platforms and notice how all
classes now also they've got periators
that those map the different kinds of The
use of traits makes it easy to write
generic algorithms.
It makes it easier to write generic
containers.
And therefore, as, as powerful a mechanism
that you'll find used throughout the
generic programming paradigm in C++.
If you take a look at this URL, you'll
find out more information about traits and
trait classes.
So now going back onto our discussion
about the, the ACE.
Abstractions.
So, we have ACE SOCK stream that's used
for communication once things are
connected.
But we first have to connect things in
order to be able to get the communication
to flow.
To do this, we have a factory called the
ACE SOCK Connecter.
And this factor is used to actively
establish a new end point of communication
by allowing.
A client, typically, to connect to a
particular address.
And this connection establishment can be
done either blocking or non-blocking or in
a timed manner.
And once the connection is actually
successfully established, what you get as
a result is an initialize and connected
ACE sock stream, which can then be used to
send or receive the data.
That's the active side of the connection
role.
These again, use traits.
Just as we used for the sock stream.
The passive side is done with another
class, called the ACE sock acceptor.
The ace sock accepter is the part that
waits to lsiten for connections to come in
froma ctive clients.
And the way this work, is it.
Waits to connect, waits for the connect to
show up.
And when the connect shows up, the accept
function returns and what you've got back
is a connected and initialized
ACE_SOCK_Stream object.
And that ACE_SOCK_Stream object can then
be used to send and receive data in
whatever application or service oriented
protocol we're using, without having to
worry about how it got connected in the
first place, be it active or passive.
You can do these accept operations both in
or, in blocking, non-blocking and timed
manner.
Again, we can also use mechanisms using
traits to be able to plug and play these
different IPC capabilities for higher
level components.
So to summarize this particular
discussion.
Unfortunately, the socket API has a bit of
a confusing asymmetry between connection
roles and the socket modes.
For example, here's a, a problem that
could arise when you're programming
sockets: There's nothing to stop you from
calling the socket factory, getting back a
socket and then accidentally calling send
on that socket.
Before you connect it, the API won't
prevent you from doing that.
Likewise, there's nothing to stop you from
getting a socket and then accepting on
that socket and then trying to do a read
on the listen mode socket, which is also
incorrect.
But there's nothing that the API can do to
make those things go away.
So, one of the nice things about the a
socket wrapper facades is that they make
it impossible to makes these kinds of
mistakes.
You can't do things in the wrong order.
You can't accidentally try to do an accept
call on a data mode sock stream.
You can't do a read and write call on a
listen mode sock acceptor, and so on.
And so these kind of things are, are
minimized in, in your, design.