.
Hello, and welcome to Part 2 of the module
that provides an overview of the JAWS Web
Server Case Study.
In the previous part of this module, we
described the pattern-oriented JAWS Web
Server Case Study.
Now, we'll turn our attention to
describing some of the key patterns that
make up the pattern-oriented design of
that web server, focusing primarily on the
portions called the event dispatcher.
Naturally, these patterns could be applied
to many other kinds of servers and other
types of concurrent and networked
applications.
All the patterns we'll be describing here,
with one exception, come from the
Pattern-Oriented Software Architecture
Volume 2 book, which focuses on patterns
for concurrent and distributed objects.
The first set of patterns we will talk
about can be grouped into service, access
and configuration.
These patterns are intended to effectively
design and configure application access to
interfaces and implementations of evolving
services and components.
We'll also talk about a number of patterns
related to event handling, which is
intended to simplify the development of
flexible and efficient event-driven apps.
We'll also talk about concurrency
patterns.
These patterns are intended to enhance the
design and performance of multi- threaded
concurrent and network software.
And finally, we'll talk about patterns
that are grouped according to
synchronization, and these patterns are
intended to provide flexible solutions to
common problems related to synchronizing
concurrent software.
If you take a look at the POSA2 book,
you'll see that there are 17 patterns in
all.
And we'll be covering 14 of these patterns
in this discussion.
You can find out more about POSA2 and the
other POSA volumes here at the website at
the bottom of the slide.
So let's talk about the different
challenges we face when developing JAWS,
and we'll discuss some of the patterns we
can apply to address those challenges.
The first set of challenges we're going to
deal with have to do with trying to
encapsulate the tedious, error-prone, and
non-portable C level interfaces.
And to do this we'll be applying the
wrapper facade pattern.
Wrapper facade is used to provide
object-oriented class and object
interfaces to these low-level C APIs.
Next, we'll talk about ways of being able
to decouple event de-multiplexing,
connector establishment and service
initialization from the actual protocol
processing we're doing with our web server
to send and receive various get requests
and post requests and other types of HTTP
requests.
In this particular case, we'll be talking
about some event handling patterns.
We'll be talking about the reactor
pattern, which is a pattern for being able
to separate the low level arrival of
incoming events from the dispatching of
those events to appropriate handlers.
We'll also be talking about the acceptor
connector pattern which is a pattern for
decoupling connection establishment and
service initialization from protocol
processing.
After this, we'll start dealing with
issues of scaling up the performance of
our web server, in order to be able to
take advantage of multi-core and
multi-processor platforms.
To do this, we'll apply the active object
and half sync, half async patterns.
These patterns allow us to have pools of
threads that can be mapped to the
underlying hardware resources and
operating system abstractions much more
scalably, and much more efficiently.
As we talk about half sync half a sync,
and we talk about active object, one of
the things we'll have to do is provide a
way to have access to a synchronized
request queue that can be put and get by
multiple threads concurrently.
In order to do this, we'll apply the
monitor object pattern.
This pattern ensures that only one thread
of control is active within the state of a
particular object at a time.
We'll next discuss an alternative pattern
for concurrency.
This pattern is meant to make this, the
concurrent processing more efficient and
more predictable relative to half sync,
half async, and the use of active object.
This pattern is called leader followers,
and it gives us another way to allocate
and manage pools of threads that has lower
overhead and less context which
synchronization, data movement and so on.
Well then, we kind of switch gears and
talk about asynchronous ways of handling
events using something called the proactor
pattern.
The proactor pattern makes it possible to
be able to leverage the underlying
asynchronous iO operations that are
available on certain operating systems
that can give you tremendous performance
boost without using lots of threads.
Next, we'll talk about a variation and an
enhancement to proactor, which makes it
possible to de-multiplex and dispatch the
completion of asynchronous operations when
they're finished.
Next, we'll talk about ways of being able
to make our web server more flexible, more
configurable, more configurable late in
the design cycle at installation time, or
even during run time.
Being able to bring in different services
and small parts.
Being able to link in different
implementations of the web server that are
tuned for the particular context in which
it's running.
To do this, we'll apply the component
configurator pattern, which makes its
possible to dynamically link in various
pieces of an application or service later
on in the life cycle.
We'll also next talk about a pattern that
does not appear in the POSA2 book.
This pattern actually is briefly
summarized in the POSA4 book, and also
appears in a paper that you can get from
my website.
This pattern is dealing with ways of
trying to minimize the utilization of
resources when clients are not actively
accessing those resources, and the pattern
is called the activator pattern.
And we'll talk about this pattern and
illustrate how to apply it to JAWS.
The remaining set of patterns we deal with
here focus on synchronization, which is
somewhat narrower in scope, but no less
important.
One of the patterns we'll talk about is a
way of being able to take the components
you develop, that are meant to be used
from different concurrency models, and
allow the locking behavior to be
strategized, by us the strategized locking
pattern.
So you can plug and play different locking
mechanisms that are tailored for the
particular use cases in which a component
appears.
A helper pattern that makes strategized
locking and other synchronization type of
activities easier to deal with is called
scope locking, which ensures that locks
are acquired on entrance to a scope and
released automatically, irrespective of
how a thread leaves that scope.
The final pattern we'll talk about in this
set is a way that we go and enhance the
use of strategized locking by ensuring
that components that have been genericized
and strategized with respect to their
synchronization properties, can do this in
a very lightweight manner using the thread
safe interface pattern.
These patterns, as you'll see, will give
us the ability to be able to do various
kinds of things, make the system easier to
work with and able to port to a much wider
range of platforms when we combine them
with various types of frameworks.
So to summarize this particular section,
the POSA2 patterns direct developers
towards strategic architecture design and
programming elements of concurrent and
network software.
If you focus on the strategic elements
effectively in your solutions, then it
helps to resolve many of the vexing
accidental and inherent complexities that
would otherwise plague your solutions.
We'll see that these patterns can be
applied to many other things besides web
servers, but this allows us to be very
concrete in what we're focusing on.
Another thing we'll do with the POSA
patterns is we'll make it possible to be
able to direct developers away from the
unhealthy preoccupation with the low level
concurrent and networking operating system
mechanisms.
It's always important to have a solid
grasp of how to do these kinds of low
level concurrency and networking
mechanisms.
But keep in mind that these are primarily
tactical in nature.
If you get the architecture right, that's
the most important thing.
If you are an expert at programming p
threads or sockets, but the architecture
of your solution doesn't work, doesn't
scale, isn't correct, isn't going to be
able to deal with performance issues and
reliability and security issues, then all
the great programming in the world won't
save you.
Naturally, it's important to have both a
strategic and tactical grasp.
And we'll focus on those kinds of things
throughout this discussion.
Finally, by combining the POSA2 patterns
with patterns from the Gang of 4 book, the
POSA4 book, other volumes of other books
and other sources of material on patterns,
it will allow us to be able to develop
much more powerful and comprehensive
pattern languages.
And we'll look at a number of those
examples as we go through the rest of this
section.