Hello and welcome to section three of the
course.
This section will build upon the material
we covered in the earlier parts, in order
to be able to demonstrate, how to apply
Patterns and frameworks to concurrent and
network software.
In section one of the course, we focused
on the concepts, mechanisms, layers, and
design dimensions of concurrent network
software.
Focusing primarily on the operating system
and host infrastructure middle Lower
layers.
Section two of the course presented an
introduction to patterns and frameworks,
focusing on concepts and relationships,
relationships between patterns,
relationships between patterns and
frameworks.
As well as covering the concepts of scope,
commonality, and variability analysis, and
variation oriented design.
Throughout the section.
This section then goes ahead and goes into
more detail illustrating, by example, the
application of patterns and frameworks to
particular examples of the course.
This particular section has seven modules
and I'll give you a quick overview of each
of them in this overview section.
The first module we'll be focusing on the
case study that we'll use as a running
example throughout the section.
This case study focuses on applying
patterns and pattern languages,
predominantly from the posted two book
with some help from the gang of four
patterns, together with a variety of
different object oriented frameworks.
From the adaptive communication
environment, or ACE, in the context of the
Jaws web server.
Jaws is an open source web server that's
bundled with the opensource ACE toolkit
and that will allow you to be able to
follow along, see how the patterns are
reaffied in code.
See how different interpretations of
patterns can be implemented in different
ways.
Using the various frameworks that come as
part of ACE.
From that point onwards, we'll then be
demonstrating the application of patterns
and frameworks to various aspects and
areas in Jaws.
We're going to start out by discussing
various patterns and components For
service access and communication.
Here, we'll be focusing on the wrapper
facade pattern which encapsulates the
tedious error prone and nonportable system
programming interfaces written in C with
much more portable, modular and reusable
object oriented class interfaces.
And we'll demonstrate a simple example of
a web server implemented using wrapper
facades in ACE and Java.
The next section will present patterns and
frameworks related to synchronous event
handling, connection establishment, and
service initialization.
Here we be focusing on several patterns
will be focusing on the reactor pattern,
which is a pattern for decoupling event
handling concerns and the acceptor
connector patterns.
Pattern, which is a pattern that relates
to decoupling connection establishment
service initialization from the actual
protocols conducted after services are
initialized.
We'll be illustrating how these patterns
can be implemented using various
frameworks that are part of ACE, including
the reactor framework and the acceptor
connector framework.
Next we'll be describing patterns for
service activation and configuration.
The idea here is to be able to compose
applications and services out of building
block parts, building block objects,
components and subservices.
That can be brought at installation time
or even at run time.
In order to be able to customize your
software for its particular environment.
Here we'll be talking about the component
configurator pattern, which is a pattern
that's used to be able to decouple the
various elements in the software system
from the time at which they're composed
together and the activator pattern, which
is used to be able to launch.
Various services or servers on demand in
response to incoming client requests.
We'll also be illustrating how these
patterns can be realized in the context of
the ACE service configuration framework,
which basically leverages off of some of
the ACE reactor framework and the ACE
receptor framework and acceptor connector
frameworks as well.
Next, we'll move our attention towards
patterns for concurrency and
synchronization.
Here we'll be exploring a wide variety of
different patterns.
We'll be exploring patterns like active
object which decouples the thread that
invokes an operation from the thread that
runs it.
And we'll be combining active object with
reactor.
And monitor object in order to be able to
form more complex patterns like Half-Sync,
Half-Async, which allows pools of threads
to run at a more scalable manner, taking
advantage of multiple CPUs and cores.
We'll also be talking about various
alternative concurrency designs, such as
the Leader/Followers pattern, which is
more predictable and efficient than
Half-Sync/Half-Async.
But perhaps not as scalable in some
environments.
Along the way we'll also be talking about
the various patterns for synchronization.
Things like scope blocking, synchronize
blocking, thread safe interface, and the
double chock, double checked optimization
pattern.
And naturally we'll be illustrating how to
apply these various patterns in the
context of a number of ACE frameworks.
Including the ACE task framework which is
used to provide various concurrence
capabilities and how that combines with
the ACE reactor and acceptor connector
frameworks that we've talked about before.
The final section to pres, pres, to
presenting the patterns and frameworks
will focus on the Proactor pattern.
This is pattern that relates to
asynchronous event handling.
Proactor is a pattern that allows multiple
operations to run asynchronously,
leveraging operating system support for
asynchronous I/O.
Allowing you to be able to get very
scalable communication without having to
use a large number of threads.
And along the way we'll also be describing
the asynchronous completion token pattern,
which is a pattern often used in
conjunction with proactor to be able to
efficiently demultiplex.
Completion results to the handlers of
those results.
Naturally, we'll also be illustrating the
application of this pattern, in the
context of one of the ace frameworks, the
ace proactor framework.
And we'll be illustrating how this
framework can be used to make it possible
to run our web server, in a very
high-performance way, on Windows platforms
leveraging Windows asynchronous I/O
operations and capabilities such as
overlapped I/O and I/O completion ports.
We'll finally wrap up this section with a
discussion of the benefits and limitations
of applying patterns and frameworks to
concurrent networked software.
We'll talk about various trade-offs,
trade-offs between learning curve and
complexity on one hand, and productivity
boosts on the other.
We'll talk about various issues of
extensibility and flexibility on the one
hand, versus some of the inevitable
performance implications, and overheads,
and indirections that come from applying
these more advance techniques.
We'll also talk about trade-offs between
building or acquiring frameworks versus
buying them in various ways.
And then we'll also be discussing
throughout issues related to testing and
debugging of pattern oriented frameworks
and component based systems.
Because those tend to be more tricky if
you don't understand the way the various
pieces throughout this section we'll be
going into a tremendous amount of detail.
We'll be looking at lots of code examples.
Most of the code examples will be in C++.
We will also be demonstrating examples in
Java to illustrate the generality and
applicability of these patterns and
frameworks in a multiplicity of languages.
So if you're feeling a little rusty with
these languages.
If you don't have a lot of background in
object oriented programming, now is a good
time to avail yourself of the resources on
the web to learn about these languages, to
learn about the design techniques, so you
can get the most out of the material that
we cover in this section.