Welcome to part four in the module that
provides a discussion of patterns and
frameworks, for service access and
communication.
In previous parts of this module, we first
talked about some of the limitations, and
accidental complexities with the C socket
API.
We then described ways in which the
wrapper facade pattern can help to
alleviate a number of these limitations
and complexities.
We then talked about the ACE socket
wrapper facades, written in C++, to
provide cleaner access to the underlying
socket mechanisms.
And now we're going to provide an example
that illustrates how to apply these
wrapper facades, to a simple iterative web
client and server application.
Here's an overview of what we're going to
be doing here.
We're going to implement a web server and
a web client, very simple, using iterative
mechanisms, so one client connection at a
time.
And we'll start out by creating an ACE
sock acceptor, which plays the passive
role, and it waits for clients to connect
to it.
We'll then create an ACE_SOCK_Connector,
which plays the active role, and that
initiates a connection, and it'll go ahead
and initiate the connection to the server,
and create, an ACE_SOCK_Stream when the
connection is complete, likewise, the
ACE_SOCK_Acceptor will be used to accept
an incoming connection from the client and
create an initialized ACE_SOCK_Stream.
And both these, when these both
ACE_SOCK_Streams have been created and
initialized, we then go ahead and have
them communicate back and forth, sending
and receiving data in accordance with the
http protocol, and they play the, the
communication role.
So those are the keys roles that we're
going to be describing.
So here's an illustration of how we can
use the ACE_SOCK_Connector for a web
client.
What we're going to do first, is we're
going to write a simple main application
in a C++ program, and we'll process
various command line arguments that
indicate what port number, and what server
address, what content we want to be able
to get, and so on.
In this particular case, we're going to be
defaulting to port 80, because that's the
typical port number for a socket, but it
would be easy to, for a web server, it
would be easy to extend that to make it
work on different ports.
We're then going to go ahead and
instantiate the SOCK_Connector and the
SOCK_Stream, and notice how we use traits
here to make this easy to program, without
having to keep track of all those details.
And then finally, we're going to go ahead
and initiate a timed connection, which
will try for up to ten seconds to get
connected to the server, and if for some
reasons you can't get connected go ahead
and fail.
Assuming it works, what we then do is we
write a little code to set up how to send
a GET request to the server.
And the way we going to do this, is we're
going to use an, iovec, which is a data
structure that's is used for gather-write
scatter read operations, do these things
efficiently.
And we set up the, the get request part of
the message part of the message, we pass
in the path name, and then we pass in kind
of the trailer part of the HTTP get
request header, and when in all those
things are put into the iovec, we then go
ahead and make a send VN call, which sends
this vector and will block until the send
is complete.
This is going to perform a blocking send.
We don't have to do a blocking send here,
we could do a time send, but just to show
you how easy it is to do a blocking send.
What we're then going to do, is we're
going to go into a loop, waiting for the
results to come back from the server.
In this particular case, just to show you
the diversity of approaches, we're going
to implement this using timed receives,
and so we'll receive the data coming back
and we'll do something to it.
In this case, we're just going to write it
to standard output but of course, you
could buffer it up, put it some place
else.
So that illustrates the client side, now
let's take a look at the server side.
This is going to illustrate the use of
ACE_SOCK_Acceptor, and ACE_SOCK_Stream to
accept a connection, and then send and
receive the data to and from the client.
Once again, we start again by initializing
some of the key objectsm we initialize our
server address for our web server to be
port 80.
We go ahead and create our acceptor, and
then we turn around and we say wow we're
going to loop forever, accept the next
connection from a client.
And, assuming that this works properly,
what we get back from that, is a connected
ACE_SOCK_Stream.
And then we turn around and we memory map,
the path name that we extract out of that
stream by using a function called, Get
Path Name, that we're not going to talk
about here in much detail.
But you can imagine it would go through
and find the, the various path name
information, from the stream.
We memory map that, take the pointer that
comes back from the memory mapping
operation, and then we do a transfer to
send all end bytes back to the client.
In this particular case, we're a doing a
blocking send, but it would be easy to
make this a non-blocking send, if we were
concerned about flow control, or some
other kind of malicious activity on the
part of clients, jamming up the connection
and preventing the send from completing.
So this particular simple example,
illustrates how to build a very light
weight, illitive, web client and server.
It alleviates a number of problems we
discussed before, with the use of sockets,
so it's less error prone.
As you can see the original C level socket
code, would not be able to detect the
error as we see here, by running it
through the compiler.
In this case, we're reading from a
acceptor listen mode socket, we're trying
to accept on our, on a data mode socket,
which are not correct things to do.
In contrast, you simply can't do that with
the ACE wrapper facades.
You can't do reads on an acceptor, the
operation isn't supported.
You can't try to, accept on a stream, the
So these kinds of silly mistakes are
caught early on in the life cycle.
The other problem we talked about with
sockets is it's very complex, you have to
know a lot about the design, it's not
clear from looking at the interfaces, what
things do what roles.
In contrast with the wrapper facades, the
surface area is done for the design in a
way where it's fairly straight forward to
tell, by looking at the names of the
classes, what role they play.
Whether they're acceptors or connectors,
which are connection roles, active and
passive, whether they're data transfer
operations and classes like streams,
whether they're local domain, local
sockets versus interdomain, TCPIP sockets,
and so on and so forth.
Those things are, are baked into the
design, so it's easy to tell what's going
on.
Other issues we talked about with respect
to portability and non-uniformity, these
issues are also cleaned up, and so as a
result, much easier to write portable
applications, much easier to write
applications that you can tune and
optimize without having to give up the
platform independent nature, of a lot of
code you might be trying to write.
Naturally, however, we need more than just
wrapper facades in order to develop
effective web servers.
So these portablility issues are nice, but
as we go on to the next modules in this
section, we'll see that there's lots more
space to explore.
We have to be able to come more effective
ways to add concurrency.
We also have to be able to add other
capabilities, that'll make it possible to,
to be able to dynamically configure the
systems out of building block parts, and
be able to apply much more sophisticated
IO mechanisms we might have on certain
platforms.
And so we'll talk about that as we go
further.