Welcome to Part 3 in the module that
provides and overview of the JAWS Web
Server Case Study.
In previous parts of this module, we
started by describing the pattern
orientated JAWS Web Server Case Study.
And then we described the patterns we use
in order to be able to rationalize and
guide and document, the design of the JAWS
Web Server.
In this part of the module, we're going to
present a pattern language for the JAWS
Web Server and explore various alternative
passe through that language.
Just to recap a bit, if you go back to
section two of the course we had a long
discussion about pattern languages.
But to recap that briefly, a pattern
language is basically a group of related
patterns that provide a vocabulary and a
process for the orderly resolution of
certain types of challenges that arise
when you build software in a particular
context.
If you take a look at this Wikipedia link,
you'll find other examples of pattern
languages that go above and beyond
software.
In the particular context in which, which
we're discussing, the patterns in our
pattern language will be used to build
upon each other to help generate a
software architecture, and allows us to be
able to walk through and navigate the soft
architecture, to successive progressions
of design decisions, transformations of
the design, and most importantly,
different ways of going through
alternative paths through the pattern
language and the design space.
So let's take a look at a number of the
different paths we'll be exploring
throughout the rest of this section.
Here's a high level view of the pattern
language for the JAWS Web Server.
And as you can see, it includes all the
patterns that we have summarized in the
previous part of the module.
Things like wrapper facade, reactor,
acceptor connector, and so on.
I'm not going to recap these here because
we've already covered them.
If you need to go back and rewatch that
section to get a overview of what they
mean, please do so at this point.
This particular pattern language for JAWS
is also not intended to be comprehensive.
There are other patterns you might have to
do in order to be able to port this to
other environments.
There are other patterns you would apply
to do other parts of building a web server
and of course if you build a large scale
and concurrent and network software system
there will be many other patterns you'll
have to deal with in order to address
other requirements and environmental
constraints.
But we'll focus primarily on the parts
that relate to the event dispatcher
portion, because that where a lot of the
interesting concurrent and network
programming issues arise.
The first path through our pattern
language looks like this.
We use the wrapper facade pattern in order
to be able to provide a portability veneer
on top of whatever operating system
platform we happen to want to run on, be
it different versions of WIndows,
different versions of Unix, different real
time operating systems and so on and so
forth.
We then apply the reactor pattern in order
to be able to handle the arrival of events
from multiple sources of events.
Multiple clients, connection events, data
events, and so on and so forth.
And then we apply the acceptor connector
pattern in order to be able to decouple
the event arrival from the connection
establishment logic.
These service initialization logic and
finally a logic of actually processing the
various types of HTTP requests that are
send from clients to the server.
This particular solution is very straight
forward its going to be reasonably east to
implement it's reactive.
Unfortunately, as we'll see it's not
particularly scalable and that's because
there's only one thread of control that's
running.
And so all the different clients have to
be multiplexed and queued up behind that
one thread.
Which could become a bottleneck, obviously
in a large scale production environment.
The next path through the pattern language
we'll explore, keeps the wrapper facade,
reactor, and acceptor connector patterns,
but then it adds a couple of more
patterns.
It adds component configurator, to make it
possible to be able to dynamically
configure.
The choice of particular implementation
details for our web server, at late
binding time, at installation time, or
even at run time.
And we can do this for a whole variety of
different purposes, we could add different
services.
We could change cashing protocols, and so
on and so forth.
And then we're also going to apply
something called the activator pattern.
Which is not in the POSTA2 book, but is a
pattern that is closely related to the
patterns in the host 2 book and we'll use
the activator pattern in order to launch
the web server process on demand when
client requests come along.
So this solution is still fairly simple,
it's reactive, it's more flexible because
we can do late binding of the
implementation details of our server.
And by using activator, it allows use to
have coarse grain scalability, basically,
process per request.
The next approach we're going to apply is
going to keep wrapper facade, reactor, and
acceptor connector.
But now we're going to add in the active
object pattern.
And we're going to use this in order to
have a pool of threads that we can run so
that each connection that comes in will
have one thread dedicated to that
connection.
By doing this, we keep some of the
benefits from before.
It's, it's still fairly simple to develop.
We now have multithreaded concurrency and
we'll also be able to get a finer level
granularity of scalability by using.
The thread per connection approach we'll
see as we go forward, forward though.
That thread per connection does have some
limitations.
If you have lots and lots of clients that
are pounding away on your server.
Allocating a thread per connection can
become prohibitively expensive, with
respect to resources allocated in the
operating system.
And unless you're willing to go out and
dedicate a lot of memory.
And a lot of horsepower from a processing
point of view.
You might not want to use thread per
connection in all circumstances.
So for situations where that doesn't
apply, we'll then talk about yet another
path through our pattern language design
space.
This path will use wrapper facade,
reactor, and acceptor connector, as we've
done before.
But now we're going to apply a number of
other patterns to process requests.
We'll use the monitor object in order to
be able to synchronize access to a thread
safe queue of requests that sit between
the reactive portion and the various
active object portions running the
separate threads.
And then we'll also get a chance to
explore a number of synchronization
patterns.
Things like strategized locking, scoped
locking, thread safe interface and so on
in order to make it easier to synchronize
access under the various conditions in
which we're applying our web server
solution.
This approach is concurrent much more
nicely scalable in, in bounded scalability
tends to work better in, under heavy loads
for example, The downside is that it's a
little bit less predictable, because
you're allocating memory, you're passing
memory between different threads, there's
synchronization overhead, context
switching overhead, data movement
overhead, and so on.
And so in some situations, especially for
small request, this might not be the right
Way to do the web server concurrency
architecture to address that issue of
course we'll apply another set of patterns
in our pattern language design space.
In this particular case, we're going to
keep the wrapper facade but now we're
going to skip over reactor.
And instead apply something called the
leader followers pattern which is
essentially a more powerful, a more tight
threaded reactor that allows a pool of
threads to take turns getting the next
request from a set of end points of
request input.
And that this particular approach compared
to the previous approach tends to be more
efficient and more predictable because
there's less context switching,
synchronization, and data movement.
And you also if you play your cards right,
don't need as much dynamic memory
allocation.
The thread in which the message is
received is the thread in which the
message is processed.
We'll still continue to use acceptor
connector with this pattern and other
things will look very much the same, but
it'll have other properties.
It'll be more predictable than
Half-Sync/Half-Async.
Then we'll take yet another path through
our pattern language.
This time, we're going to be exploring the
space of Asynchronous I/O.
We'll keep using wrapper facade to get our
portability, but now we're going to be
applying something called the Proactor.
The proactor pattern is a pattern that
allows operations to be invoked
asynchronously and is also operations
complete than the proactor will dispatch
the completion of the operations just so
called Completion Event Handlers.
And they are responsible for figuring out
what happened and then doing the next
thing which usually involves spotting
additional asynchronous operations, when
we talk about proactor we'll also talk
about, but asynchronous completion token
which is a pattern that's used to very
efficiently demultiplex event completion
with event completion handlers.
This particular approach is concurrent,
asynchronous, fairly simple to implement
once you have the implementation framework
for proactor, it's very scalable on
operating systems that support
Asynchronous I/O.
But unfortunately, not all operating
systems support these capabilities across
the board.
Windows tends to support them very well.
Some versions of UNIX do.
Other operating systems tend not to.
So there's some portability issues with
this particular path through our pattern
language.
So, to summarize this section.
The pattern language that we'll be
discussing here will allow us to be able
to navigate through the design
alternatives in a systematic way.
It'll help us to document what we do.
It'll help us to explain to other people
the reasons why we chose certain paths
through the design space.
And we're fortunate that most of the
patterns that we're describing here have
direct corollary framework realizations in
the adaptive communication environment in
ACE.
And that will make it very simple for us
to take the patterns and implement them in
a reasonable way, based on the open source
capabilities and frameworks and wrapper
facades and other components in ACE.
And that will allow us to be able to build
JAWS, which is our web server, out of
reasonable pieces, that are open source,
that are pattern oriented, that have
direct realization in frameworks that
codify the design principles and pattern
languages.
Take a look at this URL to find out more
information about ACE.