[MUSIC]
We're going to start our discussion
of deploying to the cloud by
talking about platform as a service.
And specifically Google App Engine, which
is one of the most popular platform as
a service sets of infrastructure
that you can deploy your app to.
So, when you deploy your app to the cloud,
there are a number of common things
that you need to be successful and
to be able to manage and monitor and
maintain your application.
So the first one is, of course, you
need some web container to run your app.
So, you need a web container, and
you'll have your app inside of it.
So you need somewhere
that your app can live.
Someone who will run
that web container for
you and he can keep it up in the cloud.
Another thing that you typically need,
particularly if you're going to have lots
of different instances of your app
running, is you need a load balancer.
So, something to receive
the incoming request.
And look at the traffic.
So maybe you have other instances
of either containers or
your app on different machines.
And the load balancer can decide which
one should receive a particular request.
So, load balancing can be a critical
component of deploying your
application in the cloud.
You often typically also,
as we've seen with spring data,
need a database to go and
store your data into.
So, if you're using Spring Data,
you may be using a,
a database that's uses Spring Data JPA.
Or you may be using another
API to get access to it,
as we've seen with MongoDB or
Amazon's DynamoDB.
So database is typically
another consideration.
Inevitably, of course, when we
deploy our application to the cloud,
we begin to realize that we
have bugs of some sort, or
we need to monitor our
application over time.
So, we'll need some type of logs or
a monitoring facility
to be able to see what's happening
with our applications and
watch and see if we've introduced
bugs that we didn't know about, or
if it's not performing as well
as we thought that it would.
So all of these are typically, you know,
critical ingredients to actually going and
deploying to the cloud.
Now, one of the beautiful things
about Google App Engine is,
is that it provides all of
this infrastructure for you.
And it also allows you to set
it up with one simple, tool.
So, Google App Engine has a deployment
tool so that you can go and
take your app and easily get it
into all of this infrastructure.
So with their deployment tool, you can
literally do things like to run an update
command and Google will push
your application into the cloud
and manage the setup of all of these
other pieces of infrastructure.
It'll automatically get your
app into that container.
Get that container running and
then connect it to all of the other
things that it needs to know about.
One of the other nice things about
Google's infrastructure is that
as your load grows on your container,
on your particular app,
Google will automatically
spin up new instances.
It'll automatically begin running
your application on more and
more machines in order to increase
the amount of load that it can take.
And that also may require increasing
load balance in infrastructure or not.
But it will automatically take care
of that auto scaling capability to
make sure that there's enough
infrastructure provision for
your application to be able to support
the load that it's currently seeing.
And at the same time, when that load
goes away, Google App Engine will
automatically shrink the infrastructure
that's dedicated and allocated to your
application in order to reduce the cost
that you're incurring due to that load.
So, Google provides a very nice,
all-in-one package to building a cloud
based application and running it and
monitoring it very easily.
Google's App Engine provides a,
a number of fantastic facilities for
deploying to the cloud, but
as with any technology, there are pros and
cons to using Google App Engine.
So let's take a little bit to talk
about what the pros and cons are.
So, the things that you need to be aware
of and the things that can potentially
hurt you down the road if you're not
aware of them and don't plan accordingly.
On the pro side, we've already seen it's
an all in one platform as a service.
So it gives you just
about every facility from
day to days to sending email
that you could possibly want.
It simplifies management.
So, and deployment, so you can easily
get your application up in to the cloud.
It auto-scales it, so
that you're only paying for
what you need, and it also sets up
a lot of the supporting infrastructure,
in particular the database that you
need access to, and scales that for you.
So, there's certainly a lot
of wonderful pros here.
Oh, and, and the last one that I should
also mention is it provides development
tools like plugins for Eclipse that
can help you get started and up and
running faster with your application.
Some of the cons are, even though Google
has done a great job of trying to use Java
based standards like Servlets and other
things to provide the API for App Engine,
it's still possible, in many cases,
to end up using their proprietary APIs.
So, for example,
if you want to store a file,
you can't do that on App Engine
due to security restrictions.
You can't just save a file
to disk on App Engine.
Now, with Google's newer Compute Engine,
which is more like infrastructure as
a service and it's possible to run
Google App Engine facilities on
top of Google Compute Engine, you can
begin doing some of these things, but
I'm going to talk about
just Google App Engine,
in which case you can't do
these things as easily.
So, one of the cons is if you begin
using things like the Blobstore,
which you would in many cases use in lieu
of storing data locally on the disc.
The Blobstore is equivalent of Amazon S3,
so if you begin using that,
you end up with proprietary APIs
potentially which would make
it hard for you to be able to
run your application elsewhere.
Another challenge is,
is that although Google has done a good
job of using Java standards, is that many
of the standards that they use are older.
So they have, for example,
an older servlet API as of
the time of this video, and
that can impact you in a number of ways.
One of the ways that that
impacts you is out of the box,
Spring Boot can not run
on Google App Engine.
You have to go and do a little bit
more work to make Spring Boot run.
One of those things is you have to create
a web.xml file, that then uses some,
infrastructure in a package called Spring
Boot Legacy to actually get Spring Boot
running, and
many of the wonderful Spring Data and
other libraries that we've used are harder
to get up and running on App Engine.
Because technically, they'll, they'll
depend on the latest, greatest stuff.
And some of these aren't
necessarily in App Engine, or
are hard to get configured
properly in App Engine.
And the example that we're providing in
the repository, we've actually not used
JPA, which is what we've used throughout
the course, and we've not used Gradle,
because Gradle and JPA we've found have
not been supported as well in App Engine.
So we've instead provided examples
that are using the things that
we feel are the best support in
an App Engine, which is Maven.
Which is an alternate build system,
but very closely related to Grail.
And then JDO, which is in
the Java Data Objects standard,
which is different from JPA,
but also an excellent standard.
But not exactly the same.
So, one of the things you run into is,
because you are running on
platform based service, you are restricted
to what versions of libraries or
what libraries they support and
how well they support them,
that you may not be able to use
exactly the tools that you want.
So in this case, Spring Boot doesn't
necessarily fit very well in App Engine.
One of the other challenges that
you can run into is the unique
scaling model on App Engine.
So, App Engine is very efficient and
does a great job of
trying to aggressively shut down
your unneeded application instances.
But what that means is, is that when
a request comes in, Google App Engine may,
on demand, start a new instance of
your container and your application,
that has to fully be launched before that
app, that, that, request can be processed.
Now, when we've been building
applications so far, we've been,
been building them under the assumption,
that the start up cost wasn't something or
the configuration cost wasn't
something that we really cared about.
We just wanted to get the application
running and then we assumed that once it
was running, it would stay running for
a long period of time.
And so that the start up or
configuration cost wasn't something
that we really cared about.
On Google App Engine it matters.
Because since App Engine may
spin up your instance just in
time to receive a particular request, it
means that if you have a long start up or
configuration time, it can hurt your
ability to scale on App Engine and
hurt your perceived
responsiveness to clients.
So in those first requests,
when a new instance is being spun up,
you may have clients that see poor
performance because their requests aren't
being served while this infrastructure
is spinning up and configuring itself.
And particular, with Spring,
all of the APT components scan type work,
where Spring automatically
searches through your class path
to try to find the components it needs and
wire them together.
That can be problematic.
If you explicitly declare
things as beings in your
configuration file that's
not a big problem.
But if you go and
scan large parts of the class path,
that can be problematic on
App Engine if you're using Spring.
So you have to be aware of that.
So, these are some of the key pros and
cons that you should think about when
deciding that Google App Engine
is right for your application.
It's a wonderful platform but
it always, as any technology warrants,
understanding the cons, so
that you don't go down a path too far and
realize there's something that you
need that you can't get there.
One other final parting thing is
that you need to use anything in
particular on the underlying host,
like you need to install a native library.
Or you need to have some other supporting
service that you access directly on that
host, like Open CD,
if you want to do computer vision.
You can't do that directly
in Google App Engine.
You need to go look for something that's
more infrastructure's the service,
like Google Compute Cloud, or
Amazon's web services and EC2.