[MUSIC]
Now that we've walked
through this application,
let's actually look at deploying it
to the cloud in Google App Engine.
And the tools that are available up
to us to monitor the application,
the infrastructure support.
That we can use and, and look at,
once it's actually up and
running inside of the cloud.
So the first thing we're going to do, is
we're going to use the palm file to go and
run one of Google App Engine's tools that
it provides, to upload it to the cloud.
So we're going to run
the app engine update target.
That's in our maven build,
and what this is going to do,
is it's going to go and
build our application, package it,
and then use Google's tools,
to automatically upload it to the cloud.
As we can see, it tells us that it's
deploying a new version to the cloud.
Right now.
And in a second this will be completely
uploaded to Google servers, and running.
So, this build is finished.
It's finished our,
uploading our application in the cloud and
now we can go, to the Google App Engine
console, to look at our application and
see some information about it.
One of the first things that's worth doing
is going and looking at the versions.
The screen.
And what this shows us is we can see
that we just deployed version 0-1.
Which, if you remember,
in our App Engine web file.
The version tag, which we used right here,
that's what it's referring to.
So every time we change this tag,
that will be
trapped in the versions on the versions
screen, of the App Engine console.
We can also decide that we want to go and
look at this version by clicking on
a link, and it will load this version up.
And you can see that it's taking
a little while to start our application.
But, in a minute,
it will pull up the application, and
we would have access to it.
We can also go and
make this the default inset.
So one of the nice things is is that,
we can control which of the versions
is actually receiving, the request.
So now that this other version is up,
we can go, for
example, and hit the slash video.
URL, and
in a second here when it finishes loading,
we'll probably get an error related to
one or more well, actually we, it worked.
So we got a list of the videos,
and currently there are no videos.
Now, if we had multiple versions and
we wanted one of them to
receive all of the traffic.
We could use the Make Default
button to set the version that we
wanted to be receiving the traffic.
So one of the nice things is we
can deploy different versions, and
then once we've deployed a new version,
we can test it first before we
actually go and switch over.
So for example,
if we wanted to update the version to 1-1.
We could then, rerun the build.
So we're going to do
App Engine update again.
We could rerun that.
And, the App Engine tools
are going to be used to
automatically upload our new application.
Two ap and gen and
increment the version for us.
Now we'll go back and check back on
this in a second to see, the result.
We have another a, a,
a number of other interesting things
some of which we won't go into.
Like Cron jobs and Task Queues.
Another important thing that
we have is access to Logs.
So we can go and look at and
see the requests that are coming into all
of our instances across Google's cloud.
So in this case we can see, our request
to slash a video that we sent out
a minute ago, and we can see some warnings
that are here that may be helpful to us.
For example, in this case we can
see a series of warnings related to
our request slash video, and but
potentially warnings related to just
the startup of our application.
We can also see time.
So we can see that our very first request,
took quite a long time.
It took almost ten seconds to startup.
The instance and startup spring, so
this is, we can also see our second
request also took, 8 seconds.
We went back and
we refreshed this, it should be a lot
faster, nearly instantaneous, and
then if we refresh the logs, we'll see the
second request took only 47 milliseconds.
Hm.
So this is that, that thing that I talked
about that you have to be aware of,
and that is.
When App Engine goes and
starts up a new instance of your
application it can take a long time.
In this case it took over 8 seconds, but
then the subsequent request
only took 47 milliseconds.
So, you have to be aware that app engine
starts up application instances on
demand and that can affect performance.
We can also look at the data store.
And, we've not actually created
anything of interest yet.
We haven't stored any data.
But if we wi, begin storing actual
individual videos, we could go and
look at the data store, and
look at what we've stored in it.
One of the other nice
capabilities is we can see.
How much, of Google's resources we're
using and very quickly calculate our bill.
So this shows us, all of
the information about our application.
So, we've sent a total of four
requests to this application.
And we've used up very little
of our quota on various things.
We've used up a little bit of the.
The code and static file storage.
But, overall we haven't used u a lot
of the resources available to us.
And this resource page also
gives you an idea of the breadth
of capabilities available to
you on Google App Engine.
There are number of other features of
App Engine that we're not
going to go into [COUGH].
Things like the Blobstore or
full text search.
All of these are really powerful
capabilities, that are hard to set up and
maintain and scale properly on your own.
So having a platform as a service that
bundles all of these things together for
you, can be really powerful.
Even something as simple as capturing
all the log data across all of your
application instances, and providing one
centralized console for you to view it.
Is a huge time saver.
You, there are other ways to do this
on your own, you can use things like
Logstash, which is a fantastic tool, for
capturing logs from Java applications and
other applications and Graphite to
view those logs in a web-based format.
But, not having to set those up
yourselves and maintain them, is a,
is a significant time saver when you're
using something like Google App Engine.
If we go back and
look at the versions again, we'll see
that we've deployed our new 1-1 version.
It's not currently the default
being used to serve traffic.
And if we wanted to go and swap over,
after we had tested our new version, and
make it the default,
we'd just swap it over.
So, Google has really thought through
a lot of the, the features that you need
as a developer, to maintain and
manage a very complex application,
that's running on distributed
infrastructure, in Google's cloud.
And they provide a really nice.
simplified, unified interface to all
of these really powerful capabilities,
in their platform as a service.
So, if your a single developer and
you can fit your application within the
constraints that they, they in place on it
to run in their platform,
you can take advantage of significant.
Time and complexity and, and,
and operation effort savings.
That, that, that are really substantial.
So, if you can use,
an App Engine like model for
your application, and if your libraries
and other things that you want to use,
fit into their model, it's a,
a significant time saver.
When you're actually going and
trying to run and
maintain a very complicated application.
There are lots of other great platforms
as a service, there are things like
Kuroko Amazon has Elastic Beanstalk, lots
of fantastic infrastructures as service,
platform, I mean, platform as a service
providers, that you can go and
use, and so it's definitely worth
taking an advantage of them.
We've given you a taste of Google App
Engine, and its platform as a service.
But there are lots of others that
provide similar capabilities.
And platform as a service
simplifies your operations and
deployment as a, a single developer or
a small company.
So that's one of the great advantages
of platform as a service is.
Simplifying all of these complex
deployment and operational aspects,
of running a cloud in
someone else's data center.