[MUSIC]
Now that we have a basic understanding
of the infrastructure provided by
Google's platform as a service called
App Engine, let's take a look at
a specific application that uses
Spring on Google App Engine.
But rather than using JPA, the database
standard that we've been using,
we'll use JDO.
So let's dive right in here and
look at some of the code for
this example that's now in the repository.
If you'll take a look underneath the,
source video, the video source
service app in JDO, project, you'll see
a number of familiar things very quickly.
The first one is an application class.
And this is just like we've doing
with other spring based applications.
So in this example, we have a class
that still exten, extends WebMvc.
Configure adapter is still using the
various annotations like at EnableWebMvc.
But one of the differences
that you'll notice,
is that before we were using a main
method to boot strap Spring.
Now in this example,
we're no longer doing that.
Instead, we are just using
this application class
as a configuration object for
our overall application.
So it's not being used to kick off
an embedded servlet container anymore.
It's not being used to kick off Tomcat or
Jetty.
Instead, it's just providing configur,
configuration information here, so
we could have one or more embedded
beans inside of this application.
But we couldn't for example, have the
beans that we previously had that would
configure SSA, SSL on Tomcat,
so that we could do https.
But it still gives us all
the configuration capabilities.
Now, as I mentioned earlier, this App
Engine Project has to have a web.xml file.
And this is because App Engine
uses an older Servlet API standard
that doesn't support some of the automatic
bootstrapping stuff that we've been
doing with Spring Boot.
So if you'll go down into the source,
main, web app, web amp folder, you'll
recognize the web.xml file that we talked
about in earlier examples with Servelts.
And we have to have one of these files
here when we're running on App Engine.
And basically, what we use it to do is to
bootstrap Spring, and get Spring launched
so it can go and look at our application
class and load it as the configuration.
So let me show you how
we go about doing that.
The first thing we're going to do is we're
going to take a look down at the bottom
and see the things that
we're more familiar with.
So we see that we're declaring a server,
a Servlet and
we're declaring it to be
of type dispatcher Servlet.
So this is the same dispatcher Servlet
that we walked about early on when we
began introducing Spring is, rather
than automatically having Spring Boot
set up the dispatcher Servlet, we're
providing a web.xml file that is telling
the Servlet container to go and create
an instance of the dispatcher Servlet.
Then a little farther down,
we're taking that dispatcher Servlet and
we're mapping it so
that it will handle all requests.
So what we're doing here is, we're doing
what Spring Boot normally does for
us automatically.
It automatically creates
the dispatcher Servlet for us.
It automatically loads it
into the Servlet container.
It normally does all of this for us.
But because the Servlet API
is an older version,
it can't do that automatically anymore.
So we have to do a little bit of
manual work to bootstrap this,
this spring based application
that we're developing.
Now, the good thing is is that almost all
of this code is reusable and boiler plate.
And you could just copy it over another
project as long as you get the,
any of your specific code, as long
as you update the package names and
class names appropriately,
you can reuse this over and over.
Now we have the other interesting
files that we should look at,
is this AppEngine-web.xml file.
And this provides some information
that App Engine needs to
know about your application.
Now, you can put all kinds
of different things in here,
but one of the most important
things that needs to go in
here is the application
identifier that you are given.
So, when you go and create
an application on Google App Engine,
it will require you to create
an identifier for your application.
And, once you've created that application
and you've gotten that identifier,
you need to make sure that it shows up
in your appengine-web.xml file and then
you can specify some version information,
which in this case we're just saying 0-1.
But you can provide sort of arbitrary
versions and naming, which is another nice
feature of App Engine is that it will
track these versions as you deploy them.
Now, all of that's a little bit more work,
but it's not sufficient,
significantly different from
what we've done in the past.
If we go and look at our video service and
the video service API, it's still
roughly the same as we saw before.
We have a series of Spring Request
Mappings that are mapping down
to methods of a controller.
So we have our original
controller methods for
saving a video, for listing the videos,
and for finding videos by name.
So the controller, from its perspective,
is pretty much the same.
There's nothing really that
changes on Google App Engine.
Now, we're providing still
a repository-like interface where
we have a vo, video repository.
But it you go and open up the video
repository, you'll see that
it's not actually
a Spring Data repository.
It is a repository that we've
created to look like Spring Data.
In particular, rather than being
an interface, we've created a class
that extends this other class called
JDO crud repository that we've created.
And all we've done is try
to make our class look like
the spring data repositories.
Now, we are actually providing
100% of the implementation here.
We're not getting the,
the benefit of Spring Data automatically
creating our repositories for us.
But, we are preserving that sort of
consistent interface that we used before.
So let's take a look inside of the JDO
crud repository and how we use JDO.
If we want to save an object, and in
this case we just have a generic method,
where we've used Java Generics
to parametize this method so
we can parametize it for a video or for
another thing, just like we did before.
So if you'll look up, we always had to
provide the type that we were saving,
in this case, T.
And then the ID type, just like we
did with Spring Data repositories.
And these methods have actually
been primarily copied over
from the crud repository in Spring Data.
We've just provided
implementations of them in JDO.
So, for example, if we want to
save an instance, an instance, we,
have to get an instance of the persistence
manager, when she is responsible for
saving objects to the datastore and
loading them from the datastore.
We can go and
look at this PMF class and we'll see
it's basically a sys, a singleton,
to hold on to a single instance of
the persistence manager factory.
And this is just boiler plate code
that you will see in most JDO based
Google App Engine Projects.
You will need a, typically have a PMF
class that has a Singleton instance
of the persistence manager factory
which you use then as we do in
this JDO crud repository to get
persistence managers from the factory.
And once you have a persistence manager,
in order to save an object,
all you have to do is say make persistent.
And assuming that your
objects that you're saving,
is of a class that's annotated with the
appropriate annotations for persistence,
then the persistence manager will
automatically store it in the database.
Similarly, we can go and
do things like look up an instance
of an object by it's identifier.
So again, we get the persistence manager.
And then to look up an object, we say get
object by ID and we pass in the type of
the object, which in this case for
the video repository would be video.class.
And then we pass in the ID of the object,
which in this case would be a long, which
is the unique ID of that particular video.
We can also go and do queries on objects,
like we did with the find
examples in Spring Data.
So for example, if we wanted to create a,
the equivalent of find by name and
actually produce
the implementation ourselves,
we create a persistence manager and
then we create a new query with that
persistence manager across
all the video objects.
So here, we're saying create
a persistence manager, create a query
across all of the video objects that
have been stored in the database.
And then we add a series
of filters to the query.
So we say we only care about the,
the objects where the name
member variable is equal to this
value N that we're going to provide.
And then we declare that
N is a String Parameter.
Now, what, the reason that we're having
to go through this work step by step in
constructing this query,
is that we're trying,
that we're using the infrastructure
to avoid an, a SQL injection attack.
So if we, for example, just appended
the name that we're searching for
to the end of the string, we would leave
ourselves open to a SQL injection attack.
So instead, we create the query and
we have a place holder for
the value we want, which is N.
And in the next line, we declare
that the variable N in our query,
in our filter, is of type string.
And then when we go down and
execute the query and pass in the name,
the underlying JDO implementation
can properly escape the name and
make sure that we are not susceptible
to an SQL injection attack.
So, the, the use of JDO,
we can provide a interface that still
looks like the Spring Data repositories.
Yet rather than having Spring
automatically create the implementation or
provide the implementation
of the repository for us,
we can just provide our own implementation
of the various methods that we want.
And if you go and look through the JDO
crud repository, you'll very quickly see
how you go about querying the repository,
saving object and deleting objects.
It's all fairly self explanatory.
And examples are, in the JDO crud
repository for all the common operations.
So now let's take a look at
the video object and how we change
the annotations on it, just like when
we did when we changed the Mongo DB and
when we change to Dynamo DB, we have
to change the annotations of the video
object, in order to make it persistable in
Google App Engine's big table with JDO.
The first thing we have to do is add
app persistence capable to the class.
And this basically flags to JDO that
we intend to store this
class in the database.
We then have to define a primary
key just like we did before.
In this case, we are defining a primary
key and we are saying that we want it
to automatically be generated and
provided by the database infrastructure.
So when we save a video, we want
the database to create the primary key for
us and assign it to this member variable.
This is the same thing that
we did in JPA over and over.
We're just using a different set of
annotations to make this happen.
We also have to do one other things, and
that's for each of the member
variables that we want to persist.
We have to add the at persistent
annotation to that member variable, so
that JDO knows to go and
look for that particular member
variable and save it in the database.
Similarly, when we load to the,
the object or
the video out of the database, it needs
to know when should should the member
variables be populated with
the data that are there.
So that's the basics of
an App Engine Project.
We've switched over to JDO
rather than JPA, and it,
it still provides us
the same capabilities.
There's some variations in JDO versus
JPA and some people prefer JDO,
some people prefer JPA.
But they give us both the, they both
give us the same basic capabilities.
And we can still do things like have a
repository like interface that looks like
Spring Data even if it isn't directly
Spring Data, in order to isolate our
code from the underlying database logic,
and provide some ability to change to
different repository implementations,
if we try to, to, to move away from JDO.
We still have an application class,
although it doesn't have a main method.
And one of the biggest pieces of work
that we have to do is we have to
have a web.xml file to load
our dispatcher Servlet,
which Spring Boot did automatically for
us in the past.
[COUGH] So we can see that
Google App Engine, because of
being a platform as a service, and some
restrictions in the libraries that it has,
it makes us change our
application a little bit.
But we still have the same
basic capabilities and
we get a lot of other infrastructure
to support us on App Engine.