Welcome to part one of the module that
describes patterns and frameworks for
service access and communication.
In this part of the module, we're going to
summarize many of the accidental
complexities.
That are associated with the sockets API.
If you go back to section one of the
course, we have a whole module that
describes operating system programming
mechanisms.
And there's further discussion about the
various capabilities in sockets.
We'll start with a brief recap.
And then we'll give a critique of some of
the limitations and accidental
complexities associated with the sockets
API.
Sockets were originally developed as a sea
level programming interface to the TCPIP
protocol suite in so called BSD UNIX.
And, even though we're going to provide a
somewhat thorough critique of the sockets
API.
I want to emphasize.
[inaudible].
That sockets played a transformational
role in allowing the internet revolution
to occur.
If we hadn't had a way to program TCPIP,
as conveniently and as portably and
ubiquitously as sockets.
We might not have many of the things we
take for granted today.
As proof of this, sockets are available on
almost all operating system platforms
today.
The socket API has roughly two dozen or so
functions in it, give or take as, as more
sophisticated protocol capabilities have
come online, things like IP version six,
the API has expanded a little bit but
those are the basic Two dozen or so
methods that we'll, we'll see.
You can take a look at this URL to find
out more information about the socket API,
and there's lots of good books on the
subject as well.
A socket, is essentially an end point of
communication.
What that means is it's a, a user level
integer, or handle of some kind, sometimes
implemented as a pointer on some
platforms.
It provides Access into some kernel
maintained data structures and those data
structures keep track of the state of the
protocol machine like buffer information
that goes in and out of the protocol stack
and are used to set various options and
other mechanisms to control the way in
which the protocols work and communicate
between various end points.
Most commonly, a socket can be bound to
local and remote addresses.
We do this in order to be able to
communicate via protocols like TCPIP using
port numbers and IP addresses.
And we also typically use sockets as a way
to carry out some kind of reliable
bidirectional byte stream communication
between senders and receivers.
So for example, if you go to my website,
you'll be using sockets typically in your
browser and those'll be accessing sockets
running somewhere, in the cloud, in the
web server, in the data center that serves
the web pages for my, my home site.
With those details as background, now
let's go ahead and kind of look carefully
at what's going on with sockets.
There are lots and lots of accidental
complexities in this particular
programming interface.
One of the main problems is it's not very
well structured, it's not very uniform,
and it's not very portable, even though
its widely available on different
operating platforms.
[inaudible].
Some of the issues here are the, the API,
itself, is rather linear.
It's not hierarchical.
It's hard to tell by looking at the list
of two dozen functions.
Which ones play which roles in connection
establishment, passively or actively.
Which one played different roles in terms
of communication, once things are
connected.
There's not even really any consistency
with the names.
There's no common prefix, for example, to
tell at a glance.
This function is part of the sockets
interface.
Some other problems.
It's not very portable and it's also error
prone in addition.
The function names and semantics tend to
differ on different platforms.
For example on POSIX platforms, send and
receive can be used both for file IO and
socket, network IO.
On Windows it can only be used for the
network IO, not the file IO.
You have to use different calls for that.
Likewise some old versions of real time
operating systems Were a little quirky and
if you didn't pass in an actual address
parameter to the accept call, they would
crash.
On more civilized operating systems like
Windows and Linux and Unix you don't have
to worry about that.
It'll, it'll handle that case correctly.
Some other problems, there's issues with
the way which we represent socket handles.
Sometimes, on some platforms, they're
represented as integers.
On other platforms they're represented as
pointers.
This can be confusing this can be
non-portable.
And one of the other challenges you
sometimes run in to is that different
platforms put different socket functions
and data structures in different header
files which means you have portability
issues to work around.
There are yet some other problems.
There's issues of type safety because
we're using these low level I/O handles
like pointers or ints, these issues where
the compiler can't tell you at compile
time that you're using various functions
in the wrong way.
For example, there's nothing to stop you
from trying to make an accept call On a
data mode socket.
Likewise, there's nothing to try to stop
you from doing a read or a write call on a
listen mode socket.
Bot of which are incorrect.
But your compiler can't catch that at
compile time.
There's also a fairly steep learning curve
to try to make sense out of the APIs.
There's a bunch of different capabilities
for address families, and protocol
families.
They're fairly consistent in terms of
always going together but you have to keep
in mind which world you're dealing with
them.
Am I dealing with a protocol?
Am I dealing with an address family and
it's complicated and error prone?
Another set of problems arise when you
start to use some of the options for less
frequently accessed functions, things like
multitasking Broadcasting, asynchronous
I/O, nonblocking I/O, urgent data
delivery, these are confusing, they use
ioctal and various socket option
parameters, they're not very portable,
hard to understand and so on.
There's a lot more of other very
low-level, tedious and error-prone Prone
details.
Forgetting to set the port numbers in to
network byte order is a common one.
Forgetting to zero out a socket outer
address structure before you use it in a
bind call or connect call is another
problem.
Omitting.
Calling certain functions, like forgetting
to call listen before you try to call
accept.
Having mismatches between the protocol and
address families because they're decoupled
and separated in terms of their API
capabilities.
These are all very common problems with
sockets.
To make this a little bit more concrete,
let me give you some examples of problems
I've run across when writing sockets over
the years.
Most of these problems, by the way, will
not be detected by your compiler.
So here's a little piece of code, it's,
it's an echo server example.
There can be differences in header files,
they might not all occur in the same
place, so you'll have to deal with
ifdefing them somehow.
It's easy to forget to zero out the socket
address structure.
In which case, you'll have little garbage
values in the[UNKNOWN] portions between
the fields and the structure, which will
cause various problems.
Here we're using a non-portable data type,
we're using and ent, which won't work on
Windows because sockets aren't really ents
on Windows platform.
Here's a case where we're making a call to
the factory function socket But we're
passing in socket D gram instead of the
sock stream that we intended to use.
We're now using a check for a non-portable
error return value.
Checking to see whether the result back
was minus 1, which is incorrect.
We have a mismatch between the protocol
and the address family.
We use.
The protocol family of UNIX domain but the
address family of the internet domain.
That will be caught by the compiler.
We may have the, the port number on the
wrong byte order depending on what kind of
hardware platform we're running on.
In this particular case, we forgot to zero
out the address structure and now we're
passing it to bind which will cause all
kinds of strange behaviors.
We forgot to call the listen function call
before we call accept.
We're calling accept on a socket that's
been set into the, the sock_dgram
communication type, which is very
confusing and subtle.
We're ending up reading from the wrong
handle here.
We want to be reading from a data mode
handle.
But instead, we're reading from a listen
mode handle.
And the final problem here is that there
is no guarantee that n bytes will be
written when we do a write operation due
to the issues of short writes and short
reads.
So, how do I know all these problems?
Because, after many years of programming
at the socket API in C, I probably
stumbled upon each of these at least once
and along they way it convinced me there
must be a better way to Program.
So to summarize this particular part of
the module, the native socket API has a
number of problems.
It's tedious, it's error prone, it's not
portable.
It's not very uniform, which means there's
more work for you as a developer.
These analysis we're doing here, have
focused on sockets, because that's the
emphasis of the course, which is on
communication.
But, but be aware that you can apply more
or less the same critique to, To many,
many other parts of native operating
system APIs written in C.
The process and thread management
portions, the dynamic linking portions,
various things having to do with memory
management and virtual memory management,
other types of IPC mechanisms, and so
forth and so on.
If you take a look at the URL at the
bottom of the slide Here's an article I
wrote about over 20 years ago, describing
some of these issues.
And they're still relevant today.
One of the main thing that's happened over
time is that people have begun to use
higher level languages.
And higher level abstractions like
middleware, to abstract away from lots of
these issues.
And that's a good thing because it puts us
in much a better shape.
To write concurrent and network software.
That will be correct, easier to maintain,
and easier to port to different platforms.