Hello.
And welcome to Part Two in the module that
talks about patterns and frameworks for
service access and communication.
In the previous part of this module, we
summarized some of the accidental
complexities with the C-level socket API.
In this part of the module we're going to
describe how the Wrapper Facade pattern
can help to alleviate these accidental
complexities.
So what's the problem?
If we're trying to build a web server or
any other kind of networked application we
often have to access very, various
operating system services.
Services for communication, both local and
remote communication, concurrency, both
processes and threads, synchronization.
Various kinds of memory management, and so
on, and file access.
The problem here is that programming
directly to the low level operating system
interfaces exposed by the OS, written in
C, usually, is a tedious and error prone
and non portable ordeal.
So, how are we going to get around this?
We're going to be applying the Wrapper
Facade pattern.
To avoid having to access these low-level
APIs directly.
The wrapper facade pattern encapsulates
the data and functions provided by the
existing C APIs with more concise, more
robust, portable, maintainable, and more
cohesive object-oriented classes.
Take a look at the interface that's shown
down here.
The structure was shown.
You'll see that, rather than accessing the
functions directly, which is the classic
way we would do things.
Instead, we have our applications, our web
server accessing those functions through a
class wrapper facade.
And that wrapper facade exposes a number
of different methods.
And those methods then access the low
level functions.
But they do it in a way that won't expose
those details, and the accidental
complexities of using the c level API's
directly to the application code.
If you take a look at the dynamic
interactions.
If you're a client, if you're a webserver
for example.
And you invoke an operation on
the[UNKNOWN] facade.
Then under the hood, it turns around and
makes a call to one or more system
functions to do its job.
And it would typically stash away whatever
data types have to be passed to those low
level functions and keep them as part of
the private state of the wrapper facade
object.
At first glance, the structure and
dynamics of this pattern look familiar.
They look a bit like the bridge pattern,
they look a bit like The, very other
patterns from, from the Gang of Four book
like proxy but there are some important
differences.
The main difference is their typically
light weight.
There is no interaction that's going on he
would do it with bridge and there is no
conversion and transformation its going on
with proxy.
So you can keep them very thin.
And lightweight, not adding much overhead.
In fact you can often inline the wrapper
facades to make the overhead evaporate
altogether.
You can take a look at the POSA two book
for descriptions about wrapper facade.
You can also take a look at the various
ACE books for examples of how to do this
in ACE or you can take a look at this
paper listed at the bottom of the URL.
For information about wrapper facades.
So let's talk about how we might apply the
wrapper facade pattern to JAWS.
So what we'll do here is we'll use this
for any time we're going to access system
programming interfaces.
Instead of accessing them directly, we're
going to access them through the various
wrapper facades defined by the ACE
communication environment.
And just as one simple example, here's an
example of how JAWS might use the ACE
thread mutex, which is a wrapper facade
around the low-level synchronization
mechanisms for mutual exclusion that
you'll find on various operating
environments.
This one illustrates the mapping to
Solaris threads.
It's easy to do this to map it to Pozex P
threads or Windows threads or various
other kinds of mechanisms you might find
on real-time operating system environments
and so on.
(End of transcription.) In practice, JAWS
is going to use lots more stuff that we
would find in ACE.
All the other wrapper facades for other
types of OS services it encapsulates
behind an object oriented programming
interface.
So what are some of the benefits of using
wrapper facades?
Well, first and foremost, we can provide a
much more type-safe interface, rather than
to use these low level functions and low
level data that are ints, or pointers.
We can use classes with strongly typed
interfaces, which means that A lot of the
problems and, and error conditions just
disappear all together.
We can also make things more portable.
A wrapper facade is a great layer to also
abstract a way from operating system
diversity and heterogeneity.
So you don't have to be, be whole into the
particular syntactic.
Mechanisms that Windows uses verses Linux
or verses TeXWorks, you can make those
thing pluggable and commoditize the
operating system layer.
Yet another capability you get by using
Wrapper Facades is you end up with more
modular and reusable components that can
be cohesively integrated together to form
higher layer units of abstraction.
By using things like inheritance or
parameterized types to build upon the
existing capabilities.
There are of course some limitations with
the Wrapper Facade approach anytime you
try to provide a portability veneer.
Something that abstracts away from the
particulars of any particular platform or
any particular operating system you have
to be careful that you don't reduce the
capability and the functionality by
reducing certain things that aren't
available everywhere.
For example there are certain capabilities
that you have on certain platforms with
respect to certain locking mechanisms and
if you try to come up with a wrapper
facade that's the Intersection of all the
portable capabilities of all the operating
systems, then certain things, by their
very nature, would be left out.
In those cases, you might choose to do
some emulation of one synchronization
mechanism in terms of other ones that are
more portable, in order to provide a
consistent wrapper facade facility on all
the operating environments.
Another potential limitation with wrapper
facade is performance degradation.
If you're not careful and you have large,
layered calls and indirection in your
implementation, then you can take
something that looks simple and
lightweight and turn it into a heavyweight
mechanism.
Which is one reason why we typically
recommend not using patterns like proxy or
bridge.
When you're trying to build abstraction
layers.
But instead, sticking with something
lightweigth like, wrapper facade.
Yet another potential problem, programming
language and compiler limitations if your,
if your operating environment, if your
language doesn't have a way to map
conveniently and efficiently to C
functions, then wrapper facades may be
hard to, to enable.
Fortunately, almost all languages these
days have call outs to see, so you can
find ways to encapsulate the low level
services behind higher level objects and
class interfaces.