[MUSIC]
Another platform as a service that
we're going to talk about is ama,
Amazon's Elastic Beanstalk.
So Elastic Beanstalk is an interesting
platform as a service because.
It provides many of
the capabilities that we extept,
expect of a platform as a service.
So bundling together things like,
the ability to interact with the database,
the ability to automatically
deploy your application,
put it behind the load balancer
scale it up and down as needed.
But it also has some other
interesting capabilities,
because it was built on top
of Amazon Web Services.
And one of those interesting capabilities
is that you can also take control of
lower level details that you typically
can't do, on other platforms as a service.
So for example, on Amazon if you want to
deploy to your own virtual machine image,
then maybe has hardware
specific features or
has some special native libraries
that you want to access.
You can actually do that on Amazon.
We're not going to talk about that today,
but we are going to show you how you take
your Spring Boot applications and can take
them and modify them slightly so that you
can quickly upload them to Amazon Elastic
Beanstalk and have them live in the cloud.
So let's walk through an example and
see how we do this.
So, if you'll take a look at the video
service with Dynamo and DB and
Beanstalk, this is an example that's going
to use Amazon's database called Dynamo,
which is a very fast database.
As well as their Beanstalk service.
And this is an extension of the previous
Dynamo, application that we saw before.
So if you haven't gone and
set up that Dynamo application and
created the DynamoDB tables that
you'll need, for that application,
you want to go ahead and do that first
before watching this tutorial because this
tutorial assumes that you've already
set up the proper Dynamo tables.
To persist video objects.
Other than the setup, the of DynamoDB,
the key thing that's different from
the previous Spring Boot
applications that we've done,
are that we have added
a application servlet initializer.
And this is a simple class.
That you can reuse over and
over in your applications,
that instead of having the applications
main method actually go and kick off
spring with an embedded servlet container,
this simply tells a servlet container
like Tomcat that's standalone that
you're deploying this application into.
To go and launch and configure
itself using the application class.
So this is very similar to what we saw,
in previous examples where we
used the main method to kick off,
an embedded container.
In this case we've just done
something slightly different.
Since we're going to be running in
a standalone web application container.
So rather than embedding
Tomcat into our application.
We're going to package our application
into a web application resource or
WAR file.
And then deploy it into a Tomcat instance.
So in order to that,
we also have to specify a little bit of
information to help that Tomcat instance.
Bootstrap our code into itself and
into the container.
So we add this simple application servlet,
initializer class which is going to
tell Spring where our
application configuration is.
And it inherits from the Spring Boot
servlet initializer.
Which tells the web application container
to do and set up a dispatcher servlet and
some of those other things,
that we've seen in the past.
One other slight change is in
the build.gradle file and that's,
you want to make sure that you have,
provided runtime rather than compile or
something along the lines of that, for the
Spring Boot's starter Tomcat dependency.
And the reason for this is is is when you
have provided runtime rather than compile.
It tells Spring that it needs to package
your application into a WAR file.
So if you don't have this Spring
won't necessarily package your
application correctly into a WAR file.
Luckily, the Spring Boot plug in for
our gradle files will automatically build
the war file that we need in order
to go and deploy our application.
To Amazon Elastic Beanstalk.
So to do that, we're going to go ahead and
first just Delete our bill directories, so
that we can see that this is working.
And then we're going to run
the build.gradle file using
the Task Quick Launcher.
And we're going to, just going to
run the build target, or tasks.
And we'll see that this is going to go and
run.
And it was going to package all of our
application together with Spring Boot and
the needed dependencies, into a library
that's underneath the build folder.
And then you want to look in libs.
And then it's going to be the video
service Amazon Beanstalk 1.1.war.
And, you can change this to
whatever you want inside of
your build.gradle file by
simply going to baseName.
And then, changing that to something else.
And then changing the version.
So, for example, if we go and
increment our version number to 1.2,
we can simply rerun,
the Task Quick Launcher with build.
And it will go a rebuild the chart,
the WAR file for
us, using the new name inversion.
And we see that we've got the new
WAR that's been constructed.
So these WAR files are what we're going to
be deploying to Amazon Elastic Beanstalk.
Se let's switch over to Amazon's
Elastic Beanstalk's, Web console and
start the deployment process.
Amazon actually also has an entire clips
tool suite and set of command line tools,
but we're going to do everything through
the web based console, for this demo.
So, first, we're going to go
to Create a New Application.
We're going to call this
mobilecloud14_demo.
We're going to create the application,
the Environment here is we're going to
make this a web server because we're
running a web application container and
we expect this thing to receive,
HTTP requests.
For the platform we're going to
choose Tomcat which is
a Java application server, it's a web
application container that we can use.
And we're going to go ahead and,
keep the Environment type the same.
That is, it's going to have a load
balancing and autoscaling by default.
So we'll go ahead and
click through to Next.
And the next part is where we're
going to select our WAR file.
So we're going to choose the file,
and then.
Inside of our build directory lives WAR,
we're going to choose the WAR
file that we just created.
And we'll just simply hit Next, and
this is going to upload our entire
application, to Amazon Elastic Beanstalk.
So that our WAR file can
be deployed into the cloud.
We've now got a identifier for
our application and what we're going to
see is that we get this identifier
.elasticbeanstalk.com as a URL that we
can use to access, our application.
We're not going to create any
additional relational databases for
this application because we're
going to be using DynamoDB instead.
So we don't have to worry about that.
We're going to just stick with
the default instance, the t1 micro.
But if you wanted to select one
of Amazon's other server types as
your default type, you could do that here.
You could also select a SSH
key pair that you had
created through Amazon if you wanted to
be able to SSH into your applications.
The nice things about Spring Boot
applications is they include,
a health checking URL so by default your,
your Spring Boot application has a URL
called slash help that if a request is to,
sent to it and the application
is running it will return OK.
Now this is important because.
Amazon's load balancers need to know
when a node fails for some reason, or
some error has occurred, so that they can
go and either shut that instance down and
replace it with a new one, or take that
into account in the load balancing.
So this health check URL
is going to be used by
the underlying autoscaling infrastructure
and the load balancing el, infrastructure.
And we don't have to do anything.
We get that for free with Spring Boot.
We're going to go ahead and keep
everything else, all of the other defaults
the same, and we're just going to
click through to the next screen.
We don't have any specific Environment
Tags, so we're going to skip through this.
And, now we can go and
launch, our application.
Now, this application actually requires,
some command line parame,
parameters, some properties to be
provided to the virtual machine.
And, by default,
they are not being provided.
So one of the things that you need to do,
is go to the Configuration section.
And then under Software Configuration,
we can decide parameters that we would
like to be passed, to our application.
So, if you remember, when,
we wanted to launch our application,
we had to specify in the run configuration
clips, dash d and a parameter name.
And we had a series of those
that we had to specify.
So, if you go to the application,
these were the dash d parameters,
that we were passing it in.
So we would have dash d,
AWS access key id.
We had a slightly different naming for
it in the other examples, but
in this one we're going to
use Amazon's identifiers for
those properties that we can
pass on the command line.
In this case, AWS access key id.
And AWS secret key.
And, we will provide those properties
right here, in the configuration.
Once we have provided those properties,
they'll automatically be passed to our
instance when we launch it, and so
you can go ahead and provide those
properties, and then hit Save.
We're going to go back to the Dashboard,
and we see that Amazon is in the process
of launching our application, which is
going to take a little bit of time.
While Amazon is going ahead and
launching our application,
let's take a look at some of the other
features that we have available to us.
As an a, a, app engine server,
we can go and we can get the request Logs.
And get, information about the server.
In this case,
our server hasn't launched yet, so
there's no logs that
are available to us yet.
But once the server is launched,
we'll be able to grab the logs.
We can go and monitor our server and check
its health once it's actually launched.
We can also look for events related
to the startup, of the application.
In this case we can see that Amazon's in
the process of creating an autoscaling
configuration so that as load on
our system increases, Amazon will
automatically go and deploy new instances
of our application in a virtual machine.
And automatically start Tomcat and
pass all of the correct parameters and
WAR files to it.
We can also set Alarms, for example,
when something interesting happens that we
want to know about, like the load gets
too high or response time gets too long.
We can set those types of things in Alarm.
So this is the basic infrastructure
that Amazon Elastic Beanstalk gives you.
You can also go do in much
richer configuration, but
we're not going to get into those deeper
details, but this is a very simple way,
of getting a Spring Boot application
up and running in the cloud.
Now that our application has switched over
to green, saying that it's healthy and
it's running in the Amazon's cloud.
We can actually go and
access its URL at elasticbeansalk.com,
to see that it's running.
And in this case we've got our
video service now running, and
it's reporting back to us,
that it has a slash video URL.
So, that's it and that's all it
took to go from our WAR file,
clicking through a few simple
screens on Amazon's cloud to
actually deploy the WAR file
into Elastic Beanstalk.
And, at this point, it's helpful to
understand that we've actually set up
quite a bit of complicated infrastructure.
We've got a load balancer,
that's been set up by Amazon.
It's now routing requests, to one or
more virtual machines,
that have been set up in Amazon's cloud.
Each virtual machine has Tomcat
running on it, Tomcat 7.
With our app inside of it.
We then got our app talking
to Amazon's Dynamo database.
And anytime that the load gets too high on
our application, Amazon will automatically
go and autoscale,
our application to increase or
decrease the number of virtual machines,
that are needed to handle the traffic.
So if it sees that the.
The CPU utilization on a particular
virtual machine is getting too high or
some other trigger that we've set,
it will automatically allocate new virtual
machines, launch our application in them.
And then when the, the CPU utilization or
other metrics get too low,
it will automatically take away
virtual machines as needed.
So, with a very simple bit of work,
we now have.
An application,
that can receive requests to
a URL at Elastic Beanstalk
that was created for us.
And, we can then route those requests
across multiple virtual machines,
that'll each start and
run our application.
Each of those can be connected
to Dynamo's database.
We also have access to all of the logs,
for these virtual machines and
these Tomcat instances as they're running.
So, using Spring Boot,
packaging our code into a WAR file and
then deploying it to Amazon's Elastic
Beanstalk is a very straightforward and
simple process, to get your
application running in the cloud.