[MUSIC]
The anatomy of an HTTP response is a very
critical component to know
when we're building applications that are
communicating via HTTP.
So, one of the important things that we
have to
consider when we're sending messages to
some remote server and
asking it to, give us a resource or take
some
action on that resource, is what happened
on the server.
We can't directly be present on the server
when it's
accessing that resource to see if it
successfully accessed it.
Or if there was a problem or if something
else interesting happened, for example,
the resource has been moved and the server
needs to tell us about that.
So one of the really important and first
components that's related to the anatomy
of a response message in HTDP is what's
called the Status Line.
And the Status Line is composed of two
things.
It's composed of a response code,
which is a numeric code that tells us what
happened on the server.
Did it successfully find the resource?
Did it not find the resource?
Did it encounter some other type of error?
And that response code is really important
because it's telling the client.
Here is what happened on the server.
You couldn't directly observe what
happened, but I'm going to tell
you what happened, so that you can take
the appropriate action.
And a part of that response code is the,
the first component is numeric, it's a
numeric response code.
And the second part of the status line is
a phrase or a textual
description of the reason for this code,
or the explanation of it.
So, this is, you know, text that's being
set
back to elaborate the response code that
was sent back.
So, for example, if there's a, arbitrary
error, it may say there was a server here.
And so the response code and the reason
phrase give us a hint as
to what happened on the server, and allow
the client to take the appropriate action.
The second component of an HTTP response
is a series of headers.
So, just like we saw before with request,
we can send
meta information to the client when we're
providing a response to help
that client figure out how to interpret
that data that we're sending
to it how to interpret the response that
we're sending to it.
And usually a very important component of
the headers is as we
saw with mim types the content type of
what we're sending back.
And this is a really critical piece of
information to the client because the
client needs to know what are you giving
me what is the format of it.
And we would like to not
hardcode necessarily and assume a
particular format.
In many cases we end up hardcoding and
assuming a particular format, but it's
better if we
can sit, look at the content type and
decide the format for the body of the
message.
And then finally, we get the body, in the
response.
And so this is the actual data, that, the
server, is sending back to us,
in, response, to our HTTP request, to,
take some action on a resource.
So the body may be the actual resource
itself, so, maybe we wanted to get
an HTML file, that's just HTML and
textural format stored in
the server and the server is gone and told
us it successfully retrieved that file.
It is a content type text/HTML and in the
body
is where we would find the actual data,
the textural data.
For that HTML or for example we set a
request that was for image lets say jpeg
image, the server would return a response
code to
us telling us that it successfully found
that image.
It will set the content type to
image/jpeg.
And then it would, in the body, place the
binary data for that image, the jpeg
encoding of that
data and then we would go and pull it out
of the body and interpret it as an image.
So, the response is very similar in
construction to the request.
We have headers we have a body.
But the very critical sort of difference
is we have
this concept of a status on the server,
because we
can't directly observe what's going on so
the server needs
to tell us what happened in response to
our request.
Did we make a mistake in the way that we
formatted the request?
Did we try to access some resource that
the server doesn't know about.
Did the server, you know, explode and have
an error and tell us about it.
All of these things are communicated back
to us
in the response so that our client can
react appropriately.