[MUSIC]
Normally, the client controls almost all
aspects of the communication in HTTP.
And when I say controls, I mean, it's the
driver and
instigator of the communication and what
messages it sends to the server.
But occasionally it would be helpful for
the server to provide a hint to
the client, about data that it would like
the client to provide in future requests.
So, for example, let's say that you go to
a
banking website, or a website like Amazon,
and you log in.
Sometimes those websites and servers,
would like to
provide a little data indicating that you
have logged
in, and that you can provide to the
server,
in order to prove that you actually logged
in.
Because you're sending a series of
requests to the server.
And on the server's side, it needs some
way of figuring
out that you are the same client that sent
the previous request.
Because you are going to send a request
and
then you may go away for some period of
time and come back and the server would
like
to remember, for example, that you are
logged in.
But in order to do that, typically it
needs to tell you
to send some data to it, to prove that you
previously logged in.
So, how does the server go about
indicating data that
the client should store for the server and
send back to
the server in the future, to help it
figure out
who the client it or figure some state,
regarding the client.
The way that we do this in HTTP is through
a mechanism called cookies.
And what cookies are, are they are very
small
limited pieces of data, that the server
sends back
to the client and asks the client to
remember
on its behalf and then send in future
request.
Now because the server's sending this back
to the client, and
the client could be a mobile phone, or it
could be
a very powerful computer, the
specification for cookies is designed to
be limited, it's supposed to be a little
bit of data.
We don't want to overwhelm the client with
the data that we're asking it to store.
We don't want to send back terabytes of
data and
ask the client to store them on the
server's behalf.
So, Cookies are very small pieces of data,
that get sent back to the client.
And typically the way that cookies are
delivered to the client is a header
is placed into the response of
that the server is sending back to the
client.
And what happens then is
the client reads the cookie header,
extracts a little bit of data that the
server is asking it to store and then
places it into a temporary storage.
And then, on future request, when the
client sends the request, it will
place the cookie back into the headers,
that it's sending to the server.
So, the server can access that data again
and
for example, automatically identify that
this is the same
client that previously logged in or same
client that
previously added a particular item to its
shopping cart.
So cookies are important for a topic that
we'll talk about later in the course,
called sessions.
Now, another important thing to note is
that cookies, the
server can try to give hints to indicate
what the
client should do in terms of how long it
should
store that data and the sensitivity and
security regarding that data.
So for example, cookies typically have an
expiration date attached to them.
And that's a time at which the server
wants the client to
forget the cookie and stop sending it with
its request to the server.
So for example, there's probably a limited
amount of time that
the server would like to register, you as
being logged in.
So, it wants to indicate to the client, at
some point, it should forget about sending
that cookie to
you anymore because the server isn't going
to register it
as being a valid session or a log in
anymore.
Similarly, there are certain Cookies for
example, that
we don't want to transmit unencrypted in
HTTP request.
Normally we just send HTTP requests over
the internet and we don't encrypt them.
And there's another variant of HTTP that
we'll talk about later called HTTPS, where
we do encrypt the data that we are sending
in order to protect it.
But if we want to make sure that a cookie
is
protected, we can say for example, client
only send this cookie
back to the server if a secure link, or an
HTTPS communication protocol is being used
to talk to the server.
So there's a variety of different
indications that the server can provide
to the client on how to handle the cookie,
and what is
the right way to store it, how long to
store it, and
when to send it or not send it, back to
the server.
And so, all of these things are very
important for some
of the concepts that we'll be talking
about later when we
need to remember a little bit of data for
the servers,
so that it can help figure out which
client is which.