[MUSIC]
So as we've seen, resources play a very
important role in the HTTP specification.
Every time we're sending a request to the
server, we're asking
it to take some action on some resource
that we're interested in.
So, obviously, a really important part of
understanding how to write clients
that operate on HTTP is understanding how
we talk about resources to
the server and how we identify the
resources that we're interested in
so that the server can locate them and
then take that appropriate action.
Now in HTTP, the way that resources are
identified is with what's called
a uniform resource
locator
or URL, which is what everybody should be
familiar with.
And what a URL consists of is the
specification of the protocol,
which in this case, is http://,
a host or server that's going to be talked
to.
Potentially a port number that's preceded
by a colon and that is, we're going to
connect to a specific port on that host.
And then a path,
that we would like to access, representing
that resource.
So, in this case, this is telling us which
server to go and talk to on the network.
Which port of that server we want to
deliver our HTTP messages to.
So this is typically going to be the port
that the web application container or
web server, whatever the entity is that's
providing the server side of the HTTP
communications.
This is going to be the port on this host
that it's listing.
And then finally you have the path to the
resource that we are interested in on that
particular host.
So then when the host receives this, what
it's really interested
in is typically the component at the end;
which is the path.
It already knows where it is, it already
knows its port, but
it needs to know the path to the resource
that you're looking for.
One other interesting component of URL's
that are
very important in HTTP communication from
mobile clients
and other clients trying to communicate
with web
based applications is the concept of query
parameters.
So you may have seen some URL's that look
something like this.
And what this is, is at the end of this we
have what are called query parameters.
And what query parameters are, is they are
additional information that
can be attached to the end of the URL,
that's passed
along to the server in
order to communicate information,
additional information,
about what particular aspect of that
resource the client is interested in.
And these query parameters take the form
of, they must follow
a question mark that is placed at the end
of the core part of the URL.
So right after the resource path, we have
a question mark, which we see right here.
And then we have a series of key value
pairs, where in this case we have a key
which is A and then we have the value
which is B.
And so these query parameters follow at
the end of the path that's being
specified.
Now if we want to specify multiple query
parameters, that's also possible too.
In this case we only have a single key
value pair.
We have the key A equals B.
We can also pass multiple parameters.
So for example, if we had a question mark
and then we had A
equals B, we can then add an ampersand to
the query path, I mean the query
parameters.
And then we can have a second set of key
valued pairs.
So, in this case we have the first key is
key 1 which is A.
Then, the second key which is key 2, which
is C.
And then we would have B as the first
value for key 1.
And D is the value for key 2.
So using query parameters, we can pass
essentially extra information
about a specific aspect of a resource to
the server.
And we can pass as many of these as we
want up to a limit.
Now, we just keep separating these query
parameters with ampersand in
order to understand where the separations
are between the keys and the values.
There are a couple of important concepts
that we need to
know about, if were going to pass query
parameters to the client.
One of those things is we can't have
certain
special characters appear within our query
parameter values and keys.
So as you can imagine on the server side,
the server needs to easily be able to
parse
these query parameters by looking for the
equal signs
and the ampersand signs as well as the
question mark.
And if we began inserting these special
symbols into our query
parameters, it'd be hard for the server to
extract them out.
So, by default there are a set of
characters that we're allowed to have in
our
query parameters and a set of characters
that
we aren't allowed to have in our query
parameters.
And any of those characters that aren't
allowed to be in our query parameters have
to be actually encoded using a process
that's called URL encoding.
And the idea behind this is, if we want to
pass a
value that has characters that aren't
allowed in the query parameter spec.
What we can do is instead replace those
characters, with what are called their URL
encoded
equivalence so that we can still represent
them,
and the server understands how we
represent them.
But when we actually go and look at the
characters there itself, none of these
symbols show up.
They get replaced with other things that
mean the same things.
So if we have an equals sign within our
value for a particular
key pair, it will get replaced with the
URL encoded equivalent of equal sign.
Now, you could go and look up all of the
specific ways that
you URL encode different characters into a
query parameter, but you don't need to.
Almost every programming language that
you're going
to work with has libraries and functions
available to you to automatically encode
your
query parameters into a properly URL
encoded string.
So you don't need to go and learn
them, you just need to understand the
concept that.
If you pass specific things like the equal
sign or
the ampersand or the question mark or the
slash or
space inside of one of your keys or
values, then
you need to make sure that you're URL is
URL encoded.
And so other than that, you don't need to
do anything.
But you do need to understand the cases
where if you put
something into one of your query
parameters, you need to URL encode it.
Often, when we're writing clients, they're
going to be sending data
to the server or sending requests to the
server, we want
to go ahead and URL encode all of our URLs
that
are dynamically constructed with some type
of data that we're taking in.
Because there's a possibility that that
data may
not strictly adhere to the query parameter
specification.