[MUSIC]
It's really important to understand the
details of the HTTP protocol.
In order to build and debug effective
cloud services.
So let's talk about those details in some
more depth.
So the HTTP protocol is always organized
around a client sending a request to the
server.
So we have our server and our client and
we have a request that's being sent.
Now, one of the key parts of that request
is the action
that the client is asking the server to
take on its behalf.
And so every request has a request method.
And the request method, is the action or
the verb that
the client is asking the server to take on
its behalf.
And all requests are dictated as a request
method that
should be applied to a specific resource
on the server.
So for example, when you go and access a
webpage, using your browser.
What you're typically doing is sending a
request that has the get request method.
So it is a get request, and the resource
is usually some webpage
like index.html, which is usually the.
Core webpage at a website, when you go to
that, that address.
So the get is the request method, and the
resource is the index.html.
And the resource is typically specified as
a path to a resource on the server.
So the resource will typically be a path.
So you'll see something like get, you
know, /index.html or fu/mypage or
some other resource that you would like to
access.
And here again it's a Request method, and
then a path to a resource.
So let's talk about the H [INAUDIBLE]
request methods.
There's a variety of them in the protocol,
but there's a subset of
them that we really care about for
communicating between mobile devices and
the cloud.
One of the most important ones that we
want to understand is Get.
Get is a simple request to the server it
can be without data or possibly include a
little
bit of data and it's asking the server to
get some resource that's there and return
it to us.
So we're going to talk about the important
HTTP request methods, that we really care
about.
So, this is one of the HTTP request
methods is GET.
Another really one, important one is POST.
POST is typically used when you want to
send a lot of data to the server.
So, for example, if you want to go and
Post an image to the server
that it can then store and serve up at
some later point in time.
Post is probably something you will be
using to do that.
Get you probably aren't going to be
sending an image through get.
You're going to be sending some small
amount of data through Get.
Post is your more general purpose send
data to the server.
These are your two most important, but
there's two
more that's worth knowing about having
some familiarity with.
Another one is Put is asking a server to
store
some data that is contained within the
request on the server.
And the last one you probably want to know
about is Delete.
And it's fairly self explanatory.
We weren't asking the server to delete
some information on the server.
So when you're sending HTTP requests,
you're always going to specify an HTTP
request method plus a path or resource.
That you want that method to be applied to
you.
So, I want to get this particular
resource.
I want to put this resource on the server
or I want to delete this resource in the
server.
So whenever you're sending a request,
you're always
telling the server the specific action or
request method.
That you would like to be taken on that
particular resource.