[MUSIC]
When we're writing a mobile client or a
web
based client it's going to access
resources on a server.
One of the things that we need to
understand is how
to interpret the response codes that the
server sends back to us.
We have to know how to read what the
server
is telling us happened on the server from
the numeric code.
because this is a really important part of
writing the logic in
our client to appropriately react to what
took place in the server.
We may need to re-send the request or
re-try it, or we may need to go
and look at our code because we see that
there's an error in how we format it.
So let's talk about how response codes
are formatted and represented in the http
protocol.
So there's a series of response codes that
are
typically in the range of 100 to into the
500s.
And the one XXX messages whence you will
see for example.
You might have 104, 105 anything in the
hundred range is an informational message.
So the server's telling us something.
The quest isn't completely processed yet.
But it's giving us some information about
your request.
Now the next one that we care about are
things that were successful.
So request codes that start with two are
successful request codes.
So you asked for a resource, I found it,
okay, I'm giving it to you.
So one of the really important ones that
we want
to know from the two series is 200 which
is okay.
And this is basically the server telling
you, you sent me a request,
I found the resource, I took whatever
action you wanted on that particular
resource.
It's okay, everything worked.
And the data that you're getting back in
the body you can
go and interpret it and you can assume
that things were successful.
This is a very important status code to
know.
Now, one thing to remember when you're
building clients
is you should remember the scheme that you
used.
I'm talking about 1XXX, 2XXX.
It's important that when you're building
your
logic you be able to quickly differentiate
between something that's successful verses
something that's
unsuccessful as I'll show in a second.
3XXX is typically redirection.
It means that, for example, something has
moved.
The client is going to have to do some
extra work
in order to completely send that request
and get it processed.
So, for example, you know, you asked for a
request.
Are you, you, you sent a request on a
resource that is now moved somewhere else.
And so the server's going to tell you the
new location of that resource and you are
required to resend your request in order
to have it processed and completed.
So this is some type of redirection
typically.
Further work that the client's going to
have to
do in order to get its request completed.
So it's not necessarily that the request
was unsuccessful
it was just that we have to do more.
We're probably going to have to resend the
request to
a different location that the server's
going to give us.
That's typically what's happening with the
three series.
The next series is 4XXX.
And what this is, is you messed up.
The client messed up.
So the server's going to tell you,
that either the resource you requested
doesn't exist.
So for example 404 is a common
error code that you're probably going to
want to handle.
And that's that the resource wasn't found
or you may
have, depending on if you're sending
parameters
to the data, you may have a response
telling you that
you've formatted your requests
incorrectly.
So, for an example, in later parts of the
course, we'll see when we're building
in our web-based services and applications
to handle data from the clients.
We actually can enforce the rules that
certain data is set from the request.
And if data that we expect to be there is
not, we can send
back a response code to the client,
telling it that its request was formatted
improperly.
And then the next series of response codes
that
we want to be aware of are the five
series.
And what these are are server errors.
So this is something bad went wrong on the
server.
So a common one that you'll see is error
500 which is some
error took place on the server you as the
client need
to know about because we didn't
successfully complete your request and
often
the body of the message might tell you
information about the error.
So, for example, if you're building a or
communication with a Java-based
application, the application may return
a stack trace to you in the body
of the message telling you exactly what
went wrong.
Although, you typically don't want to do
that.
You don't want to send to much information
like a stack trace back in
your response to a client because you
don't want them to know that information.
For security purposes you shouldn't be
doing that.
But it is helpful to have information
about what went wrong to some degree.
So when your building a client you want to
build logic that reads
these response codes and then takes the
appropriate action.
So you want to handle the response
differently based on the code.
So you don't want to go and send a request
and then blindly assume that it was
correct, read the data out of the request
and for example interpret that data as an
image.
You want to read the response code, see if
you've gotten for example 200 okay.
If you have you can go and interpret that
data as an image.
If you've gotten 5XXX you shouldn't
interpret that data as an image.
You need to interpret as, you know, some
information related
to the error that, that server sent back
to you.
So you need to understand these response
codes for
you clients in order to put the right
logic
in them to evaluate the response that's
coming back
and determine if it was successfully
completed or not.