[MUSIC]
Both client and server can send bodies in
the messages that they send through HTTP.
So, for example, a client can include a
body in
the HTTP messages, a request that it sends
to the server.
And that body has some data in it that
the server needs to use, to process the
client's request.
Similarly, the, the server can have data
in the response that it sends back to
the client, that the client needs in order
to receive the results of its request.
So, one of the really important issues
that has to be sorted out in HTTP, is how
do the client and server tell each other
about what the data is
and how to interpret the data that's being
sent in those bodies of the HTTP messages?
So, for example, you can imagine that you
could
have an image download service on a
HTTP-based server.
And depending on which image you access,
it could have a different format.
So, for example, the server could store
images that are in
JPEG format, as well as images that were
in PNG format.
And the resource identifier, the URL for
that
particular image, may not actually tell
you what the format of the image is.
It would be a good practice to encode the,
the correct
file extension into the resource,
potentially, but it doesn't have to.
So, when that message comes back from the
server and has some image
data in it, the client needs to be able to
figure out, is
this image data for a JPEG, is this image
data for a PNG,
or even if the server is sending back
textual data to the client.
It may need to tell the client how to
interpret that textual data.
For example, the server could send back
pure, plain text to the client that
the client is just supposed to display and
not interpret in any special way.
Or the server could send back HTML, which
the client is expected to render as HTML
and
render all of the proper elements from
HTML in
a user interface, before showing it to the
user.
So in both cases, there's different types
of data that
are being sent back in the body and we
need way
of communicating how to interpret that
data, what format the client
or the server should interpret that data
as being part of.
Now, the way that this is done in HTTP is
through what's called MIME types.
And a MIME type is an identifier for a
particular type or format of information.
And the client and the server communicate
to each other by passing MIME types
back and forth, explaining how to
interpret
the bodies of the messages that they're
sending.
Now, if you go and look at the MIME types,
you'll see
a lot of common things that may seem
familiar, expressed as MIME types.
So, for example, you may see a MIME type
that looks like image/jpg.
And this would be the MIME type for a
JPEG-encoded image.
Similarly, the server could send back
image/png, indicating this is a PNG image.
Or, the server could send back text/plain
to indicate this is just plain text
or text/html.
And all of these different MIME types are
identifiers for a well
known format for the data in the body of
either a request or a response.
And the client is supposed to look at
these and the server is supposed to look
at these MIME types, and then based on
this, decide how to interpret the data.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And again, all of this, these different
MIME types, are typically describing.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The body of the request.
So, this body is being described by the
MIME types.
The format of that body is being described
be the more the MIME types.
And this allows a client and server to
send back different types of data for
a particular resource, or for a particular
request, or for a particular response.
And indicate to the other end of the
conversation, how to interpret that data.
Now you might say, shouldn't we just
encode all of this into the URLs?
But you can imagine that there may be
particular
resources on the server, for example, that
we might want
to map differently and have different
formats for it
and be able to change those formats in the
servers.
We don't want to couple our URL,
necessarily, to the exact
format that we are going to return the
data in.
So, having MIME types allows us to
flexibly adapt our bodies and be
able to tell the other end of the party,
how we've decided to format those bodies.
So, how do we communicate these MIME types
that
are associate with the bodies of requests
and responses?
This is where the headers in HTTP messages
come into play.
We need to provide meta information to
either the client or the server, telling
it how to interpret the body of the HTTP
message.
And, this meta information gets
communicated as the content-type
header in an HTTP message.
And what the content-type header says, is
this body of this
message should be interpreted as a
particular MIME type.
So, the content type communicates
the MIME type that's either a,
that's associated with the body
of either a request or a response.
So, we can use the content-type header in
both
request messages, and response messages,
that include a body.
And so, either end of the conversation can
look at the HTTP
content-type header and then determine how
the body should be interpreted.
So, we learned about headers before and we
saw that there were meta information that
helped one end of the conversation to
process, or handle, the message in some
way.
And in this case, this is a perfect
example of how they're used.
The content type is telling us the format
of the body of a request,
or of a response, and how the server, or
the client, should interpret that data