[MUSIC]
Hi, I'm Jules White from Vanderbilt
University.
And welcome to my course on
programming Cloud Services for Android
handheld systems.
So there's different estimates, but people
estimate that Amazon has between
150,000 and 450,000
servers that are backing its public cloud
that you can get access to.
Similarly, there are estimates that Google
and Microsoft
have over a million different servers that
are
backing their infrastructure that they use
to support
things like Gmail, or Google search or
Bing search.
So cloud services have become really a
fundamental capability that
you need to be able to build really large
scale
and compelling applications, like Amazon
and Google and Microsoft do,
or the many start-ups that are doing
really fascinating things.
So what this course is about is how do you
build scalable, secure Cloud services that
communicate with mobile devices?
Now there's lots of material on building
web based services.
But this course is going to focus
specifically on services that live in the
cloud and talk to mobile devices, using
protocols like the Hypertext Transfer
Protocol, or HTTP.
And how do we use things like the Java
Spring framework to receive requests over
HTTP and process them.
And then what are the special issues that
we have to think about
when we're storing data in cloud specific
data storage, like a key value store?
Where maybe we don't have the same query
capabilities that we normally did.
How do we architect things differently?
That's what this class is going to focus
on.
And hopefully, what it will give you the
ability to do is to
create really compelling and fascinating
applications that
take the data from a single device
or multiple devices, send it to the cloud,
and process it, combine it, and
store it in a way that you just couldn't
do on an individual device.
Because at the end of the day, although
mobile devices are
really impressive, a single mobile device,
a single Android device that we're
going to run, is never going to be quite
as compelling
as that device when it's connected to
100,000 servers, or 1000 servers.
Or maybe it's just ten servers, and each
of these
servers has significantly more computing
power than that single device.
So this class is about how we connect
these
devices to this cloud to build
applications that span these
resources that allocate things to the
right place in the
stack and do things in a scalable and
secure manner.
So I look forward to working with you
through the next several weeks
to understand how we build really
compelling cloud services to support
mobile devices.