[MUSIC]
So what do we need if we're going to talk
to a server that's sitting remote from our
mobile device?
So we've got our mobile device that's
sitting here, and we're
going to communicate between it and some
cloud resources.
So what do we need to do in order to
support that interaction?
Well, one of the most important things we
have to do
is we have to select a protocol for
talking to that cloud.
How do we go in about and talk to
the cloud, the cloud, and that's what a
protocol is.
A protocol is a set of rules dictating how
we
communicate with the resources on the
other end of this network.
Now why do we need a protocol, or some
specialized
way of communicating, and what does the
protocol get us?
So if we just go and make a local method
call,
this is going to be, you know, very, very
fast, nearly instantaneous.
But when
we go and do some communication over the
network, for example,
we communicate over a cellular connection
to resources that are sitting
in a cloud that could be, you know,
thousands of miles
away, this could be milliseconds to
seconds to do that communication.
So there's a substantial longer period of
time to establish that connection
to transfer data and to receive some type
of response that we're waiting for.
So a big question that comes up is, well,
how long is too long?
When should I disconnect from that server
and
assume that my communication from my
mobile device failed?
because, we've all experienced it, where
you're driving along
and suddenly your call drops because your
signal goes away.
Well how does that cloud know when it's
been too long since it's heard something
from you?
Or, what if you go and log in to a
website, when
should it, decide to de-authenticate you
and make you log in again?
All of these things are aspects of the
protocols that we
design in order to communicate with some
other entity that's farther away.
And it's really important to have a
robust protocol for this communication to
ensure that
we interact securely and reliably and
quickly with
the resources that we're trying to
interact with.
So to give you an example, think about the
Mars Rover
that, that NASA has launched and been
controlling from the earth.
When they send a message from Earth to the
Mars Rover to drive it or control it, it
can
take a substantial period of time for that
message
to receive, to be received on Mars by that
rover.
It's not milliseconds or seconds on the,
it's on the order of hours.
So think about it, you're driving this
rover, and
suddenly it hasn't received a message in
an hour.
What should it do?
How should it respond?
Should it keep going at 50 miles an hour
or 10 miles
an hour or however fast the rover goes, or
should it stop?
Should it try to return to where it
started from?
So this is what a protocol defines, is
it tells you how you communicate with
another entity.
And it defines a syntax, or basically a
format, for
the messages that you can send to that
other entity.
So it says, when I send a message, it has
to have these properties to it, and that's
the syntax.
It defines semantics, and this is
basically the meaning of the messages.
So if I send you message A and then I
send you message B, here's what I mean by
that, I
don't want you to get confused, I want you
to
understand the semantics of my messages,
or the meaning of them.
And then it spells out the timing, so I if
I send you
message A, how long do I have before I
should send you message B?
Or should I even send you message B at
all?
Should I send you something else instead?
So building and selecting the right
protocol for the interaction with the
cloud is one of the most important aspects
of mobile to cloud interactions.