[MUSIC]
Whenever a client sends a request to a
server using
HTTP, that request has to have a very
specific format.
I mean, just think about it, if you're
that server
receiving all of these requests from all
over the place.
You have to absolutely make sure that they
all have the same format so
you can interpret them properly and figure
out the right thing to do with them.
And that's why HTTP, very strictly
specifies what the
format and the rules are for sending that
request.
So let's talk about the Parts of a
Request.
So we have our HTTP Request.
And, each HTTP Request has a number of
critical, some mandatory
and some optional, parts that have to be
sent to the server.
One of the first parts that has to be sent
to the server is the Request Line.
And the Request Line specifies two really
important things.
The first thing is it specifies the
Request Method.
And the second thing that it specifies is
the Resource.
That we want to take action on, which is
typically specified as a Path.
So these are a request part.
Now, this is the key thing.
We're going to say, server, please go and
take this action.
On this particular Resource.
But when that server gets that Request
there's lots of cases where
it may have multiple options for how it
goes and completes that request.
For example, let's say that we have a
webpage on the server, and it's the
homepage of that particular web address,
so you go to the Equivalent of google.com.
Well, sometimes the server needs help
knowing some
information about the client that can help
it to
complete that request, things like the
language that
the client would like to receive the
response in.
So, the next piece of the request is a
series of Headers.
And what we can think of these is extra
information to help the server.
And these were things like the language
that
we would like the response to come back
in.
Or the character set that we would like to
see the response in, or the content type,
what we're sending back to the client so
it knows how to interpret it and process
it.
Or possibly something like the cookies or
small pieces
of data that were sent from the server to
the
client in a past request that the client's
now
providing back to the server to help it
figure out.
Where it was or who this person is, and
associate them with past requests.
So the Headers are the second key
component of a request, and they provide
extra information to help the server
figure
out the right way to process the request.
A final piece of information that can be
part of an HTTP Request.
Is the Request Body, and the Body is any
data
that the client is sending to the server,
in order to help it complete the request.
Now, this an optional part of a request,
and not a
100% required, but let's distinguish it a
little bit from the Headers.
The Headers are meta information, things
to help
it know the right way to process the
request.
The Body is core data that is being sent
to the server to process the request.
Now one way to think about this is in most
cases.
If you didn't include the Headers, but you
did
include the Body, the server could still
process the Request.
It just may not give it back to you in the
format that you expected or exactly the
way that you expected it.
But if you didn't include the Body and the
server
needed the Body, it wouldn't be able to
process the Request.
So the Body is the data the client is
sending, that
the server absolutely has to have in order
to complete that Request.
The Headers are extra information that the
client is
giving the server to help it complete that
Request.