So how
do we send data to the server?
Well we saw one method of doing this, and
that was to
use query parameters in the URL that we
were sending to the server.
And the server can extract the key value
pairs
that we're sending in that request from
the URL.
But, query parameters don't always make
sense as
the mechanism for sending data to the
server.
So there's another mechanism that we can
use to send data to the
server and that's through sending data in
the body that we've talked about.
So when we send a, a request message, we
can
associate a body with it that we would
like to place
data into, so we can have a body.
And as we saw, we can have different mime
types for that body.
But let's talk about the two most common
mime types that we're
going to see in bodies of messages that
we're sending to the server.
If you've ever gone and filled out a form
on the internet, you've probably used
one of these body types, and that's the
URL encoded form body type.
And so what that is is URL encoded is a
body mime
type that tells the server just like we
did in the query parameters,
we're going to have a set of key value
pairs that are
encoded exactly the same way as we would
put them into the URL.
But instead of putting those parameters
into the query parameter part of the URL,
we're instead going to take those key
value pairs and put them into the body.
So we can have URL encoded form data, or
data key value pairs, that we're sending
to the server.
There's a second type of mind type that we
often see for bodies and if you ever
uploaded a file through a forum in your
browser, you've probably used this mime
type and that's multipart enc, encoded
data.
And, what multipart does is rather than
using
the typical URL encoding, where we see a
key
equals a value ampersand another key
equals a value,
etc and we have all of the characters
escape.
Instead, multipart has a series of part
separators that are expressed.
And then we'll have data like byte data
for the different parts.
So basically, we can build a message and
we can
express the different parts of that
message using the multipart encodings.
The body is broken into a series of parts,
each of which can have its own identifier,
so essentially
its own key, and also its own mime type,
so
that we can interpret what to do with that
part.
So multipart is typically used for
uploading data like
images, or large amounts of data to the
server.
Whereas URL encoded is technically used
for sending
simple key value pair sets to the data.
Now you may be asking yourselves, well
when should I use one or the other?
What is the rule?
Well there's, the the basic thing you need
to
consider is how much data you're sending
to the server.
Multipart is good for sending a lot of
data to the server.
If you're sending a file to the server,
you're uploading some large chunk if
binary data.
Multpart is the appropriate way to do
that.
If you're sending a series of simple key
values pairs.
URL encoded is the way to do it.
And one of the reasons for that is that
URL encoded is going to be more efficient,
more space efficient in the size of the
message for small amounts of data than a
multipart.
And that's, and the reason is is that if
you have a series of short key value
pairs.
In a multipart message, each one of those
key value pairs has to be broken up and
pre-fixed by a specific, message indicator
in the multipart message.
And when you add up all of the overhead of
this various formatting rules for
multipart for small sets of key value
pairs,
it's less efficient than a URL encoded
message.
However, if you're sending a lot of data,
multipart is a much more efficient way of
doing
it than URL encoded, because the URL
encoding rules
require a transformation of that data so
that it
meets the URL encoding rules which ends up
increasing
the amount of data that we're actually
sending to
the server in order to safely express what
we're
sending to the server in a URL encoded
way.
So, we can think of this for lots of data
or binary data like files.
And we can think of this as, you know,
small amounts of data.
Or simple key value pairs.
And when you're sending
request messages, where you're sending
data to server, depending on how much data
you're sending, and
sort of the characteristics of that data,
you will choose
a content type that's either URL encoded
typically or multipart.
Now, when we get further into the course,
we'll see that there's
another type that commonly gets used, and
is popular now, called application/JSON.
But we'll talk about that type when we get
to it later in the course.