[MUSIC]
So how do we talk to 150,000 servers in
Amazon EC2?
How does a lonely little mobile device,
that's
connected to some network, out in the
wild.
Get access to these thousands of servers,
that are sitting in some cloud computing
environment.
So how do we get from there to there?
Well the way that we're going to talk
about getting from the
mobile device to the cloud is through the
use of HTTP.
And what you can think of HTTP is, it's
basically a dialog or a language
that a mobile device can use to speak to a
cloud, it's a protocol, an application
protocol, for communicating between
devices on a network.
Now.
We're going to use HTTP here as our
protocol for communication.
But it's helpful to have a little bit of
history.
And understand what HTTP, was originally
built for.
HTTP is the protocol, or the way that your
browser communicates with a web server.
In order to retrieve resources from that
web server such as a web page.
So when you go and you log in to Facebook,
for example, your browser is sending
HTTP, probably a series of HTTP requests,
to one or more Facebook servers.
And then that server, or servers that are
receiving the request or requests.
Send data back to your browser.
HTTP is a client-server protocol and what
that means
is that, the interactions that are
mediated
via the HTTP protocol, are always
initiated by a client that wants to.
Access or request, some resource on the
server.
So the server has a series of resources,
that it can provide to
the client, and the client sends requests
for those resources and the server.
Returns responses to those requests.
And the responses may have the resource
that was requested or it may have a
message indicating why the Server could or
couldn't process the request, that the
client sent.
But fundamentally, the HTTP protocol is
an application protocol that is
client-server.
So, the client will always be initiating
the communications.
And there are some changes to this with
newer things
like web sockets, that we'll talk about
later in this course.
But in general, the client will always
start the interaction.
And the server will receive the
interactions.
And process them.
So, this is the fundamental way, that HTTP
works.
Now the client can be either a mobile
device as we'll
focus on in this class, or it can be a
browser.
So, we can have a mobile device be the
client, or we can have a browser be the
client.
Or we could have some other device, maybe
in
the internet of things, we use HTTP as the
protocol
to communicate between different pieces of
equipment in a
factory and the different controllers,
that are monitoring their status.
So HTTP is a general purpose protocol.
That can be used, to communicate between a
client and a server.
Now one of the reasons that HTTP has
become so popular for mobile
integration with cloud, is that HTTP is a
widely used protocol already.
All of the websites that you visit are
already using.
HTTP as the protocol that's being used to
access those web res, resources.
So there's already so much infrastructure
that's been built
up and so much investment that has been
put
into HTTP protocol, and so much
understanding of how
the HTTP protocol works, that
organizations naturally want to reuse.
That infrastructure and investment, on
their mobile platforms.
So by using HTTP, they can write a server
side, that provides access
to these resources, which could be a
service, or could be a web page.
And, they can provide a common interface
to those resources, through HTTP.
It's a common protocol and a common server
site interface, to access those resources.
So when a server sends a response back, it
doesn't necessarily have to care whether
the person or thing
that's consuming that response is a mobile
device or a
browser, or some other thing that it's
never seen before.
As long as that thing knows how to speak
the HTTP protocol,
it can consume the resources and services,
that are available on that server.