[MUSIC]
So what is exactly is a cloud service,
that a mobile device might talk to,
and how do we differentiate and
understand,
how these services differ from the typical
applications.
That we're used to writing.
So, let's take a look at an example and
hopefully it'll
help to clarify and better understand what
a clou, a cloud
service is, and what the scope of this
course is and
what are the challenges that we're
going to face, when building these
services.
So let's assume we're writing a Java
application.
And what that java application allows us
to do, is we can capture a video
and then we can run a command line utility
that will be our application.
And it will go in save the video, on the
underline file system.
And not only will be going and save the
video in the underlying file system,
but it will also take that video and it
will save it to a database.
So, that we have a record of all
of the videos, that we've entered into our
system.
So, this is our service in this case or
application.
That we're going to be building.
And we'll assume that there's nothing
special
about this, it's just a Java application.
Well, if we're going to be running this
thing over here
from the command line, one of the things
that we're
probably going to want to do, if we're
writing this
in Java is we're goig to have a main
method.
So, we might have a public, static,
void, main that takes some arguments.
And we could go out and spell out what
those are.
And then in that main method.
We might go and do things like you know,
look
for the flags that were passed on the
command line.
So, we can look for flags.
We can look for the file that they want to
add the video.
So, look for the video path, and
we can do a whole bunch of other stuff.
But the key would be, we've got this main
method, which is part
of this application and every time from
the command line they invoke our
application.
They're going to be passing commands from
the command line into our application,
so what we have is a stream of commands
that are being passed into our
application.
So, every time the user goes and invokes
this thing from
the command line, they're basically
sending a different command to it.
And the tax that they enter in the command
line is then
being passed to our public static void
main method, where we can
start up our application, take action
based on the data that they
passed us, then going store something in a
database, or do something else.
We might also want to issue commands to
our application.
That have it go and query the information
we've already stored,
or be processed based on the information
we've already set the application.
So one of the, the things we might have to
do then,
is provide feedback to the user that's
sending the commands to the application.
So we might have something in our main
method that's printing out feedback.
Using System.out.printline back to the
user,
so that the user can see the results of
the commands that they're issuing.
Or see information that comes out of the
database that the user is querying.
So, not only do we have a situation, where
we are sending commands and asking.
The application to go and store data, but
we also
have situations where we need to, based on
those commands,
go and provide feedback to the user, about
the success
or failure of those commands and any data
associated with them.
So, for example, if the user issues a
query to see all of the videos created.
In a certain time period we'll probably
want to
print out the query back to the command
line.
Similarly if the user issues a query
that's malformed.
We would probably expect the application
to go
in print on the command line an error
message.
Stating what the user did wrong, and
helping them to
figure out how to formulate that command
correctly and send it.
Where if the application went and
processed the
command, and it had a bug in the program
and it crashed or [UNKNOWN] we would
expect to
get some feedback telling us that the
application crashed.
So what we'll see is this basic
architecture of commands being sent to
an application processing data in some
format
either storing it or performing some
analysis
on it, and then providing feedback to the
user based on the success or
failure of those commands, and in the
results of the execution of those
commands.
That's the basic architecture we're going
to be working with throughout this class.
The big difference is when we go into the
cloud services
model, what we're going to have is, the
case where we're sending
the commands to the application from a
mobile device, that's not
sitting on the same app, the same host as
that application.
So this mobile device is going to be
sending this command remotely over the
internet.
To this application and this application's
going to be living in
the cloud and receiving those commands,
processing data through some data store,
saving the information somewhere that's
being sent to it, and having to
remotely send back to the mobile device,
the results of those commands.
So, we have this remote interactions
that's based on commands being issued to
the application and results coming back,
that we're going to be working with.
We're going to be sending data from the
mobile
device, which is the client, to the
application.
It's going to process that information.
And in this case, the application is
going to be a server.
And it's going to be living in the cloud
and then it's going to
send the results back to the mobile
device, so that it can know what happened.
So it may be sending back results that say
here's the result of running your command.
It may send results back that say you
you know, did not formulate your command
correctly.
Or it may be sending results back saying
the server had a problem.
Here's what the problem was and it
crashed.
And that's the architecture that we're
going to be building through this class.
Is this remote distributed architecture
where mobile
clients, your mobile devices on Android,
are sending
commands over the internet, to a service
or a server that's living in the cloud.
And they're being processed and then
results
are being sent back to the mobile client.
And one of the key questions that we have
to answer and address is, how do
we get these commands from the mobile
device
to the server and communicate the results
back?
What are the requirements and rules for
that communication with they server that's
remote?
How do we ensure that it's reliable?
How do we ensure that it's orderly, and
done in a
way that the server can understand and
process commands for us?