[MUSIC]
So why are we using a web browser
protocol to integrate mobile clients with
cloud services?
Why do we want to use HTTP to talk to the
cloud?
Well HTTP provides us a number of nice
properties.
One is, we've got a uniform interface that
we can provide via
HTTP to the services or resources that are
sitting on the server.
And, for example, if a client is a Browser
and sends a request over HTTP and that
Server
rec, receives that request, the request is
exactly the
same as if a mobile device had sent it.
So, if this is a Mobile device that's
sending that request, either way
on the other side, on the server side,
that request still has to conform
to the same requirements and
specifications of the HTTP protocol.
So we can have a common interface.
This is one of the big advantages of
using HTTP to interact with cloud
resources and services.
Is we don't have to go and rewrite
everything from scratch and figure out a
whole
new way of having our servers accessible
and
having mobile devices able to communicate
with them.
We can reuse what we're already building
and providing
to our browser based clients and the web
is ubiquitous.
Everybody's building websites, everybody's
supporting web service as it is.
Why not reuse this infrastructure for
mobile?
And so that's one of the big reasons
behind using
HTTP to support mobile and cloud
interactions.
Now, we get a number or of other great
things as well.
There's already all kinds of stuff on the
server side from a
framework and programmatic perspective
that we can use to process HTTP requests.
So there's things for doing stuff like
sessions
or remembering when people request
something, who that
person is and what they previously
requested or
what other data is associated with their
current login.
We also get things like Data marshalling.
This is very important when you want to
convert from the format of
the HTTP request to some other format that
you need to process.
And there's a huge amount of
infrastructure that's already
been developed, in terms of libraries and
frameworks, that
you can use to program if you use HTTP
as your underlying protocol for your
interaction with the cloud.
But there's also a number of other reasons
that it's really nice to use HTTP.
There's also infrastructure that decides,
how do we
load balance and distribute requests
across our servers?
So for example, if you have a million
people accessing your, your
service simultaneously, how are you going
to distribute those requests across those
servers?
So, Load Balancing infrastructure for HTTP
can be reused
if we're using HTTP as the communication
mechanism with the cloud.
So there's such a significant investment
both in the existing frameworks and
libraries, the load balancing and other
management infrastructure that's been
developed for HTTP.
It's natural to use HTTP as an interaction
mechanism with the cloud.
Now, as we'll see later in the class,
there's some challenges to
using HTTP, particularly when things that
we would like to do with
our mobile services don't fit into the
client server model where the
client is always the mobile device
requesting some resource from the server.
So maybe an email comes into the server
and your client needs to be notified about
it.
Well that's difficult to fit into the HTTP
model.
But we'll talk about how we overcome some
of those challenges later in the lessons.