Welcome to Part 8 in the module on
Patterns and Frameworks for Concurrency
and Synchronization.
In the previous parts of this module, we
first described the active object pattern
and illustrated how the ACE Task framework
will be used to implement this pattern.
Within illustrated the application of ACE
Task and ACE Acceptor-Connector and some
other Frameworks to implement a thread for
connection version of our JAWS web server.
We then describe the Half-Sync, Half-Async
pattern that combines Reactor and active
object and illustrated a number of ACE
frameworks that could be combined to
implement this pattern and apply it in the
context of jaws to provide a more scalable
solution.
Within illustrated the application of ACE
Task and ACE Acceptor-Connector and some
other frameworks to implement a thread for
connection version of our JAWS Web Server.
We then describe the Half-Sync/Half-Async
pattern that combines Reactor and active
object and illustrated a number of ACE
Frameworks that could be combined to
implement this pattern and apply it in the
context of jaws to provide a more scalable
solution.
We then describe the monographic pattern
which was used to serialize access to a
synchronized request queue in our
Half-Sync/Half-Async solution.
And also, illustrated ways in which
various synchronization patterns can be
applied to monitor an object in the ACE
message queue to make it more pluggable,
more scaleable, easier to use in different
contexts.
What we're going to do now is turn our
attention to one final concurrency pattern
in this particular module, which relates
to something called Leaders/Follower,
Leader/Follower pattern.
And this pattern is another way to provide
for pools of thread that access underlying
event sources.
If you went back and looked at the
Half-Sync/Half-Async solution, even though
we did a good job of addressing the
limitations with the reactive approach,
where there was only one sort of control.
Even though, we did a good job of being
able to be more effective in our use of
resources than the thread per connection
approach where we used the reactive
object, there still are potentially some
problems.
Especially, if you have requests that
don't run for very long periods of time.
And here's what some of the limitations
are with Half-Sync/Half-Async.
One of the problems is that because the
thread that receives the incoming request
is not the same thread that will process
it, we have to end up using dynamic memory
allocation, which incurred synchronization
overhead and deals with, with memory
fragmentation and free lists and all those
kinds of issues.
Likewise, when we try to go ahead and NQ
and DQ things onto our thread safe
synchronized request cue, we're going to
have to do synchronization operations.
So, we'll have to grab a lock and that'll
have some overhead.
Likewise, when we try to move things
between these threads, that will typically
incur a context switch, which can take
many, many low-level instruction
operations in order to be run.
And we'll deal with caches and other low
level-hardware overheads.
Another issue, speaking of low-level
hardware overheads, has to do with the
overhead of moving data such as these
request messages between caches, between
cores, between CPUs, on a multi-CPU
platform, and that all starts to add up as
well.
So even though Half-Sync/Half-Async has
many positive qualities for certain types
of request, it may be too much overhead.
So what can we do to address this problem?
What we're going to describe here is how
to apply the Leader/Followers pattern in
order to be able to address this issue.
Leader/followers is a pattern that allows
a pool of threads, to efficiently and
predictably take turns accessing a lower
level set of event endpoints.
Things that you might have with, say, the
select system call that I've talked about
in the past or the poll system call.
This particular pattern is structured in
the couple of ways we're going to talk
about here.
Part of it, looks an awful lot like the
Reactor.
You've got a set of handles that you're
going to walk and manage, and, and
interact with, and monitor for different
kinds of events, from different sources of
events.
You've got a number of event handlers that
you can use to dispatch when things happen
on those sets of handles.
There's also a set of concrete event
handlers that you can inherit from the
abstract event handlers to do application
or server specific processing logic.
And all of this sounds quite a bit like
the reactor, of course.
But the one thing that's different from
the classic Reactor pattern is the
presence of a thread pool.
So we can actually have a pool of threads
that we'll call down into the hands, the
handle set in order to take turns,
accessing the source of events that, that
handle set encapsulates.
If you take a look at this URL, you'll
find a paper that describes other aspects
of this pattern.
Naturally, you can also read the
corresponding chapter in the posted two
book for much, much more detail about how
all of this works.
Let's now talk a bit about dynamics.
At first glance, the dynamics here look a
little daunting.
But when we break it down, you'll see it's
actually pretty straightforward.
So here's what happens.
You end up spawning a pool of threads and
they all attempt to become the Leader
thread.
Only one thread at a time can become the
Leader.
And the leader will sit there and wait for
something to happen on the source of
events perhaps using select and the other
threads will then wait on some kind of
synchronizer or queue as Follower threads.
When an event occurs, when an event
arrives, the Leader thread will take that
request and go ahead and deal with it.
It will read it.
It will process it and so on and so forth,
before it does that, it goes ahead and
first promotes.
One of the Follower threads to become a
Leader.
And when the Follower thread becomes a new
leader, it will of course, wait for the
next set of events.
While the original Leader thread morphs
itself into a so called processing thread
to handle the request.
And notice that the thread now that
handles the request is the same thread
that received the request.
So we don't have those issues of Dynamic
memory allocation and not as much issues
of synchronization and context switching
and data movement as we had with
Half-Sync/Half-Async.
When the processing thread, that was a
leader thread, finishes, it then typically
turns around and goes back to being new
Follower thread to wait for its turn to
become the leader, in some implementations
of this pattern you'll see that threads
that are done being processing threads
actually become the new leader thread.
And that's a way of trying to enhance
cache affinity and thread affinity so you
can keep things warmer and moving faster.
This is also something that makes it a
little bit more responsive and quite
different from the types of things that
humans would normally do where you would
queue up in a queue and take turns in a
FIFA order.
You can do a LIFO style model with the
leader, followers pattern and things work
quite fine because threads don't care the
order in which they wait to do their work,
they can all process things one at a time.
Let's now talk about how we could apply
this particular pattern to JAWS.
What we can do is we can use a special
framework that's part of ACE called the
ACE Thread Pool reactor or ACE TP Reactor.
And this TP reactor is basically a reactor
with the special property that a pool of
threads can call its run event loop, its
handle events method.
And in that particular pool of threads,
then it uses a Leader/Followers pattern to
have one thread at a time wait for work to
do while the other threads queue up as
followers.
The nice thing about doing this particular
approach is we can eliminate the need for
the extra thread in the async layer we had
with Half-Sync/Half-Async.
We could also get rid of the synchronized
message queue that we had at
Half-Sync/Half-Async.
So, as a consequence, it will greatly
reduce the amount of overhead and make the
system more predictable.
We're going to talk in a bit more, just a
moment, about the benefits and limitations
of Leader/Followers.
But I first want to talk about how, even
though, it will make the processing a
little bit lower overhead, especially for
small, short duration requests, you might
still consider using Half-Sync/Half-Async
for some environments, some contexts.
In particular, Half-Sync/Half-Async does a
few things in a little different way than
Leader/Followers, which may be beneficial.
One thing that Half-Sync/Half-Async does
is it allows you to be able to reorder and
reprioritize incoming requests, because
they sit on a separate synchronized
request queue.
So you can deal with the requests by the
importance of the clients for example, as
opposed to the order in which they arrive.
Another benefit you get with
Half-Sync/Half-Async is the ability to be
able to dedicate user level virtual memory
to queue up the requests.
You can allocate megabytes and gigabytes
and so on of internal memory to queue
these things up.
In contrast with Leader/Followers, the
queuing is typically done in the operating
system protocol stack layer.
And there is not nearly as much memory
available there on a per connection basis.
It's usually more like a 100K bytes or so
before you end up filling up your Window
size.
So an architect needs to know which of
these approaches to apply, and these
patterns help you to navigate through the
alternative design space as part of our
pattern language.
Let's now go and talk about the benefits
and limitations of Leader/Followers.
Some of the benefits are, we end up
getting tremendous performance
enhancements in certain areas.
For example, having the one thread of
control wait for work to do, and then
making sure that, that thread is where the
work is done.
Can improve cache affinity for the thread,
which means that you don't need to move
things between the caches.
It also means you don't have to even
allocate memory dynamically oftentimes if
you have a big enough buffer in the stack
frame in which the request comes in.
So that will improve and reduce certain
sources of overhead that Half sync half
async has to incur.
Likewise you can also minimize the amount
of locking overhead and the need to be
able to exchange data between threads,
because we're not moving data between
threads.
When the data comes it, it stays with the
thread that originally detected it and is
going to read it and process it in some
subsequent way when it morphs from being a
leader thread.
So that can reduce the need for
synchronization Overhead.
Likewise you can also end up reducing the
amount of priority inversion because we're
not trying to cue things up in some way
that would end incurring additional
overhead.
People often times will actually allocate
multiple pools of threads each one running
their own thread pool reactor.
At the appropriate priority level in order
to be able to maximize the priority
preservation in a real time system.
And another reason why this can be a
beneficial approach versus
Half-Sync/Half-Async is the amount of
context switching is reduced for each
event.
We are not moving things around between
the threads as much.
So, that's a win as well.
Another nice thing is it makes it really
to implement a thread pool using a
reactive style of design.
In the next part, in this module, we will
give you an illustration of how to do that
with our JAWS Web Server.
Naturally, of course, there are
limitations.
This particular pattern is very
complicated to Implement.
We've implemented many variations of it in
ACE over the years and I think we've got
all the bugs out.
But it took us a while because there's
subtleties, there's different variance of
Leader/Followers, there's a bound variant,
there's an unbound variant that are
described in the various papers and it's
important to understand these different
variations to implement it effectively.
And naturally, it also helps if you have a
framework that does the work for you so
you don't have to do it yourself.
Another downside is it's a bit less
flexible than Half-Sync/Half-Async.
You can't easily discard the messages, you
can't easily reprioritize them, because
there's no extra queue, there's no extra
thread in which to do that.
So that can be a little tricky, and of
course, because we have one thread of
control that's waiting at a time for
incoming requests on a set of handles that
itself could become a bottleneck in highly
scalable systems.
So as a general rule of thumb, I like to
use Leader/Followers in situations where
I've got more real-time responsiveness,
where predictability is more important
than scalability and I like to be able to
use Half-Sync/Half-Async situations with
the reverse properties where scalability
is very important and predictibility is a
little bit less important.
Next, we'll talk about how to illustrate
this pattern being applied to JAWS.