Welcome to the module where we'll evaluate
patterns and frameworks for concurrent and
networked software.
In this one and only part of the module.
We're going to step back and take a look
at some of the benefits and limitations of
applying patterns and frameworks to
concurrent and networked software.
If you recall, at the end of section two,
we had done a similar analysis after
providing an introduction to patterns and
frameworks.
Now that we've gone through quite a
lengthy.
Explanation and analysis of the
application of many patterns and many
frameworks to the web server.
We're going to step back and see if we can
take a look.
And bring up some pros and cons of the
technologies we've been applying in the
context of our previous discussion.
Let's start by talking about some of the
benefits of patterns.
If you take a look back over all the
material we covered.
In this section, you'll see that there
were a number of core architectural
patterns that we use to systematically
reuse capabilities in order to build a
concurrent Web server, an a, event driven
Web server.
W applied patterns like the reactor
patter, we applied half sync, half async,
we applied leader followers, we applied
the proactor pattern.
And these are all ways of trying to embody
Successful designs that have been done
well before we ever came along and tried
to build a web server.
Likewise, we also explored a number of
paths through our pattern language, which
combined these core architectural patterns
with a number of other design patterns.
In order to be able to handle different
variations on a theme.
Be able to make things more scalable less
scalable and so on and so forth.
One of the nice things about this is that
these approaches we looked at really
weren't specific to web servers.
They'd been developed long before we did
anything with our JAWS web server.
And they've proven themselves to be useful
over time.
In many other contexts as well.
So that illustrates one of the benefits of
patterns.
You can build upon prior success, in order
to build new applications in new contexts.
Another benefit we have of patterns is the
ability to record explicitly.
Trade offs between different design
approaches in terms of our engineering and
our application of different design
techniques.
So for example when we looked at the
different paths through our pattern
language through our web server, you saw
that we had a number of different
alternatives that we could evaluate and
determine what the benefits were, what the
trade offs were and so on.
For example we looked at the, the reactive
path which was very simple and easy to
develop but didn't really scale because it
only used one thread of control at a time.
We then went and explore a different path
through our pattern language.
We look at the use of half sync half
async, which combines the reactive
approach with an active object approach
and a number of other concurrency
insynchronization pattern.
In order to build the scale up to take
better advantage of multiple CPU's that
you might find in a multi-core environment
or an upgrade system that supports various
kinds of occur ency and multiple type,
threading in multiprocessing.
This particular approach is well different
from the reactive approach and it allows
us to explicitly.
Trade off and analyze these different
approaches.
Yet another approach that we've followed
was 1 that was based on the leader
followers pattern.
Which is, perhaps, less scalable than half
sync half a sync.
But by the same token, can be more
predictable.
Taking advantage of thread pools by
arranging the concurrency and the
concurrency processing and event handling
in a slightly different way.
Applications, different requirements,
different domains.
Will require different paths through this
pattern language.
We also took a step back and looked at the
use of asynchronous processing.
Following the proactor pattern and various
patterns that relate to it.
Such as asynchronous completion token.
And this gives us a way to get a lot of
the benefits of multi-threading without
incurring some of the complexities of
multi-threading and synchronization.
The downside here of course, is that we
had less portability in our solution,
which might make it difficult to use in
it's broad a number of different contexts
as some of the other paths through our
pattern language.
But the key point here was tha tpatterns
allow us to be explicit in recording and
documementing these tradeoffs.
Which are otherwise often lost, in terms
of internal implementation details.
And other information that's locked in the
head of experts or buried deep in the
source code.
Another benifite of patterns is that they
help us to have a shared vocabulary that
allows team memeber to communicate to each
other much more clearly and concisely.
For example when we had started to develop
the jaws web server in the late 90's The
group I was working with at the time, grad
students, staff members, other faculty,
had been working with patterns for about 4
or 5 years.
And so we had begun to document many of
the key architectural roles and
responsibilities.
That found their way into the use of the
web server.
And the nice part was when we brought new
team members into the project, it was very
easy to bring them up to speed.
We just, we would say, go read these
papers or go look at these source code
examples and very quickly they could latch
onto the key design behavioral issues,
structural issues.
Ways of arranging the software to make it
effective in the context of the web
server.
If we hadn't had that information
documented, it would have been much more
difficult to bring the team up to speed
quickly.
Of course nowadays we have things much
easier.
We're able to use various books that have
been published on these topics on a wide
variety of different programming languages
and operating environments.
We're able to leverage digital learning.
Means such as these video courses and so
on in order to be able to teach people
these concepts without having to go
through the school of hard knocks and
painful trial and error that takes a long
time to do.
If you take a look at the website at the
bottom of this slide, you can find out
more papers that document the origins of
our JAWS web server and how we came upon
the ideas of trying to build it around a
shared commonality using patterns and
pattern languages.
Another benefit of patterns is it helps to
transcend language-centric perspectives,
language-centric biases.
Programming languages are a lot like
movies, music, art.
We all have our personal favorites.
And it's a lot of fun to argue vehemently
with other people.
Trying to convince them that what we like
is better than what they like.
But of course, in reality, there's a lot
of underlying Themes that are important to
also realize.
And focus on patterns allows us to elevate
the discussion to the more strategic
issues of design and then make it more
straightforward to apply those good design
techniques and those best practices in the
context of whatever programming language
you may happen to work with, be it your
favorite one or one that is imposed upon
you because of the context, or customer,
or the work group that you're interacting
with.
There are some other issues related to
this as well.
Patterns also allow us to abstract away
from other details, above and beyond the
programming language.
For example, if you go back and watch the
various modules in this section that
talked about the different paths though
our pattern language.
You'll see that almost all the discussions
begin by discussing the patterns without
having yet wrapped around issues like the
choice of the operating system, the choice
of the particular details of concurrency,
synchronization, event demultiplexing and
so on.
And so that allows us to be able to
abstract away from some of these
unessential details when it makes sense to
think more strategically.
At the design phase, at the architecture
phase.
And these are all good things because they
help people get it right in the broad
sense before they start to delve down into
those implementation details.
Of course there's also some limitations
that come from patterns in this regard as
well.
If you just read the pattern literature,
it often gives you a somewhat incomplete
view of trying to address these design and
implementation concerns.
The pattern's literature typically does a
good job of explaining the design roles in
relationships.
What are the key structures, what are the
common behavioral aspects?
But often times doesn't really dig down
deep enough into some of these more subtle
implementation and optimization concerns.
So when you actually go to apply these
patterns in practice, especially in
environments where performance and quality
of service has a big impact on the success
or failure of a system There's a lot of
other things you're going to have to
wrestle with in order to be successful.
You'll have to think about different ways
of doing event demultiplexing, A weight
for multiple objects versus select.
Edge-triggered versus level-triggered
event demultiplexors.
Different semantics for threading and
concurrency.
Different ways of handling asynchronous
I/O.
Windows does it one way, it does it quite
well.
Posics does it a different way.
Often not quite as well.
How do you try to find ways to factor out
those diversities.
There's other issues of course, with
different kinds of inter-process
communication mechanisms, dynamic linking,
multiprocessing, security, and so on and
so forth.
And of course, don't forget the language
specific issues too.
Different languages embody different ways
of implementing these patterns.
More efficiently or less efficiently or
more effectively and less effectively.
And so it's important to get down a little
deeper than just an understanding at a
cursory level of the design issues.
Now it turns out that some of the
limitations we had talked about previously
when we had been in the section providing
an introduction to patterns and frameworks
Are not quite as important or not quite as
relevant when we start applying patterns
together with frameworks.
For example one of the things we've talked
about earlier in the previous analyses was
that patterns don't write the code.
You have to figure out some way of being
able to take the patterns description and
turn them into source code.
Well obviously if you're using a framework
or a set of frameworks And those
frameworks do embody the patterns, then
that particular issue is much less
problematic.
There may be other issues but the issue of
trying to have the code reusable as well
as the design is somehow alleviated or
somewhat alleviated when you combine
patterns of frameworks.
This a good segway into the discussion
about some of the benefits Of frameworks
that we've discussed as we've been going
through this section three.
One of the main things you get with
frameworks is even further elaboration on
reusive design.
By their nature, patterns are about
reusing design concepts, design artifacts,
design architecures and so on.
When you get into the frameworks, you're
using.
They're reusing the design, but it's more
the detailed design.
It's the way in which the various classes,
and components, and functions interact
with each other in regular ways in
recurring structures and behaviors.
And as you saw in our illustration in the
context of the JAWS Web server, because we
developed the frameworks using variation
orientated design And careful commonality
and variability analysis.
It was often very straight forward to go
from one model, one event to multiplexing
or concurrency model to another without
much change in the design.
For example we were able to go from a
reactive approach to doing concurrency
with the web server to one that used a
thread per connection model with virtually
no change whatsoever to the design.
Just a few little tweaks here verriding a
few methods, implementing things spawning
active objects as opposed to passive
objects and so on and so forth.
So that's a nice example of how the
various frameworks that we've been
discussing allow tremendous reuse of
design.
And that design insight of course is built
up over many, many years of re-factoring
an application and generalization and
customization.
Based on real experience and real
environments.
Another benefit that follows nicely from
design reuse with frameworks is
implementation reuse.
We didn't have to write the code to do the
synchronous and asychronous event
handling.
We didn't have to write the code to do all
those various concurrency models, things
like half sync half async, active object
leader followers, proactor and so on.
Those were handled for us by the framework
so the ability to take these elements off
the shelf and then apply them using
patterns to guide our design and
programming techniques, is a tremendous
productivity enhancer.
Yet another benefit that comes from
frameworks is the ability to be able to
reuse validation.
To paraphrase Dilbert, writing software is
easy.
The hard part of software is trying to get
that software to run reliably,
predictably, securely, efficiently,
reusably, modularly on the different
processors, the different platforms of
what you're trying to apply.
And that can often take a lot of work.
So one of the nice things about a
framework, or frameworks, is you can
amortize.
The testing and debugging effort over long
periods of time.
Especially if you avail yourselves of
modern techniques for quality assurance.
Things like test driven development,
continuous integration, and so on.
We've developed a number of capabilities
over the years that are part of our open
source release for ACE and Dow, and other
elements of our middleware.
And as you take a look at this slide and
take a look at the link that's shown at
the bottom of the slide, you can see that
we have a nice, interactive daily
scoreboard where it'll tell us what the
status is of our various software modules.
How many of the tests have succeeded, how
many of the tests have failed.
We can also go back and click through the
history of these various reports to find
out how things were a month ago, year ago.
The last major release, the last minor
release and so on and so forth.
So that greatly simplifies the way in
which we can do verification and
validation of the quality of our software.
And because we have a framework, or a set
of frameworks, it's worth investing the
time.
In building this regression testing
scaffolding, because we can leverage it
for many new things going forward.
So by the time you go to use a mature
framework, hopefully the bugs have been
found and fixed long ago by other people
who have been there before you.
There are, of course, a number of
limitations of frameworks and it's
important to be very honest and forthright
about these so you can make an informed
decision about what technologies to apply
for your projects.
One of the challenges with frameworks, of
course, is they can often be rather large.
And that means there's a big surface area
for you to navigate through it, for you to
understand, for you to learn how to
customize and tailor, and extend and
compose, and integrate to build your
particular applications.
Just as one example, the frameworks that
we've developed over the years for ACE and
other parts of our middle ware, are now
roughly around two million lines of code.
There are thousands of classes, there many
more thousands of methods in those
classes.
And you can imagine it, the average person
can't easily sit down and plow through
millions of lines of code in an afternoon
to figure out how all the peices fit
together, so there's clearly a learning
curve here.
How do you navigate through that learning
curve?
How do you master The complexity of
learning something that big.
Well obviously a good place to start is by
understanding the core architectural
patterns.
And a lot of the discussion that we've had
in this section has introduced you to the
core frameworks, the half a dozen or so
core frameworks.
And the couple scores of classes that are
important to make the most out of the
architectural elements in this reusable
body of software.
So that's one way of being able to deal
with the complexity and the scope is by
being able to narrow it down by focusing
on the strategic patterns and their core
models of structure and interactive
behavior.
Another sort of complexities with using
frameworks is the fact that they can be a
little bit tedious and challenging to
debug.
Why is this?
Well there's a number of reasons.
The use of polymorphism, both dynamic
polymorphism, polymorphism through
subclassing and overriding in methods.
The use of static polymorphism, templates
and parameterized types and so on means
that you often have a hard time figuring
out just exactly what your software does.
And you need to have a debugger that knows
how to work with templates, know how to be
able to make it easy to debug virtual
function calls and so, So on.
The use of inversion of control, which is
one of the hallmarks of a framework, can
be complicated, knowing where to set
breakpoints, knowing that when you set a
breakpoint and you get to a certain part
of your code, there may be a long stack of
activation records sitting underneath
where you are that you didn't necessarily
write but maybe necessary to understand to
some extent.
To make sense of why your program is not
working.
So having a feel for this, obviously
having a source code, can make a big
difference in debugging as well.
And naturally anytime you start spawning
threads, anytime you start doing
asynchronous processing, there are going
to be some serious complexities you have
to wrestle with because things are going
to take, they're going to run in different
orders.
There's an inherent non-determinism.
The way in which you debug your code may
be different from the way in which you run
it in a production environment.
Because running the debugger may change
some of the timing properties.
And these are all things you'll just have
to become accustomed to.
Fortunately, once you get familiar with
the frameworks, the patterns, the
interaction modes.
You start to develop a 6th sense of how to
do these debugging techniques.
You'll develop trick of the trade that can
help you be more successful.
In applying different ways of finding out
why things are going wrong.
And of course, if you're very lucky a lot
of the kind of bugs you ordinarily might
have had, because you wrote the code from
scratch, will have been handled by using a
framework or frameworks that have long
since been carefully tested and vetted to
remove those kinds of defects.
Another tricky issue with, related to
quality assurance and debugging, has to do
with the late binding nature of
frameworks.
We, we saw that to some extent with the
previous slide about polomorphisms various
forms and inversion of control.
But oftentimes when you go to framework
The framework's correctness or the
framework's performance is, to some
extent, a function of how it's composed,
how it's integrated, how the pieces are
plugged together and that may not be easy
to test when you're building the reusable
infrastructure itself.
Once again, it makes a lot of sense to
invest in test-driven development,
continuous integration, automated
regression test suites Various tools that
you can use to figure out how much of the
surface area of your source code is
actually checked by the regression tests
that you have.
And of course the goal should always be to
write new tests whenever defects are
found.
Write a regression test to check for those
things in the future, to make sure the
problems don't pop up again.
This slide illustrates some software that
we use with our open source.
Middleware in order to be able to check
whether or not the test cases are covering
large portions of the software.
That of course, is no guarantee of
success.
There are ways of customize and extending
our infrastructure that will lead to new
bugs that we have not anticipated.
Or new interactions that we did not
anticipate with our previous test.
But you also get a much better sense of
what's been tested.
As a general rule of thumb, if things
aren't tested, there are probably bugs
lurking in them and so that's a good
motivation to go and continually improve
and upgrade the infrastructure.
This is also a good way in which you can
leverage the benefits of crowd sourcing.
People will often come along, especially
in open source projects And provide new
text cases, provide ways of automating and
scripting how you check to see whether
certain conditions can be prevented or
certain conditions can be demonstrated to
not exist.
Another challenge with frameworks, of
course, is the fact that there are often
many different levels of indirection, and
they're complex structures with a number
of different layer involved, and if you're
not careful this can make your software
become big and bloated and difficult to
optimize and difficult to be able to meet
your end to end latency, through put,
jitter and other types of performance
requirements, dependability, security and
so on.
So one of the key things that's important
here is once again to try to find a way to
objectively and continuously monitor the
performance aspects of your software.
There is a variety of ways you can improve
things you can run profiling tools to look
for bottlenecks in critical paths and then
come up with various optimizations that
reduce the use of memory allocation or
locking in those critical path.
As the software grows in size and scope
and as more people get involved, it's also
important to make sure that you don't let
little inefficiencies creep in, some small
part at a time, that, individually, don't
add much overhead but when composed
together into an aggregate, it makes the
system becomes noticeably slower.
One of the things that we've been doing to
keep track of that and to try to avoid it
and alliviate it as quickly as possible Is
by running continuous regression
performance tests all the time with our
software.
We actually have a computer that we've
been using for quite a long time, a decade
or so, and we always run, every night, all
of our performance tests on that computer.
And then we graph the output as shown here
and we can tell at a glance whether things
are getting slower or faster as people
make changes to the middle ware, to the
source code, to the code base.
And this provides a good baseline to let
us know when things are starting to get
out of hand and we have to go back and
spend more time refactoring, reoptimizing
to bring the performance back to what was
expected.
And this of course is a continual process,
there's never one point where you declare
victory and all the overhead is gone, or
all the bugs are gone.
Once again important to automate this, to
leverage the cost deficiencies of
computing that you can use in an automated
regression test environment.
So to summarize this particular module,
patterns, frameworks, middle ware are all
very synergistic.
They leverage each other in effective
ways.
Patterns of course are particularly useful
to be able to reuse design knowledge and
design expertise in a way that people can
understand and learn and then hopefully
begin to apply to the code that they
develop, or the code that they integrate
from elsewhere.
Frameworks, in contrast, reuse more
implementation artifacts.
They reuse specific algorithms.
They reuse specific structures and
behaviors.
They reuse implementations.
Not surprisingly, there is a lot of
relationship between the frameworks you
develop these days and the patterns that
help to guide and document the design of
those frameworks.
And of course middle ware can really be
used as a common set of framework
capabilities that are exposed through
simpler, easier to use interfaces and
facades that emphasize clean lines, clean
demarcation, crisp boundaries for
application developers to work with, even
though under the hood, there may be quite
a number of intricate interactions and
dependencies and call back and concurrency
and so on, taking place within the
implementation of middle ware using the
frame One of the nice things these days is
that there are powerful feedback loops
that are helping to build on these
synergies.
Twenty, thirty years ago only a handful of
people really understood the concepts
we're describing here.
Nowadays you can read books on these
subjects, you can watch video lectures on
this subject.
You can see the culmination of decades of
bringing together patterns and frameworks.
In the form of the technologies that you
are working with on a day-to-day basis and
that, that is tremendously liberating it
provides a great boost to both
productivity, and quality, and performance
which we are starting to see today in the
off-the-shelf solutions that we use in
many environments.
So to rap things up One of the ways you
can think about patterns is how to become
much more effective at understanding how
to apply these powerful frameworks.
Both to build infrastructure, as well as
applications.
Patterns help you to build frameworks.
Patterns help you to use frameworks more
effectively.
Many of the most interesting patterns that
have been documented over the years have
grown up from people who were building and
applying frameworks in a wide variety of
interesting domains, and so it should be
no surprise there's a real tight synergy
and relationships between these different
technologies.
It also important to realize too that
patterns can be applied to many other
things besides frameworks.
We've been focusing on frameworks and the
relation of patterns to frameworks, cause
that's the subject of this course, but
there are many other technologies that are
not really framework based that are also
rich with patterns.
Just as one simple example, if you're a
fan of generic-programming the kinds of
things that you find with C++ standard
template library.
Boost other ways of using parameterized
types in effective ways, template
metaprogramming and so on.
There are also many, many patterns in that
space.
There are, some of the patterns, the Gang
of 4 patterns in particular, are also
applicable in things like STL and generic
programming.
Iterator, of course, strategy for
functors, factories for various things to
make iterators.
There's other patterns you'll see.
Adapters, there's lots and lots of use of
the adapter pattern in STL, and in C++
parameterized generic programming.
And so, don't think that the patterns
we've been talking about are only good if
you apply frameworks.
They're also useful for many other things
as well.
And needless to say, as you start trying
to apply some of these generic programming
paradigms.
With broader framework related
technologies, there're also patterns that
help to make those things work together
effectively too.
For example, the bridge pattern is
commonly used to be able to use ways of
taking object oriented objects and then
using them in the context of generic
algorithms and generic containers, and you
can use the bridge pattern to be able to
do very efficient copying, managing
reference counts.
Not exposing memory management out to the
application users, and so on and so forth.
So I hope that you've enjoyed all the
material that we've covered in this
section.
And I look forward to discussing with you
the various issues of patterns and
frameworks for concurrent and network
software through the various discussion
groups that we have at our disposal.