Welcome to part 3 in the module on
patterns and frameworks for asynchronous
event handling.
In previous parts of this module, we first
discussed the proactive pattern.
And then described how ACE provides a
framework called the proactive framework.
In order to implement this pattern in a
portable and efficient way on multiple
operating systems that support
asyncrhonous I/O.
Now, we're going to apply the ACE
proactive framework to JAWS to indicate
yet another path through our pattern
language for high performance web server.
This particular path is going to
demonstrate the use of asyncrhonous I/O.
As a way to be able to initiate
connections, handling of connections and
be able to handle asynchronous read and
write operations that take place after
asynchronous connections are completed and
established.
Let's first take a look at the archtecture
of our overall solution.
We'll be focusing primarily here on the
use of the ACE_Service_Handler and
ACE_Asynch_Acceptor.
As well as the ace proactive framework of
course in order to be able to carry out
this asynchronous processing.
If you take a look at these structures of
the solution it looks quite a bit like the
reactor pattern solution except unlike the
reactor pattern we're driving everything
by an asynchronous operation using
completion events as opposed to
synchronous operations using initiation
events.
Notice also that even though we only have
one thread of control in our solution, it
can still scale up quite nicely on
operating systems that sypport
asynchronous IO, such as Windows.
So let's first start talking about the
classes involved here.
We're going to implement a class called
the HTTP ACEsync handler which inherits
from ACE Service Handler.
And what this allows it to do is it allows
it to be able to implement various
asynchronous operations to implement the
HETP pro, protocol processing.
We define a number of data members, we
define a pointer to the ACE proactor, we,
we cache away to keep track of that
relationship.
We define a memory map file abstraction we
can use to efficiently keep track of files
that we map into memory.
We keep track of the handle.
That's the socket endpoint that we're
going to be connected to and so on.
And we also define something called HTTP
request.
Which is simply a little wrapper around
the ace message block abstraction, that's
used by the ace proactor framework.
To be able to send the received data very
efficiently without having to copy large
chunks of data, and be able to deal with
things very fast with respect to chaining
messages together.
We also have a pair of data members here
that are an a, a sync read stream.
And, and a, Asynch right stream.
And we will use these to invoke
asynchronous read and write operations
respectively.
In order to carry out the processing
without blocking the server thread for the
duration of the call.
Lets now take a look at the open hook.
This is the hook method called back by the
HTTP_Asynch_Acceptor in order to be able
to activate our HTTP_Asynch_Handler once
the connection has been established
passively.
What this particular approach does is it
first opens the read stream.
And it associates with the read stream the
handle that we're reading on, as well as a
reference to this object, which will be
used to indicate where the completion
events need to be sent to when the
asychronous read operation is done.
We then turn around and kick off the
asynchronous read operation, passing in
the message buffer that we've allocated to
store the results that come back from,
from the client application.
Here then is the handle read stream hook
method, which is dispatched by the
proactor framework when that asynchronous
read operation that we initiated
completes.
We'll talk shortly about how the
connection is made between the initiation
of the asynchronous read operation and
this completion event hook method that
gets dispatched by the proactor framework.
But be that as it may, assume it gets
called back and what we do now is we go
ahead and check to see whether or not we.
You've gotten a complete request from the
client and if we have gotten the complete
request, we're going to go ahead and
handle that complete request.
If we have not gotten a complete request,
if we've only got part of a request, then
we go ahead and reinitiate an asynchronous
operation in order to get the complete
request and this may take place actually
for a number of cycles until we're able to
read the entire request form the client.
Assuming we've got the complete request
then the handler request method is called,
and this is going to do a couple things.
The first thing it does is it checks to
see what kind of requests we've received,
so keep in mind these things are initiated
asynchronously and we could have
asynchronous receives for get request post
requests, put requests and so on.
Let's assume for the sake of argument that
we've got a get request.
So if we have a get request, what we do in
that case is going to be very familiar.
We take the filename that we got, that
came in the request from the client that
we extracted out of the stream once it was
read asynchronously.
We memory map that file and then we turn
around and we initiate an asynchronous
write operation.
This asynchronous write operation of
course will attempt to send the entire
file back to the client asynchronously.
Notice that we've used a write operation.
We could also have used the transmit file
mechanism.
Transmit file is a very interesting
mechanism available with Windows, and also
available on a number of other.
Posix machines and Unix machines now via
the send file system call.
And what it does is it takes open file
handles.
An open file handle to an open file.
An open file handle to an open socket.
And it does an asynchronous operation to
transmit the entire content of the file to
the socket in one fell swoop.
So that's a nice way of being able to use
and leverage the underlying hardware and
device driver mechanisms for efficient
data transfer.
Things like device memory mapped I/O and
various kinds of other ways of
transmitting data without Incurring
contact switches copies and other kinds of
overhead that you typically incur if you
did this one buffer or one chunck at a
time.
Here is the HTTP async receptor it
inherents from ACE acceptor ACE asynch
acceptor .
The Ace asynch acceptor works very much
like The way that the acceptor connector
framework did earlier.
When we talked about the ACE acceptor and
ACE connector.
You can basically parametarized it with a
kind of service handler that you want to
have it create.
In this case, it's an HTTP_Asynch_Handler
and this then serves as a factory for
passively accepting connections.
Initializing the handlers and then being
able to have those handlers activated to
do their thing.
In this particular case, the constructor
for the HTTP_Asynch_Acceptor will simply
delegate up to the underlying
ACE_Asynch_Acceptor and call its open
method and this open method takes a number
of parameters.
The key parameters it takes are the
address it wants to listen on for incoming
connections, typically port 80 in our
case, and it also indicates some other
things.
It indicates whether or not it should go
ahead and invoke certain operations such
as asynchronous accept calls, and it says
how many of these calls should be invoked?
For example in this case, we're going to
have some kind of backlog number of them,
perhaps five, that will kick off
simultaneously.
And it will also indicate that we're going
to keep re re-initiating these calls
automatically as they're being connected
with a client.
So we'll always have a number of
asynchronistic set calls that are ready to
go in case a client connects to our
server.
We also pass in the proactor, and that's
in order to get access to the IO
completion port that it holds internally.
That it uses in order to match up the
completion events with the original
requests that were invoked asynchronously.
So a lot of things going on in a simple
constructor.
But you don't have to really worry about
the details.
That's all handled for you internally by
the ACE Proactor framework.
Finally we have our main program, as you
can see, it's very simple not unlike the
reactor examples we've looked at before.
What we do is go ahead and set up the
addressing to listen on port That's
important for the web server like port 80.
Then we create ourselves an instance of
the HTTP_Asynch_Acceptor passing in that
Internet address passing in the proactor.
As you just saw that will kick off the
asynchronous accept operations.
However that is done on a particular
platform and after those asynchronous
accept operations are kicked off Then we
go and run the main proacter event loop.
And all that does is it just sits there,
waiting for completion events to occur as
clients connect and as read operations,
right operations that were invoked,
asynchronistly complete.
As well as of course, other accept
operations that may complete likewise.
So that's really all there is to it, very
simple, very streamlined way of writing
the server program.
As I've often said, it's sometimes a
little bit hard to understand the
interactions between various pieces by
looking purely at source code.
So here's a sequence diagram that
illustrates the various interactions
between the components that I've
demonstrated.
And illustrated in the previous code.
So as we see here, the web server starts
out by creating an HTTP a sync acceptor.
And that will go ahead and initiate the a
sync accept operation on the underlying
asynchronous operating processor,
operation processor, such as the operating
system like windows or Posics that
supports.
Ports, asynchronous I/O, it then turns
over control to the proactor.
And when a connection shows up, callbacks
are driven to the HTTP async acceptor in
order to create an appropriate HTTP async
handle.
So that's all part of the.
Service initialization, and connection
establishment phase.
Once that connection has been established,
and the handler's been created, from that
point onwards, for the duration of that
particular conversation with the client,
we will then drive the communication by
asynchronous read, and asynchronous write
operation calls.
So we'll do an asynchronous read call to
get the data from the client.
And we'll do asynchronous right calls once
we've received the URI in order to be able
to transmit that back and you can see if
you carefully at the sequence diagram the
various ways in which the pieces talk back
and forth to each other to carry out the
processing in a solely asynchronous
manner.
So to summarize this part of the module.
The ACE proactor framework alleviates some
of the bottlenecks with reactive I/O
because things can run asynchronously, we
could also have some threads in a pool to
kick off new asynchronous operations in a
concurrent way.
This also can alleviate some of the
complexities.
Of synchronous multi threading because we
can write our programs often to have few
or no locks required because everything's
driven asynchronously and all the
concurrency handled largely inside the
operating system in kernel.
The framework allows applications to
invoke I/O operations asynchronously In 2
canonical phases.
The first phase is the initiation phase,
where they kick off the operations on the
asynchronous operation processor such as
Windows, doing things like accept EX or
read file, write file EX, and so on.
These are all operations that are part of
Windows.
We can abstract away, of course, using.
The ACE proactor to hide those details.
But under the hood, that's what's being
used.
So that's how we kick the operations off
asynchronously.
And then the second phase is Ryanwhen
those operations complete, we can go ahead
and handle the demultiplexing and
dispatching of those completion events
back to the appropriate completion event
handlers.
Which in our case would be the acceptor
and the various asynch handlers To do
reading and writing of the actual data
from the clients.
So that, that illustrates how we can apply
this particular pattern in the context of
Jaws, using the ACE proactor framework and
next we'll talk about yet another pattern
that's often combined with proactor in
order to handle the multiplexing of
responses for completion of[UNKNOWN] very
efficiently.