Welcome to Part 7 in the module on
Patterns and Frameworks for Concurrency
and Synchronization.
In previous parts of this module, we
described the active object pattern and
illustrated the ways in which you can
implement active object using the ACE Task
Framework.
And then apply the ACE Task Framework to
implement a thread per connection
concurrency model implementation of the
JAWS Web Server.
We then move on and talk about the
Half-Sync/Half-Async pattern and
illustrated how that pattern can be
implemented, using some of the frame work
in ace as well.
What we're going, what we then did is we
described the Monitor Object pattern and
talked about how we could use monitor
object to apply it to a portion of the
Half-Sync/Half-Async solution in order to
implement a synchronized request queue.
What we're going to do in this part of the
module is we're going to explore how we
might Apply monitor object along with a
number of other synchronization patterns
to implement the ACE Message Queue class.
And use this in order to flesh out a bit
more of our pattern language relating to
scaleability in a multi-threaded or
multi-cole environment.
Let's first start by talking a bit more
about what we need to have an ACE Message
Queue class for in the first place.
So it turns out when producer and consumer
threads interact with each other in
concurrent programs, there's often a need
to be able to exchange messages within.
A process address space.
Typically a producer task will create
messages and then insert them or, or pass
them off to consumer tasks.
And those consumer tasks will then either
process them immediately.
Or more likely do a little bit of
processing or no processing at all.
And then stick those messages on to a
thread safe message queue.
Queue.
If the queue is full, then the producers
typically wait.
Either they block indefinitely or they
block for a certain time-out period.
And likewise, if the message queue is
empty, then the consumer thread or threads
will either block indefinitely or block
for some bounded amount of time.
Waiting to see if there's some more work
showing up for them.
So that's kind of the, the background of,
of why you need an ACE Message Queue and
sort of how it interacts with other pieces
in the system.
When we implement ACE Message Queue,
there's a number of pieces that it
involves.
One piece is the message itself, and we
call this the ACE Message Block.
The purpose of the ACE Message Block is to
be able to manage the memory of the
message in a very efficient way, allowing
us to do a couple of things.
First, it allows us to be able to support
reference counting.
So if we end up having to use a message
that's held from a couple of different
parts of our solution, say, in a
re-transmit buffer.
We can do reference counting to be able to
make a logical copy of the message.
Without having to physically copy the data
itself.
So that's much more efficient.
Another thing you can do with an ACE
Message Block, is you can also chain
together a sequence of ACE Message Blocks
to form some kind of composite message,
which can be useful in situations where
you're dealing with a lot of network
protocol messages.
Where you have to add headers and, and
trailers to them.
And you want to be able to do this again
without having to copy the messages
repeatedly.
Another thing you can do with an ACE
message block is it's got next and
previous pointers and so you can actually
chain together groups of ACE Message
Blocks, which themselves may be composite
messages.
In order to be able to provide a doubly
linked list that will be use for the ACE
Message Queue that we'll talk about in
just a moment.
Another thing you can do with an ACE
Message Block is, you can treat
synchronization and memory management
issues as aspects.
And you can change the locks.
You can change where the memory comes from
without changing the logic of the class
itself.
This composite structure, as a general
rule, is intended to minimize data
copying.
So you could often get by without having
to do a full copy of the data.
And you only have to update reference
counts in various ways.
This particular abstraction handles the
variability of messaging operations via a
common interface.
An ACE Message Queue is really nothing
more than a double link list of ACE
Message Blocks with a number of other
mechanisms thrown in for good measure.
In order to make it easier to work with
this as a cohesive abstraction.
For example, there are operations on an
ACE Message Queue to be able to en-queue
and de-queue messages at the head or the
tail.
And you can also go ahead and en-queue
messages in so called priority order.
Such that when you de-queue them, the
message of highest priority is always the
1 that will be at the front of the queue.
Something else you can do with an ACE
message queue, and it depends a bit on the
synchronization properties we're about to
talk about, is you can also do timed
operations.
If the queue is full, for example, you can
have it blocked until the queue is no
longer full.
Now this concept of being able to block or
not depends on something called the
synchronization strategy that is
configured Into the ACE Message Queue.
And this is, again, done as an aspect
using the strategy pattern and using c
plus, plus templates.
And so as we'll see, and this will cover
actually the bulk of the discussion
throughout this part of the module, we can
embody or configure an ACE Message Queue.
In a couple of different configurations.
1 configuration is single threaded.
Which means that it never blocks.
It just fails if its empty or full.
Another configuration is multi threaded.
To use a multi threaded synchronization
strategy.
This is the way we would typically do it,
of course, when we implement the
Half-Sync/Half-Async.
Pattern and we need to have a synchronized
request queue.
In this case, it will end up being able to
block under certain circumstances, which
we will talk about in just a moment.
Some other thing you can do with the
master queue, you can control its
synchronization strategy.
You can also control where its memory
allocation comes from.
So it can come from different alocators,
that may be allocate, there are different
types of pools Memory.
What this particular class does, from a
commonality and variability point of view,
is it handles the variability of queuing
and synchronization mechanisms of queuing
behind a common interface.
And we'll talk about why we do this as we
go throughout this part of the module.
So let's first start talking about this
notion of being able to transparently
Parameterize synchronization into a, a
class.
Like, ACE Message Queue.
The various concurrency patterns we've
talked about before give you a hint here
that you might want to keep certain
components fixed with respect to their
functional behavior.
But be able to change their
synchronization strategies depending on
how it is they're being used.
So it might turn out in some situations,
we just need have a, a queue to store data
but we don't need to have that be
synchronized or thread safe.
Conversely, when start trying to work with
the half-synch half-asynch pattern, we
need to have a synchronized request queue.
Queue.
Well you can imagine doing things in a
couple of inadequate ways, or, or
dysfunctional ways.
One approach would be to try to maintain
multiple copies of queues that were
customized and hard-coded for different
synchronization use cases.
For example, we might have a
non-synchronized message queue that has no
locks in it Whatsoever.
Conversley we might have a synchronized
message queue that has a bunch of locks in
it.
Well.
The problem when you start trying to do
this is now you have to manage these
different variance manually and that means
that when you make changes in one you have
to make sure you go make changes in the
other.
As you add new features, you have to make
sure those are added.
As you fix bugs you have to go and fix
them in multiple places and that quickly
becomes unwieldy.
What's a more effective approach?
Apply the strategize locking pattern.
This pattern is a pattern that appears in
the[UNKNOWN] book and I'll give you a link
to a paper where it appears as well.
And basically what it does is it allows
you to treat synchronization as a first
class citizen from an aspect perspective
and you can strategize different
synchronization mechanisms via a common
interface.
So we can use that to keep say ACE Message
Queue fixed and then change its
synchronization properties without
changing its, other parts of its
implementation.
Take a look at this URL for more
information about this particular pattern,
which again appears in the[UNKNOWN] two
book as well.
I, here's a way to apply this particular
pattern to ACE_Message_Queue.
We, we follow a couple of steps here.
The first step is to strategize.
The locking mechanism.
So if you take a look at this particular
class which is a snippet from the
ACE_Message_Queue class, what it does is
it makes the synchronization strategy a
template.
And then we can use various traits from
the template parameter that's passed in,
in order to get the appropriate kind of
synchronization strategy that we want with
respect to mutual exclusion.
As well as various condition operations
for the not empty and not full conditions.
Here's an example of how to define some of
the different trait classes we might have.
You notice here that we have two trait
classes that are built in from scratch.
You're welcome to add more of course,
because it's extensible One model is the
ACE_NULL_SYNCH class and this has nothing
but a bunch of no-op traits that do
nothing they're the Null_Mutex, the
Null_Condition, the Null_Semaphore using
the null object pattern.
The ACE_MT_SYNCH, in contrast, that
particular traits class, has real
synchronizers it uses ACE_Thread_Mutex.
Ace condition.
It uses ACE thread semaphore and so on.
And each of these provides real mechanisms
that can be used in a threaded
environment, in order to work
appropriately to lock, and wait, and
notify when things change, that are
important.
Notice by using trades class is that it
doesn't require us to have any common base
class or even use any virtual methods at
all.
We can simply use the magic of C++'s
signature based type conforments and the
template policy mechanisms in order to
parameterize the way in which we use these
with ACE Message Queue.
Speaking of which, let's take a look now
at how we could use these trait classes to
instantiate the appropriate variant of
ACE_Message_Queue depending on what it is
we're trying to do.
If we don't need synchronization at all,
we can simply provide a no-op synchronizer
like ACE_NULL_SYNCH and that traits class
and that means anytime you try to dequeue
from a queue that's empty It won't block,
it'll just fail.
Conversely, if we apply the ACE MT sync
traits class to make a message queue.
And we define an instance of 1 of those
types of, of, synchronized objects.
Then, when you do a DQ head on empty
queue.
That will block until somebody puts
something into the queue to allow it to be
able to continue.
So the nice thing here is the logic
remains the same, but we're changing the
synchronization mechanisms via the
strategy and the strategized locking
pattern.
I show an example here that's using
templates and it's a basically static
typing and early binding.
It's also a common practice to use some
kind of base class with a common method.
With virtual methods in order to be able
to plug these things in at run time as
well.
The benefits with the template approach
there's less overhead.
The downside it's less flexible.
The benefits with the virtual methods and
inheritence approach is it's more flexible
at run time, but there's a bit more
overhead.
Whether that overhead matters for you of
course is up to your profiling and
architects to decide.
So let's talk about some of the pros and
cons of strategized locking.
The benefits is it enhances flexibility
and customization.
You can change the different locking
mechanisms very flexibly without having to
modify the behavior of your class.
That means you have less work to maintain,
different variants, because they all exist
in one place.
And you just strategize locking You can
think of this as a glorified example of
the strategy pattern applied to the
context of synchronization.
It also, to some extent, can improve reuse
because now you can have these reusable
components that can be strategized for
different use cases and different
contexts.
And it's a very simple thing to do.
Of course there are some downsides.
One of the problems is that the locking
now moves out to the interface of the
class.
And sometimes you want the locking
mechanisms to be secret so people, they
don't, don't even know that they exist
unless makes them more overt, more
obtrusive, even also think of this as
being a bit over engineered.
If you're not careful, people can do it
wrong.
They can put in the wrong kind of locks
and things will fail in somewhat subtle
And pernicious ways.
We'll talk about a couple of other
patterns shortly to help reduce the risk
of that occurring.
But it's always a risk.
So that was basically scoped.
That was basically the strategized locking
pattern and applying it to the ACE Message
Queue.
Let's now talk about another dimension of
synchronization that corresponds to what
we just described.
This is ensuring that locks are released
properly.
If you start writing single-threaded code,
then.
Releasing locks is a, a non issue.
When you begin to write multi threaded
code, of course.
Releasing locks is a big deal.
And if you don't release locks properly,
you could end up with dead lock, or other
kinds of inefficiencies in your solution.
This is a particularly tricky thing when
we start trying to apply things like
strategized locking, where it's not always
clear whether we're locking things for
real or not.
'Because we might have null locks.
Or recursive locks or nonrecursive locks
and so on.
But in any case, we have to write the code
that acquires a lock on the entry to a
critical section and releases it on the
way out.
And if we're not careful and we write the
code like it's shown on this slide, some
bad things can happen.
In particular, if something goes A miss in
the implementation of this method, this
method is the DQ head method, then, we
might not actually release the lock on all
exit paths out of this method.
For example, if it does a return, that
lock might not be released, if it does, if
an exception is thrown, the lock might not
be released and so on and so forth.
If a goto or a break statement is called,
for example The lock may not be released.
So how can we ensure that these locks are
always released properly?
Well, we're going to apply the Scoped
Locking pattern.
And this pattern will make it possible to
use some features of object oriented
languages, where constructors acquire
resources, and destructors release them,
to ensure that the scope over which things
are applied, will always properly acquire
and release the locks Automatically.
You can take again, take a look at this
particular paper for more information
about this pattern.
So let's talk about how we might apply
scope blocking to the ACE Message Queue
implementation.
What we're going to do is we're going to
define a guard class.
This particular one happens to be part of
ACE, but you could do the same thing if
you didn't use ACE.
And this guard class, which is a template
class, Follows a very simple protocol.
It's coructor is going to acquire a lock
that corresponds to the parameter that's
passed into the template.
And its destructor is going to release
that lock.
So when we come in, the constructor
acquires a lock.
And the destructor releases the lock.
Thereby insuring that we always are going
to release the lock, whether or not we
have an exception or a return or a goto or
anything else that will allow that scope
to be exited.
The ACE guard that we show here as a
helper class also illustrates another
reason why wrapper facades are so
powerful.
Notice that we're using the wrapper Facade
mechanisms for ACE Thread Mutex, ACE
Semaphore, ACE Reader/Writer locks and so
on.
And all of those have the same interface.
They all have acquire and release methods.
And so, all we have to be able to do to
use all these different mechanisms is
create.
A parameterized guard class.
Which is a helper class.
That implements the scoped locking
pattern.
And then we can parameterize it with a
particular type of the wrapper facade.
If you were just using functions, it would
be much more complicated to work this way.
So once again wrapper facades provide
building blocks for more powerful
Composition and capabilities with
object-oriented designs.
The next thing we do is we let the
critical sections correspond to the scope
and lifetime of these guard objects.
Here's an illustration using the DQ head
method that we had in the message queue
from before.
Now what we do when we come in is we use
the scope locking pattern in order to be
able to automatically acquire the lock in
its constructor.
And then no-matter how we leave the scope,
short of crashing the program, that lock
is going to automatically be released,
which is much more powerful and much more
fool proof.
You're not going to make as many mistakes
because it automatically cleans things up.
You can allocate instances of the ace
guard on the stack so they're very
lightweight, they don't require any
dynamic memory allocation and they just
grab the lock on entry and release the
lock on exit to a scope.
There's a number of benefits of course to
using this particular pattern.
It makes things more robust because.
You can eliminate this common source of
overheads where you have the mistake of
forgetting to release the locks or, or
jumping out of this scope too quickly and
having problems.
This of course is really an embodiment of
a broader C++ idiom called resource
acquisition is initialization or RAII.
And you can read more about RAII.
Here at the Wikipedia site.
There are some limitations with this,
using this particular pattern.
One of the problems is that you can end up
with dead lock if you use this
recursively.
We'll talk a bit more about how to get
around this particular problem, but if you
have self recursive calls you can end up
with dead lock on a recursive, on a
non-recursive mutex which could be a
problem.
And there's also some language semantics
issues.
We're using.
C plus, plus programming language
features.
And while that will work for certain
things, it doesn't know about low level
features that are available in the
operating system to do, to do things like
exit threads by thread exit calls.
Or do long jumps using set jump and long
jump mechanisms.
So, if you're not careful you could still
find some way to subvert.
The ability to release the locks
automatically.
But at least this gives you a fighting
chance for the common case.
The next, and last, part of this
particular part of the module will
describe one of the consequences of
apllying the strategized locking pattern.
If you think about strategized locking, it
was encouraging you to make the locking
mechanism.
A policy or a strategy that you can
parameterize with your components.
So for example, now we have an ACE Message
Queue or we can parameterize the
particular type of locking mechanisms that
we use.
The strategy for that.
The tricky part here is if you have
Obstructions, classes like
ACE_Message_Queue that have intra-object
method calls.
You have to watch out for two things.
The first thing you need to watch out for
is not incurring unnecessary sources of
locking that aren't strictly necessary or
needed and the second problem you have to
watch out for is ending up with
self-deadlock.
So let's take a look and see how this
might arise.
So here we have an example where we've got
the dequeue head method and depending on
the type O lock that's strategized into
the ACE Message Queue, you're either going
to have extra overhead in this example or
you'll have self deadlock.
Why is this?
Well, the reason this is the case is
because the dq head method in this
implementation.
First acquires the lock using the guard
and then it calls is empty to check to see
whether or not the queue is empty or
not.Is empty as you can see is an
interface method that also acquires the
lock and then it goes to check to see if
there's any bytes in the, in the queue.
What the problem there is if we give this
thing a nonrecursive mutex.
It will self-deadlock and even if we give
it a recursive mutex, we'll still have an
extra level of locking that really isn't
strictly necessary, which increases the
overhead.
So how can we avoid this particular
problem?
Well, we'll apply another pattern.
This is called the Thread-safe Interface
pattern.
And this pattern is used to minimize
Unnecessary locking, and ensure that
intra-component or object method calls
don't end up incurring self-deadlock.
So let's talk a little bit about how this
pattern works.
What it does is it splits the world up
into 2 parts.
It has interface methods that check and do
very little work.
And it has Implementation methods that
trust and do work.
And Implementation methods only call other
Implementation methods.
By organizing things this way we can have
the interface methods acquire the locks,
and then call down to Implementation
methods to do the actual heavy lifting,
and do the actual logic.
Those implementation methods assume Trust
the locks are held.
They do the work and they only ever call
other implementation methods.
This pattern also appears in POSA2 and you
can read more about it at the URL at the
bottom of this particular slide.
Let's see how we can refactor our code to
apply thread-safe interface To
ACE_Message_Queue.
What we can do in this case is we can
split things up a little bit.
Instead of having the dequeue_head method
call is_empty, which is an interface
method, instead, it acquires the lock and
then it calls down to the is_empty_i
method, is_empty_i is the implementation
method.
As you can see Is empty I, is a private
It's not public.
It trusts that it aws called in a context
that the lock was properly held.
And it actually does some work.
In this particular case, it just checks to
see if there's some counts or zero.
And doesn't do any other work.
But if it was actually doing some other
work.
It would only be able to call other
implementation methods, not call out to
the interface methods.
This pattern, as you can see, allows a
broader range of syncronization strategies
to be used without running afoul of those
issues of self-deadlock and additional
overhead.
So to talk about some of the benefits and
limitations of this pattern.
The key benefit, of course, is increased
robustness.
We can avoid having to worry about this
self deadlock issue.
We avoid extra calls that are going to be
unnecessary, and, and cause additional
locks.
Even if it's going to work with the use of
recursive locks.
We may be able to enhance performance by
doing that.
And we can simplify the software by
decoupling out the locking logic from the
business logic.
And that may have some other benefits as
well, by being able to think more clearly
about what your business logic is.
Naturally there's some downsides, as
always.
There's additional indirection and there's
lots of extra methods.
For every interface method that matters
you may also have a corresponding set of
implementation methods.
So that means your, your interface, your
Surface area of your class will go up even
though the public interface may remain the
same.
There's also of course the potential for
misuse.
In some ob, object oriented languages like
C++ and Java, they have class level access
control as opposed to object level access
control.
So it's potentially possible to peek
around and access things you're not
supposed to in those environments.
So you have to be careful how you use this
pattern, you have to check and ensure that
people are not violating the rules in any
malicious or accidental way.
So this particular set of patterns has
helped to explain ways in which we can
take what ACE Message Queue provides us,
with respect to a queuing mechanism, and
then use the monitor object in conjunction
with strategized locking.
Scope locking and threads save interface
to make the ACE Message Queue much more
reusable, much more flexible, much more
configurable for a wide range of contexts.
In which we're likely to use it, including
of course for Half-Sync/Half-Async
implementation that we use for the JAWS
Web Server.