Welcome to Part One in the module on
Patterns and Frameworks for Asynchronous
Event Handling.
In this first part of the module we're
going to discuss the proacter pattern.
If you think about what we've been
describing in the various modules we've
covered to this point, the composition of
what we've focused on has largely been on
either synchronous event handling, using
various variants of the reactor pattern.
As well as synchronous multithreading.
Using patterns like active object, or half
sync, half a sync.
The half a sync part we looked at also
used the reactor patterns.
So that also used synchronous event to
multiplexing.
These approaches work pretty well.
But it turns out that in some
environments, in some operating systems.
Synchronous event handling and synchronous
multithreading are not the most efficient
or scalable way to take advantage of the
operating system resources.
In those type environments, they support
some from of asynchronous I/O, which can
be used more effectively in some
conditions.
For example, on the Windows platform, they
support something called I/O completion
ports and overlapped I/O which allows you
to invoke a number of asynchronous
operations such as asynchronous accept
calls or asynchronous reads or
asynchronous write operations.
And when these operation's complete, the
results of the operations are stored in
something called an I/O completion port.
Which is essentially a queue managed by
the operating system kernel.
And 1 or more threads of control can wait
to pull the completion events out of that
port, and then handle the despatching of
those clea, completion events.
To do whatever they require in order to
take care of the operation that's
finished, based on the success or failure
or contents of the results.
That were passed back.
While these approaches tend to be very
scaleable, there's a number of challenges
when trying to program them.
When you start trying to program
Asynchronous I/O, there's a number of
complexities that arise because of the
separation in time and space where
operations are invoked and where
completions occur.
So how can we address this particular set
of challenges?
We're going to apply the Proactor pattern.
In order to be able to more effectively
and efficiently handle asynchronous I/O on
operating system platforms that have good
support for this capability.
The proactor pattern can be used to allow
asynchronous I/O operations to run.
Providing scalability without incurring
some of the complications and accidental
complexities of programming with
multi-threads and synchronous event
Handling.
Let's talk a bit about this pattern.
This pattern is somewhat complicated.
There's a number of pieces in it, and you
have to understand them in order to make
sense of how the various parts
interrelate.
The initial portion of the pattern starts
with something called an initiator.
An initiator might be the main program, it
might be another thread of control.
And its job is to invoke asynchronous
operations.
It invokes these asynchronous operations
on an asynchronous operation processor.
Typically, an operating system.
But it could be some kind of a proxy or
facade that was im-, implemented to
emulate asynchronous IO in an operating
system.
When you invoke an asynchronous operation.
You do it on a handle, such as a socket
handle or a file handle.
And you also pass along with that
operation some type of completion handler,
which is typically a pointer.
And all this information is then bundled
together, given to the operating system,
and it goes ahead and runs the operations.
When those operations finish, then they
are placed by the operating system into An
I/O completion report or some kind of
completion event que and then we use a
proactor to demultiplex a completion
results and turn them back into calls on
concrete completion handlers that do
whatever work is necessary to clean up
perhaps reinitiate perhaps asynchronous
operations perhaps transmit files Do other
kinds of operations and so on and so
forth.
If you take a look at the URL at the
bottom of this slide you'll find out more
about the proactor pattern, which also of
course appears in the posted tool book.
Let's talk a bit about the dynamics of the
interactions here.
The dynamics typically work as follows.
You start out by initiating some number of
asynchronous operations.
Typically asynchronous accepts or perhaps
asynchronous reads.
You then turn the flow of control over to
the proactor framework.
Which is actually driven by inversion of
control.
Clients will then go ahead and initiate
various kinds of requests to your server,
to your service, or your application.
And as that happens, the proactor is
responsible for handling the completion of
these asynchronous operations
corresponding to the client request.
And then doing the various.
Dispatching and demultiplexing to the
completion handlers to get the work done.
There's a number of similarities and
differences between reactor and proactor,
there both driven by call-backs, so in
that way they're the same.
The primary differences, is that the
reactor works on so called initiation
events.
These are events where you ask the reactor
framework Is it okay to read without
blocking?
Is it okay to accept without blocking?
And if it turns out that it's okay to read
or accept or connect or whatever operation
you're doing, then you can go ahead and
initiate that operation.
So these are essentially initiation events
with the reactor.
In contrast, with the proactor pattern,
what you're dealing with are completion
events.
Some has told the, the proactor start this
operation, run this command, invoke this
operation to read or write or accept and
when that operation is done the proactor
calls you back and says here you go.
Here are the results.
So it's really a difference between
initiation and completion events that
differentiate the These patterns.
Let's talk about how we could apply the
proactor pattern to our JAWS web server.
And we'll look at some other
implementations after we talked about the
proactor framework in other parts of this
module.
This particular example starts as follows.
We will have the main application.
Create some kind of HTTP acceptor which
uses asynchronous I/O to invoke
asynchronous accept calls on the operating
system and you would typically invoke a
number of these, maybe, say five or so.
Those operations then go and wait for
someone to connect to the server.
When a client comes along and connects
That will cause a completion event to
occur.
The operating system, the device driver
will work together in order to handle the
accept operation and then it will return a
completion event that says accept complete
back the HTTP acceptor.
The HTTP acceptor Then turns around and
creates an HTTP handler.
And this http handler then initiates an
asynchronous read operation and returns
control back to the proactor event loop.
Later, when the client sends over a get
request, that get request shows up as a
completion event for the read call that
was invoked earlier by the http handler.
The proactor will dispatch that event back
to the handler, that handler will then
look inside the event and figure out what
the URI is that's being requested by the
client and perhaps memory map that file,
and then intiate and asynchronous write
operation to write the event back to the
client.
When that write operation completes, when
the file is entirely set Then, yet another
completion event would be generated.
And that will cause the HTTP handler to
shut itself down.
Some things to note anbout this particular
pattern , is that almost all operations
are driven by a-synchro-SAO.
Which run in the operating system kernel
context.
And only for brief periods of time, are
call-backs invoked to the application or
the service.
In order to do whatever works is
necessary.
To re-initiate yet another asynchronous
operation.
So the application code actually has very
little to do and typically doesn't block,
it initiates asynchronous operations to
complete the various states that it's
transitioning to when carrying out the
processing requests.
Let's talk a bit about the benefits and
limitations to this pattern.
Much like the reactor pattern, one of the
benefits of this proactor approach is the
ability to separate concerns.
We can cleanly differentiate between these
different roles the initiation of events,
the completion of events, the accepting,
the connecting, the reading, the writing
and so on.
Part of the other benefit that we get is
portability.
It's possible to port implementations of
the proactive pattern to a wide variety of
different operating systems which have
radically different support for
asynchronous IO under the hood.
Another benefit is we're able to decouple
concurrency from the use of threading.
Because operating systems that support
asynchronous IO often have a very high
performance support within the OS kernel
and the device driver frameworks.
You can typically get very good
performance without having to rely on
using a lot of threads.
You may only need one thread of control.
Or just a handful of threads to handle
different completions and then kick off
new asynchronious operations.
So you can get concurrency without
incurring the complexity and
synchronization overhead and so on, of
multi-threading Likewise, there's another
performace benefit that comes by being
able to avoid a lot of context switching.
Ypu trypically don't have seperate threads
that are sitting there blocking on I/O
operations.
You simply have things kick off
asyncrhonous operations and maybe the
proactor thread waits for the completion
events to come back to it to do the next
phase in the transfer.
And yet another benefit you can greatly
simplify the application synchronization
logic.
Often times applications don't need any
synchronization because there's only one
thread of control and everything's being
driven by Asynchronous I/O running largely
in the context of the operating system
kernel.
Naturally of course there's some
limitations with this pattern.
First and foremost, if you don't have an
operating system that supports asynchronus
I O natively, or if you have and operating
system that supports asynchronus I O
inefficently, or in a buggy fashion, then
you're going to have a hard time really
being able to leverage this pattern.
Another problem that arises here is a
typical problem that occurs whenever you
have concurrency, asynchrony, separation
in time and space of invocations and
completions and so on, and that's
additional complexity with respect to
testing, debugging, validation and so on.
Clearly, knowledge of the pattern can help
you understand these roles and
relationships and interactions much more
effectively.
And the last limitation with this pattern
is that you don't often have a lot of
control over the order in which these
asynchronous events execute.
If the asynchronous events need to
complete in a certain order to carry out
some, some kind of collaborative task.
Then you're going to have to provide some
sort of reassembly buffer to take the
results, and reassemble them somehow,
before you can go on to the next phase of
your processing.
Another complexity that you sometimes have
to deal with is it may be difficult to
cancel an operation once its begun.
And some operating systems don't support
cancellation.
Other operating systems support it in a
limited way, or you may have situations
where there are race conditions between
cancelling things and actually knowing
when they're finished so you can clean up
the various resources.
So that completes our quick overview of
the proactor pattern and then in the
remainder of this module we'll talk about
ways to implement this particular pattern
and apply it in a more detailed way to our
jaws web server.