Welcome to part 9 in the module on
patterns and frameworks for concurrency
and synchronization.
In previous parts of this module, we
started by describing the active object
pattern.
Discussed ways in which you can implement
active objects using the ACE task
framework.
And then applied the ACE task framework,
along with some other frameworks in ACE,
to implement a thread per connection
version of active objects for our Jawsweb
server.
Next we described the Half-Syn/Half-Async
pattern, which generalizes and makes more
scalable the active objects.
And we illustrated how you can apply
various ACE frameworks in order to
implement Half-Sync/Half-Async for our
Jaws web server.
We then focused in on a particular set of
patterns that relate to synchronization
and trying to have a synchronized request
queue in Half-Sync/Half-Async, discussing
the monitor object pattern and a number of
other synchronization patterns to help
monitor object be applied Successfully in
the context of thee ACE message cue class
which we use to provide a request cue
between the different layers in a
Half-Sync,/Half-Async solution.
And now we're describing the leader
followers pattern.
The previous part of this module described
the pattern, now we're illustrating how we
can apply the leader followers pattern.
Using the ACE thread pool reactor
mechanisms that are part of the ACE
reactor framework, in order to make us
more predictable and more efficient in
terms of how we have a path for a pool of
threads in our pattern language for the
Jaws web server.
Let's first start by talking about the
motivation for.
Ace TP reactor.
Although you can use the ACE select
reactor very conveninetly as we've
illustrated a number of times.
It has one key limitation.
Only one thread of control can own its
event loop.
Which means it can only really be used on
a single CPU or a single core.
So it's not going to scale up very
effectively, in contrast, the ACE thread
pool reactor implements the
Leaders/Followers pattern and that allows
a pool of threads to run its event loop in
a way that is going to, to be much more
scalable, work much more effectively on
the kinds of advanced hardware and
software we find ourselves having at our
disposal in modern operating system
environments.
Let's talk a bit about the ace tp reactor
class.
This class actually inherits from ace
select reactors, So it reuses large parts
of its implementation.
Likewise, it also implements the ACE
reactor interface.
If you recall, the ace reactor frameworks
uses the bridge pattern, and its ace
reactor class is the abstraction role.
In that particular pattern and so classes
like ACE_Select_Reactor, ACE_TP_Reactor
and so on are the various parts of the
implementation or the implementer
hierarchy that form that pattern.
And then we go ahead and apply the leader
followers logic.
In ACE_TP_Reactor to do a couple of
things.
The most important thing we do is we could
have a pool of threads all of which call
run event loop or run reactor event loop
on the ACE_TP_reactor and this will be
managed under the hood using the
mechanisms that define by the Leader/
Followers pattern in order to ensure that
one of those threads at a time takes
turns.
Handling the incoming events on the handle
set that the reactor provides.
The other things that ACE_TP_Reactor does,
it's kind of nice.
Is, it insures that only one thread at a
time is reading requests from a given
handle.
And so what that helps to ensure is that
we don't have to make a lot of changes to.
Traditional single threaded code when we
move from a select reactor based solution
to an ACE_TP_Reactor based solution.
We don't have to end up worrying about
multiple threads trying to read out the
same end point, which would cause all
kinds of chaos and insanity.
So one of the nice things about this
approach is that the ACE_TP_Reactor
handles the variability of multithreaded
access to I/O multiplexers like select or
pull using a common API.
So could have different ways of doing
concurrency, but it all works out in a
common way from the programming point of
view.
Let's not talk about how we could extend
the earlier ACE acceptor connecter example
for Jaws to spawn a pool of threads that
will work to wait on the different sources
of I/O concurrently.
If you look at this diagram, you can see
it's very similar to the one we had
before.
The main difference is that now a pool of
threads are calling the event loop
mechanisms on the ACE TP reactor, rather
than just 1 at a time.
So we can imagine that the scaleability
will be much higher.
Let's take a look at the implementation.
The actual implementation logic in many
ways is very similar.
We include a bunch of header files that we
would have had before.
We define 4 declarations for a couple of
thread functions we're going to use in
order to be able to manage the pool of
threads.
And be able to control the lifetime of the
web server.
The particular use of the reactor HTTP
server template.
Will be identical to what we had before in
the acceptor connector version of this
solution.
We used HTTP_Svc_Acceptor as the parameter
to this, this particular template to
create the HTTP_Server_Daemon type def.
The main difference occurs in part of the
main program.
If you take a look here, you can see that
unlike before, when we just had an ACE
reactor that uses ACE select reactor by
default on POSIX platforms, instead we
explicitly define an ACE TP reactor.
And then associate that.
Which is the implementer portion with the
abstraction part of the ACE reactor class
from the ACE reactor framework.
So henceforth, whenever methods are called
on this particular reactor.
It will forward those methods to the
ACE_TP_Reactor implementation.
We then go ahead and allocate a new
HTTP_server_Daemon object.
And we dynamically allocate it, and
associate it with the reactor.
So it will be cleaned up correctly when
everything shuts down.
And here's where things get a little bit
different and more interesting.
What we do next, is we use the ACE thread
manager class to spawn a pool of threads.
All of which will run the event loop
function.
Which is the entry point.
So we'll have a pool of threads.
In this case we have 8 threads.
We can easily change that.
All of which are associated this the
thread pool reactor.
And then we also spawn another thread of
control that will run the controller
function.
Which is we'll see can be used to have.
Administrative access to cleanly shutting
down the web server as the need arises.
The final thing we do here is we have the,
a barrier synchronizer that's used from
ACE Thread Manager to wait for all the
other threads of control to shutdown.
And this of course guards against cases
where some operating systems Will shut a
process down if the main threat of control
happens to exit.
So we don't let that happen by using a
barrier synchronization.
Here now is the event loop method.
This is the function that we passed when
we spawn a thread or threads from the ACE
thread manager.
As you can see all that does is it takes
in an ACE reactor.
Pointer and then it goes ahead and calls
the reactor's event loop method to, to run
it.
And because it's a threadpool reactor, it
can do this in multiple threads of
control.
Here is the controller function, very
simple.
All it does is it runs in it's own thread
of control and it waits for something to
type quit.
On the command line interface which will
then tell the server to shut itself down
in a clean and graceful way.
Notice how similar the single threaded and
multithreaded versions are, really the
only major difference was with the
multithreaded version, that used the ACE
thread pull reactor, what we do is we spot
a pool of threads that take advantage of
its leader followers implementation to run
those threads in a way that takes turns
accessing the low level event.
The multiplexing and multiplexing
mechanisms that the operating system
provides under the hood.
So to summarize this particular part of
the module and to kind of wrap up this
module altogether, there's a wide variety
of different event De-multiplexing
mechanisms and concurrency mechanisms that
are available on different operating
systems.
And trying to keep track of all this
diversity can be a little bit daunting at
times.
One of the nice things about the ACE
reactor framework is it provides a
convenient way of handling these different
mechanisms through a common interface.
As we saw here, you can create an ACE
thread pool reactor and you can associate
it with the ACE reactor.
Abstraction from the bridge pattern.
And this allows you to kind of push the
details down into the framework
implementation, so all these complexities
are largly hidden from you and you can
focus on your business logic, on the
application, on the services that you're
developing.
We didn't really talk about it in this
module, but it's also worth noting, that
there's yet another implementation of the
ACE Reactor framework, called the ACE Wait
for multiple objects reactor or the ACE
WFMO reactor.
And Ace WFMO reactor provides many of the
same capabilities that the ACE thread pool
reactor does, but it does it using the
Window's wait for multiple objects
function which gives you yet even more
powerful capabilities for running things
Involved with threads of control in
handling various kinds of synchronization
and events from the wide range of
synchronizers that Windows supports.