Welcome to Part 4, in the module on
Patterns and Frameworks for Asyncronous
Event Handling.
In previous parts of this module, we first
described the proactor pattern and we
illustrated how the ACE proactor framework
can be used to implement this pattern, on
a number of operating systems that support
Asynchronous I/O.
We then implemented how you can apply the
ACE proactive framework on Windows or
other operating systems in order to
implement an asynchronous version of our
JAWS webs server.
What we're going to do in this part of the
module is continue on by discussing yet
another pattern, the asynchronous
completion token pattern, that fleshes out
our pattern language in order to be able
to handle efficient demultiplexing of
responses that occur after asynchronous
operations have completed their execution.
So let's first start talk, talking about
motivating the need for this particular
pattern.
If you take a look at our web server that
we implemented in the previous part of the
module, you'll see that one of the goals
was to make it as efficient as possible,
using as few threads as possible,
leveraging the underlying asynchronous I/O
operations.
Well, part of the goal of making things
efficient is to be able to get those
completion event handlers processed as
quickly as possible and we'd like to
figure out a way of doing this that will
minimize the time and the space overhead
necessary to associate the results of an
asynchronous operation with a handler
that's been dedicated to clean up and
complete the processing on those
operations.
So, in order to do this.
In order to, to make that as quick and
small and lean as possible.
We're going to apply something called, the
asynchronous completion token pattern.
And we're going to use this to demultiplex
and process the responses of asynchronous
requests, asynchronous operations, very
efficiently.
This pattern is something that appears in
the Posta 2 book, and it works as follows.
You start out by having some kind of an
initiator, that invokes an asynchronous
operation and when it invokes the
operation, it passes along an asynchronous
completion token.
And I'll talk a bit more in a moment about
what that might look like.
But a moment, think for the moment that
it's some kind of pointer or index or very
small, lean data object that can be passed
along with an asynchronous call.
That asynchronous call, of course, is
invoked on some kind of service which
might be a remote service, it might be an
operating system service such as
asynchronous I/O operations that's
supported on Windows or various versions
of Posix.
When the service is finished running, it
then goes ahead and returns a response
back to the original initiator.
And along with that response, is contained
the asynchronous completion token, or act,
that was passed along with the original
call invoked by the initiator.
And this act is then used to figure out
how to get the appropriate completion
handler to clean up, and do the, the
processing of the response as quickly as
possible.
If you take a look at the URL at the
bottom of this page, you'll find a paper
that describes this pattern in more
detail, and of course it's also in POSA2.
Here's a more dynamic view of what's going
on.
This illustrates what's being passed along
with the various operations.
What's happening here is this Asynchronous
completion token or ACT, is being bundled
along with any parameters to the service.
That were invoked when the initiators
started the asynchronous operation and the
service simply takes this ACT tucks it
away someplace.
Typically, doesn't change it any way,
shape, or form, and then when it's done,
when it's processing it passes this ACT
back unchanged to, to the initiator where
the completion handler can then be
identified rapidly in order to be able to
carry out the completion processing.
So let's talk about how we might be able
to apply this pattern in the context of
JAWS.
Well it turns out that we've actually
shown this pattern earlier, we just didn't
emphasize it much, when we were reviewing
the code.
If you take a look at the various diagrams
and the code snippets, you'll see that
whenever we go ahead and activate a
service handler, and we associate the read
or write operations that will be invoked
asynchronously with the, the service
handler is called, we actually pass-in
the, this pointer and use this as the
asynchronous completion token.
So we pass in a pointer to ourselves when
we initiate the connection between an
operations that's going to asynchronously
and the various data structures in ACE
that keep track of those, those
operations.
So in this case for example, when we open
the connection to the read stream, we pass
ourselves in as an asynchronous completion
token.
And then when the read call is invoked,
what will happen is that this pointer is
bundled up and passed along as an
overlapped I/O struct, which goes through
the windows read file ex call or read file
call.
And these calls then take that
information, stash it through the
operating system.
It goes through the bowels of the
internals of the windows kernel.
And then when the completion even is done,
that completion event is handed back to
the proactor where the asynchronous
completion token can be quickly extracted
and used to do the demultiplexing.
This next slide illustrates how that
demultiplexing takes place by effectively
having the proactor downcast the
asynchronous completion token back to the
appropriate ACE handler and then invoking
the appropriate callback method, depending
on what kind of an asynchronous call it
was.
So in the case of an asynchronous read
call, we would end up with the handle read
stream hook method dispatched by the
proactor framework.
And the thing that's powerful about this,
is it didn't have to do any table look
ups.
It didn't have to do any complicated
processing.
All it had to do was take this
asynchronous completion token that popped
back out of the get queued completion
status call from the operating system.
System when the call was done and then do
some down casting operations in order to
turn it back into the right kind of object
with the right kind of hook method to do
the right type of completion processing.
So the nice part about it is it's very
fast it's essentially constant time look
up, just takes a few bytes worth of space
to store the pointer and we're leveraging
the internal mechanisms that Windows Ports
for asynchronous completion token
processing in the APIs it offers up to the
application.
And there's similar kinds of mechanisms
you can use with Posix asynchronous I/O as
well.
So let's talk a bit about the benefits and
limitations of this pattern.
One of the nice things about using this
pattern is it simplify the data structures
needed on the initiator side.
You don't have to maintain some kind of
hash table, or map or vector to map the
requests with the responses.
The request and response are simply glon
together with the asynchronous completion
token you pass in when you invoke the
operation asychronously.
We also then get both time and space
benefits.
The time benefits come because when we get
back this completion token all we have to
do is do a downcast, so there's no
expensive look up, the space benefits come
because all we're doing is really passing
a pointer, so it's just a few bytes, so
it's not taking up much space.
And that pointer is not checked or, or
accessed by the operating system, it's
simply returned back to the initiator when
the completion results are done.
Another benefit we get is flexibility.
There's various ways of implementing this
pattern, one way to do it is to pass
around pointers, you could also pass
around indexes or indices and you don't
even have to use any kind of inheritance
hierarchy if you don't want to.
You can simply create objects that know
how to get back to the completion handler
logic with a downcast of some kind.
Cut, naturally there are some limitations
with this approach one problem is if you
start handing out dynamically allocated
memory addresses to the services that you
are calling, if they don't ever end up
completing, if the call fails.
Then it's hard to know whether you can
delete those pointers without ending up
with dangling pointers or memory leaks.
So this is one thing to keep in mind when
you use this pattern.
You might have to deal with some kind of
generation count or scavenging or garbage
collection to clean up these memory
resources appropriately.
You certainly don't want to clean them up
prematurely because if you do, then when
the call's complete, you'll get back a
pointer to memory that's been freed or has
perhaps been reused for some other
purpose.
Another tricky issue has to do with
authentication.
You're handing out a pointer to some
service.
If the service is the operating system,
you can probably be pretty confident it's
not going to be maliciously changing the
contents of that pointer or that object
somehow.
Conversely, if you pass out to something
in the Internet, it may not be so clear it
hasn't changed things or forged some
identity.
So you may need, need to build some kind
of authentication protocol on top of this
mechanism to make it more assured in its
use, much the way that we deal with
various cookie processing in a web
environment.
And the last issue is if you actually pass
out pointers to raw memory from the client
application space to the service, you have
to be careful if you end up remapping the
virtual address of the client space
somehow, that those pointers don't end up
pointing to other places in memory.
Obviously, there's various ways to deal
with this using indirection, tables, or
handles of some kind.
But it's something you have to be aware
of, and you don't want to get caught
passing out pointers to raw memory and
then having things be remapped, because
all kinds of crazy things will happen.
So this is essentially a short overview of
the asynchronous completion token pattern.
We've described it in the context of the
proactor, framework, and the proactor
pattern, but in practice, it's also used
widely for many other kinds of use cases.
It's used for various cookie processing in
web transactions, it's used a lot in
various kinds of middleware to be able to
efficiently associate requests with
responses that go across address spaces.
So, it's a nice pattern to know, it solves
a fairly small problem, but if used
properly and carefully can help make your
code smaller and faster