Welcome to Part 2 in the module on
Patterns and Frameworks for Asynchronous
Event Handling.
In the previous part of this module, we
described the Proactor pattern.
We're now going to describe the ACE
Proactor Framework, which can be used to
implement this pattern in a portable
manner on a number of different operating
system platforms.
We're now going to describe the ACE
Proactor Framework which can be used to
implement this pattern in a portable
manner on a number of different operating
system platforms.
As you'll see, this is by far the most
complicated framework that's in ACE and as
we go through the discussion.
I'll explain to you where the complexity
comes from and how the framework tries its
best to alleviate the complexity as much
as possible.
Let's first talk by talking about the
motivation for the ACE Proactive
Framework.
Operating systems have support for
asynchronous operations in various
degrees.
Windows has good support.
Other POSIX platforms have some support.
But as a general rule of thumb, these
mechanisms are characterized in a few ways
that are some what problematic.
First of all, they tend to be some what
tedious and error prone to program and the
reason for the complexity comes from a
number of sources, the APIs are often
somewhat low level and difficult to
understand.
In asynchronous programming, by its very
nature is complicated, because it
separates the invocation of an operation
from its completions in time and space.
And it also doesn't help the fact that
another of the APIs that you have, to
program these on various operating
systems, tend to be non-portable and often
inefficient as well.
Windows does a very nice job of
asynchronous I/O.
It supports asynchronous I/O through I/O
completion ports, it supports overlapped
I/O.
And in general, even though it's somewhat
tricky to program, the implementation is
robust and the performance is good.
Posix, in contrast, is a bit more
problematic.
The APIs are somewhat limited.
They don't provide as wide range of
capabilities in a more, in as consistent
of a way that Windows does.
The asynchronous I/O mechanisms in POSIX
were largely designed originally for Disk
I/O.
And you can use them for network I/O, but
it's a little tricky, and it's not as
generalizable and consistent as it is in
Windows.
The other problem is that there tend to be
a number of inefficiencies.
Some operating system implementations of
Asynchronous I/O on POSIX platforms,
actually spawn a thread for each
asynchronous operation, which to some
extent, defeats the whole purpose.
So, because of all these different issues.
It, we decided to come up with a framework
that would help to hide as much of these
complexities as we could.
This framework is the ACE Proactor
Framework.
And the classes in this framework allow
event-driven applications to process
completion events for operations that are
invoked asynchronously.
Typically, classes who use this framework
will end up inheriting from something
called ACE_Svc_Handler, which is a little
different from the ACE_Svc_Handler we
talked about in the context of the
Acceptor-Connector Framework.
And the reason for that is it's used for
asynchronous operations and the ACE
Proactor Framework will then dispatch
various hook methods when things complete.
After these asynchronous operations are
done running.
Naturally, the various classes that are
part of the ACE Proactive Framework are
inspired and designed in accordance with
the Proactor pattern that we talked about
before.
So let's talk about the various classes
that are part of the ACE Proactor
Framework.
The first set of classes that are in there
are largely responsible for.
Invoking operations asynchronously and
then being able to handle the completion
of those operations in as clean a way as
possible, given the overall asynchronous
I/O paradigm.
And these would include the ACE_Handler
class and the various read stream and
write stream classes that were.
We're going to talk about.
There then are a set of classes for being
able to accept connections or to initiate
connections asynchronously.
So we have the ACE_Asynch_Acceptor and the
ACE_Asynch_Connector.
And those are used much the way that
they're used in the Acceptor-Connector
Framework.
Except, now we're doing this in a more
asynchronous way.
There is then a service handler that I
mentioned before.
And it typically provides the target for
the creation of these services when the
acceptors and connectors asynchronous
operation is complete.
And the service handlers also provide
various means of being able to do TCP/IP
processing in a network environment.
And then, the final piece here is
something called the ACE Proactor, and the
ACE Proactor itself is really the, the
heart of this, it's the driver, it's the
thing that controls the event loop.
It's the thing that derives the
asynchronous processing and the completion
dispatching to the completion handlers
when the processing is done.
You can take a look at this URL for more
discussion about the ACE Proactor
Framework.
Of course, this discussion also appears in
Chapter 8 of the C++ Network Programming,
Volume 2 book.
So let's now go ahead and talk about the
various classes that are part of the ACE
Proactor Framework.
And as you can see, there's a number of
them.
Many more than there are say in the ACE
Reactor Framework or in some of the other
frameworks.
And the reason for this, really, is easy
to understand.
When you deal with asynchronous I/O, you
have to separate in time and space, the
invocation of operations from their
completion.
And all these various mechanisms we're
about to talk about are there to support
that separation.
The first of the classes we're going to
talk about are the ACE_Asynch_Read_Stream
and the ACE_Asynch_Write_Stream classes.
And these classes are used to initiate
asynchronous operation to read and write
data.
As the names might suggest.
If you think about how you would do this
in a classic synchronous multi-threaded
environment, you can invoke a call like
send or receive that may block.
And there's no problem with this, because
you've got a separate thread of control
and a separate run time stack to keep
track of any state And any other
interactions.
So that when the control comes back to
that function.
When it returns, you can pick up from
where you left off.
With asynchronous I/O, however, it doesn't
work this way.
When you invoke an operation, the handling
of the completion may occur much later in
time.
It may occur in a different thread of
control.
And so there's separation or a decoupling
in time and space.
Of invocation from completion header
processing.
And this class helps with that particular
process.
One of these you can do with this class is
you can initiate asynchronous operations,
reads and writes, and those operations
will no block and they will go ahead and
set the wheels in motion to have the
underlying asynchronous operation
processor.
The, the operating system typically, to
run these operations, while the caller
thread goes back to doing something else.
Something else you can do with this is you
can also bind an I/O handle and
ACE_Handler object, which is used to get
the completion results back and an ACE
Proactor which keeps track of who's going
to demultiplex the results with the done
with the particular operation that you're
invoking.
So they're all bundled together.
Yet another thing you can do is
internally, it'll create an object that
can keep track of all the parameters
associated with the asynchronous
operation.
So when the operation is done, those
parameters come back.
To the completion handler and they can be
used to figure out what to do next whether
things succeeded, whether they failed,
whether or not their issues with respect
to how much data you read or send and so
on and so forth.
Because we inherit from a class called
Asynch, Asynch Operation we can also open
And initiate as well as cancel
asynchronous operations.
This particular class helps to handle the
variability of asynchronous I/O operations
via a common interface which can work with
Windows, it can work with Posics in, in a
consistent way.
The next class we're going to talk about
handles the completion of these
asynchronous operations when they're done.
And this is called the ACE_Handler class.
And what this class does is it provides a
set of hook methods that are called back
automatically by the Proactor framework
when an asynchronously invoked operation
completes.
And so, for each different kind of
operation that we can have run
asynchronously.
Asynchronous accepts, asynchronous
connects, asynchronous reads and writes on
screens, asynchronous reads and writes on
files, other kinds of transmissions such
as using transmit file which use direct
memory access to do very efficient
asynchronous transfer of bulk data from a
file to a socket and so on.
All of these different kinds of completion
events and the handling of them can be
expressed through a single base class
interface called ACE_handler.
It also provides a way to handle timeout
events as well.
This particular class allows us to handle
the variability of asynchronous completion
handling within a common API.
So clearly The read and write streams that
we saw before and the handlers all go
together.
They're basically two sides of the same
coin.
The initiation side and the completion
side.
We then, for network communication, have
something called the ACE_Svc_Handler
class, and this is essentially the target
of the ACE_Asynch_Acceptor and the
ACE_Asynch_Connector that are used to
initiate connections actively and
passively.
And when they're done they go ahead and
initialize this ACE_Svc_Handler, and the
ACE service handler provides a couple of
things.
It provides a way to be able to activate a
service to do something, typically to run
things in some kind of, of a synchronous
way although you could spawn threads if
you chose to.
It's up to you because you can control how
those hook methods are overridden in sub
classes.
It also allows you to figure out who the
connected peer is, what their addresses
are, which you may want to use for various
purposes.
For example, to figure out if you want to
actually communicate to this peer at all.
And because it inherits from ACE_Handler,
it is able to handle the completion.
Of I/O events, things like asynchronous
reads and asynchronous writes.
So ACE service handler is typically used
in cases where you want to handle the
variability of network asynchronous I/O
behind a common interface.
The next class we'll look at should be
pretty clear by now.
This is the ACE_Asynch_Acceptor.
There's also an ACE_Asynch_Connector that
is the dual of this.
The ACE_Asynch_Connector is used to
initiate passive connection establishment.
Asynchronous, of course, so you can go
ahead and open and accept connections that
come in and those we handle asynchronously
as they complete when the clients connect.
It's a factory that will create and
initialize service handlers.
Much like the acceptors and connectors do
that we talked about before in the ACE
Acceptor-Connector Framework, that's more
synchronous in nature.
It also allows you to be able to cancel
previously initiated asynchronous accept
operations.
It provides a hook method to validate
connections before you actually create
service handlers.
You can do a form of call screening to
ignore connections from clients you don't
want to talk to.
And again, because it inherits from
ACE_Handler, it's able to handle the
completion of asynchronous accept events
in a common way.
So, the ACE_Asynch_Acceptor, much like the
ACE_Asynch_Connector that we're not going
to talk about here.
Allow us to be able to handle the
variability of asynchronous connection
establishment within a common API.
And this can work both for UNIX platforms,
Posics platforms that don't really support
asynchronous accepts and connects.
So we have to emulate them using threads.
Or the Windows platforms that do support,
natively.
Asynchronistic and asynchronistic
connects.
So they're very powerful.
And you can hide all those diversities and
heterogeneous differences behind a common
API.
The final piece of the puzzle here, brings
it all together, this is the ACE Proactor
class.
Much like for Ace Reactor, it's the class
that runs the event loop.
It does a couple of things.
It centralizes the event loop processing
by providing methods to run the event
loop.
Either indefinetely or one at a time.
It also provides a way to be able to
demultiplex completion events that come in
from the underlying completion event
queses, things like I/O ports on Windows,
and other similar mechanisms you have on
Posics platforms.
And be able to get those things dispatched
back to the oppropriate completion
handler, that knows what to do.
In response to the completion of the
events, such as kick off an asynchronous
read call or kick off another asynchronous
write call, etcetera.
It also can be used to dispatch time outs
as well.
So, just like the reactor, we can dispatch
a number of different kinds of events.
I/o events, time events and so on with one
common interface.
This particular class handles the overall
variability of asynchronous event handling
behind a common API that works both on
Unix and, and POSIX platforms, as well as
on Windows.
So to summarize this particular part in
the module Proactive I/O models are more
complicated.
They are inherently more complicated to
program than synchronous event handling,
and synchronous threading.
And that's because of this separation in
terms of time and space, from the
initiation and the completion.
Which means that things that you
historically would have handled by
implicit.
Information stored in the run time stack,
say in the activation record when you made
a function call that was blocking.
That kind of information can no longer be
stored implicitly on the stack, but
instead you have to store it explicitly
using a variety of different data
structures.
Some of the ones we'll talk about here.
Some of which such as asynchronous
completion tokens, we'll talk about in
later parts of this module.
There are also, of course, a number of
significant accidental complexities of
programming with asynchronous I/O.
The programming interfaces are somewhat
clumsy, not well-documented.
Hard to find information on how to use
them effectively.
If you just read the manual pages in
isolation, you'll have a really difficult
time knowing how all the pieces fit
together.
So because of these issues, and because of
some of the portability issues as well, we
developed the ACE Proactive Framework to
help shield a lot of those accidental
complexities, make those portable wherever
possible, make things a lot more
systematically.
Applicable systematically reusable, so
even though there are more moving parts
than a reactive approach or a, a, leader
followers approach or a
Half-Sync/Half-Async approach.
The surface area that you deal with is
much easier to understand, it uses common
object oriented techniques such as
inheritance.
And other patterns we're going to talk
about in just a moment, in order to be
able to reduce the overall complexity of
programming these very powerful
asynchronous I/O models.