Welcome to part six of the module on
Patterns and Frameworks for Concurrency
and Synchronization.
In previous parts of this module, we
described the active object pattern.
It illustrated the ACE Task framework that
implements this and other concurrency
patterns.
We also illustrated how to apply ACE Task
and ACE Acceptor-Connector and ACE Reactor
frameworks to implement a thread per
connection web server based on our JAWS
example.
We then described the Half-Sync/Half-Async
pattern.
And then we illustrated how to apply a
variety of ACE frameworks to implement
Half-Sync/Half-Async for JAWS.
If you took a look at the JAWS
implementation, you would've seen one
place that used a synchronized request
queue.
And in this particular part of the module,
we're going to describe how the Monitor
Object pattern to be used to implement
this request queue.
In a very straightforward and efficient
way.
If you go back and take a look at the
previous part, you'll see that between the
Half-Async portion of the solution and the
Half-Sync portion of the solution, we had
an ACE message queue that was used to pass
request messages containing get request
between the 2 different layers.
That was the queuing layer in the
Half-Sync/Half-Async pattern.
And it's instructive to consider how we
might go about implementing this
particular queuing layer.
It we did things in naive way, we could
end with a number of different problems.
One problem might be, if we neglected to
put any kind of synchronization into the
request queue at all, which would
guarantee that different threads of
control would corrupt the internal data
structures, because they'd be accessing
them at the same time.
And there would be race conditions galore.
Another problem which we might encounter
would be to try to put some kind of spin
lock and use that solely to provide access
to the particular request queue.
While that might work in some abstract
sense, it would be wildly inefficient
because we would spend lot of time
spinning when the queue was either empty
or full, just burning out CPU cycles for
no particular good reason.
That might be useful in some kind of
safety, critical, nuclear reactor control
system, but not for our web server
solution.
So, what's the approach we're going to use
instead?
We're going to apply the Monitor Object
pattern in order to be able to serialize
access to our request queue in a manner
that will both be thread safe and also
efficient.
The Monitor Object pattern is used to
provide an object-oriented access point
that allows multiple threads of control to
invoke methods on a Monitor Object while
only allowing only one method at a time to
run.
So, that provides corruption protection
and avoids race conditions.
And the other thing that we're going to do
with Monitor Object, is make it possible
to be able to allow the different threads
of control to schedule and coordinate
their interaction by using various parts
of the Monitor Object as well.
If you take a look at the structure
diagram illustrated on this slide, you'll
see that there's a number of parts to
Monitor Object.
The first part of Monitor Object is the
Monitor Object itself, which contains a
number of so-called synchronized methods.
People who are Java programmers should be
very familiar with the concept of
synchronized method.
Because in Java, this is supported
natively in the language by the
synchronized keyword.
And you can simply add that to a method to
ensure that only one of those methods will
be active inside of an object at a time.
In order to be able to ensure that this
takes place, there is typically a Monitor
Lock of some kind.
Maybe a mutex, or a reader's writer lock,
perhaps a recursive mutex, perhaps a
nonrecursive mutex.
Sort of depends on the use case.
And this Monitor Lock is used to make sure
that there's only one method active at a
time inside a Monitor Object.
And then there's also, potentially 0 or
more Monitor Conditions, which are
condition variables that are used to allow
threads to cooperatively schedule their
interactions and to coordinate with each
other in various stylized ways.
By being able to wait, notify, and notify
all waiting threads when something
interesting happens and conditions change.
If you're programming in Java, these
things come built-in to the language.
If you're programming in other languages
like C++ or C, then you'll have to
understand how the pattern works in order
to be able to use this for the code that
you write, where it's appropriate.
If you take a look at this URL at the
bottom of the slide, you'll find out more
information about the Monitor Object
pattern.
And of course it also appears in the POSA
2 book.
Let's now talk a bit about the dynamics of
this pattern.
At first glance, these dynamics appear a
little daunting because there's a lot of
moving parts.
But if you break it down, it's actually
quite easy to understand.
And in order to make it a little bit more
intuitive, I'll describe this in the
context of our synchronized request queue.
And we'll imagine that we're trying to
dequeue an item a message from this
request queue.
What happens in this case is the thread
comes along and it says, I would like to
dequeue something from the queue.
I'd like to do a Get-Queue.
And it would go in.
The Monitor Lock would be acquired.
Let's assume there were no other threads
running at the time.
So the Monitor Lock is acquired.
No other, no other threads, no other
methods can execute at that point in that
particular Monitor Object.
And then what'll happen is it'll go ahead.
That method will check to see if there's
any elements, any messages on the queue.
In this particular case, let's assume
there are no elements in the queue.
So, what will happen at that point is that
this particular method will voluntarily
relinquish the threat of control.
And it will do this by waiting on a
notEmpty condition.
So, this is a condition variable, a
Monitor Condition, that's used to wait
for.
It's there to be something in the queue.
So it's no longer empty.
When the waitCall is invoked, that will
also atomically release the lock.
And this threat is now suspended waiting
for the notEmpty condition to change.
At some point along the way, another
thread will come along that will actually
enqueue or do a putQueue to put a message
into the queue.
That method will acquire the Monitor Lock
which was released earlier, when we did
the wait.
It will go ahead and add a message to the
message queue.
And then it'll notice that someone was
waiting and it will go ahead and invoke
the, the notify method or the notify all
method to wake up any waiting threads.
And then it will go ahead and exit the,
the Monitor Object and release the lock.
At some point henceforth, the sleeping
thread will be reawakened.
It will acquire the lock, will go and
check to see that there is indeed, a
message on the message queue and it will
remove the message from the message queue,
release the lock and return to the caller.
And these kinds of synchronization and
scheduling activities will go on over and
over again, as we insert and remove things
into our request queue.
So, how could we apply this to JAWS?
Well, we kind of already gave an example
on the previous slide when we were
discussing the dynamics.
But let's put it a bit more into the
context of our JAWS web server using the
Half-Sync/Half-Async design.
So, if you recall we have an ACE Task and
part of an ACE Task is an ACE Message
Queue, which we're going to look at in
much more detail in the next part of this
module.
This ACE message queue can be used in a
couple of ways by the Task.
Most typically what happens is, when the
TP HTTP handler running in the Half-Async
portion, the reactive portion of our web
server calls put, on the Task on the TP
HTTP Task, that put method if you recall,
will enqueue the request on the
synchronized ACE Message Queue using the
Monitor Condition and the Monitor Lock and
the various things we just described.
Once it's been put on the queue, then one
or more of the threads that are waiting to
receive notification that there's new work
to be done, will be awakened by the thread
scheduler.
And these threads that are running as part
of the active object in the TP HTTP Task,
will call getQueue and that getQueue will
return with the queue to process.
And you can see here that we use the
notEmpty and notFull conditions, in order
to be able to dictate when things can
start up again, when they can be notified,
when they have to wait and block and so
on.
So, in this particular case, the producer
side will block if the queue is full, and
the consumer threads will block if the
queue is empty.
And everything is driven by those types of
interactions.
It's instructive to compare and contrast
Monitor Object that we're talking about
here, with Active Object that we described
somewhat earlier.
There's a couple of different ways to
relate these patterns because they, at
first glance, appear to be solving a
similar style of problem.
In the Monitor Object case, the thread
that invokes a method is borrowed to run
the method.
In the Active Objective case, in contrast,
the thread that invokes the method is not
the thread that runs the method.
Those two things are separated and they're
run in different threads of control.
So that's one difference.
As a consequence of some of those
differences, there's additional
flexibility with active object.
In active object cases, you can reorder
the requests that are coming in, the
method requests that correspond to the
messages.
And you can run them in a different order
than they arrived.
You may run them in priority order or some
other type of order that depends on
synchronization constraints or guards that
may dictate how those method requests can
be executed on the, the Active Object
server.
Conversely, as we'll see with, with
Monitor Objects, typically the order in
which you invoke the methods are the order
in which they run.
There's usually a FIFO queuing like
regiment that's followed by the Monitor
Lock, although that's often OS and
implementation specific.
Another thing to keep in mind is that,
because Active Object has the methods that
invoke the request in a different thread
from the methods that run the request,
there will be some additional context
switching, synchronization, and data
movement and memory allocation overhead,
to do those various operations.
So, you probably want to use Monitor
Object when you're, have short running
operations to run, to execute.
And perhaps, consider using Active Object
when things take longer to run.
So, those overheads don't really amount
for very much relative to the duration of
time the operations are executing in the
pool of threads.
It's also worth noting that Active Object
is more scalable in some ways than Monitor
Object is because you can have a pool of
threads to run the various requests.
So, let's talk about the benefits of the
Monitor Object pattern.
One of the great things that Monitor
Object provides, which is one reason why
they, they bake it into Java, is that it
greatly simplifies the way in which you
think about concurrency In an object
oriented program.
In Monitor Object, the method indication
is the unit of synchronization and one
method at a time is able to execute within
the context of any given object.
Likewise, you can also do fairly straight
forward say scheduling operations between
the different methods when they run.
And then you have to be careful, of
course, that you're, you're thoughtful
about how these different things interact
and they have to know about the protocol
for waiting and notifying.
But it's pretty straightforward an object
oriented developer can quickly understand
how to use this particular pattern.
There are of course some limitations, one
of the downsides is, it's easy to have a
Monitor Object become a contention point
by having too many threads try to descend
upon it, which means that you'll end up
with long queues on your Monitor Lock
waiting to get their turn to run in a
context of the Monitor Object.
It's also possible, if you're not careful
when you design with Monitor Object, to
end up with limited extensibility.
It's often easy to intertwine the
synchronization logic with the business
logic of your, of your object, or your,
your component or service.
And avoiding that is, is tricky.
Yet another issue, and this is
particularly true in languages like Java,
if you use Monitor Object naively, and you
try to nest monitor objects, you could end
up with a problem known as the Nested
Monitor Lockout Problem.
If you take a look at this link at the
bottom of the slide, it describes some of
these problems in the context of Java and
illustrates how you can avoid these
problems in Java, if you follow a few
other certain idioms and patterns when you
implement your solution.
A great place to look for lots of other
discussion about Java concurrency patterns
of course, is Doug Lea's Concurrent
Programming in Java.