[MUSIC].
Using Session cookies isn't
really the most convenient way of
authenticating mobile devices and, and
remembering the users associated with
the mobile devices that are sending
requests to your Cloud service.
So let me give you some examples
of why sessions aren't ideal.
So let's say that we have a server.
And we have access to various
resources on that server.
So we might be able to upload video,
we might be
able to delete video
that's in our account.
And we might be able to get a list
of the videos that we've uploaded.
Now, if I'm writing a cloud
service that I intend for
different mobile apps to use,
I need a way of allowing some mobile app.
That's running our device.
So let's say, we've got our Android device
here, or some other device like an iPhone.
We've got all of these different apps.
So we've got App 1, App 2,
and they're going to be
sending requests to the server
to get access to our video data.
So you can imagine YouTube and
other sites deal with stuff like this.
And so, App 2 may send request to
the server to get access to our video.
App 1 may send request to our server
to get access to different aspects of
the videos that we've uploaded.
Now, how do those apps go and
establish their identity and
associate themselves with me and
my user account, so
that they can get access to my
information, either upload new videos or
delete videos, or
list the videos that I've uploaded?
Well, if we're just using
the standard session approach, that
we've used before where we create session
cookies after logging in a log in page.
Each app would basically display a login
that would say, you know, give us your
username, and it would have a box, and
then it would have a box for the password.
And it would collect all of
this information from me, and
then just pass it along to the server.
And each of these apps
might go about doing that.
Now, let's say that I want to
not have to login every time.
Well, this app may say, okay, well,
you don't have to login every time, I'll
just store your username and password.
And then this app says, oh,
I'll store your username and password too.
And very quickly we get into this
situation where our private information,
our username and password is being
stored by all of these different apps.
And the security of how well it's stored
is determined by the weakest link.
The, the first app in here that goes and
stores it in plain text or
doesn't do the proper encryption or
other things hashing to protect it,
the, the, the easier it is for
an attacker to gain access to it.
So we don't really like this idea that
we're going to provide our user name and
password to each app.
And then each app is going to store that
information and then provide it over and
over again to the server.
So that's one disadvantage of this model
where we're going to use session cookies.
Another disadvantage is,
let's say that I really trust App 2.
So this is an app that I really,
really trust.
I give it a little check mark here.
I really trust App 2.
This is an app that's produced by
a really well known app developer.
But App 1, eh, I sort of trust them,
but I want to try that app out.
Well, even though I trust this
app a lot more, there's no
way that I can differentiate the access
that they should have to my account.
So either one I'm going to give
my username and password to.
They're both going to be able
to login the server, and
they're both going to have
full access to my account.
So they'll both be able to upload videos,
delete videos, and list videos.
And what if I really wanted
to try this app out,
but only give it
the ability to list videos?
Or maybe it only needs to
access to list videos.
So, let's say that this
is just a viewer browser.
Well, it shouldn't have access to
upload and delete videos if it doesn't
need the access, but with this username
and password model, each app is going to.
Potentially store, but at the very risk,
get access to my username and password,
and be able to use it to authenticate
with the server and do everything.
So, I don't really want every app to have
full access to my account and I especially
don't want every app to have full access
to my account if they don't need it.
Because the more times I give
out my username and password,
the more apps that improperly protect it
or store it, and the less they actually
need to use it the more I'm exposing
myself to a security vulnerability.
The more I'm offering up my account
to be attacked and compromised.
So, what we need is a way
to allow apps to get
access to certain resources that
are associated with my account.
So we want one app to just
have access to list my videos.
And maybe we want another app that
we trust more to have access to
listing the videos and to deleting them.
So we're going to give this to App 2.
This one to one and two, and
we're not going to give delete access to
any of the apps because none of them,
we don't trust any of the apps that much.
Well, this type of model isn't
supported well by a username and
password that generates a session
cookie that gets stores in an app and
used to access data in my account.
There's no granularity in
the control of the access.
And we have that fact that either
we're providing the username and
password to the app every single time
we want to use it, or that app is
storing it on disk, so it may be going and
storing it somewhere on your device.
And then this app may be going and storing
your username and password somewhere else.
Otherwise they're forcing
you to login every time and
the app developers don't want to do that.
So suddenly we are having our username and
password stored all over the place.
We can't govern access to the resources in
our account on any type of granular level.
And it ends up being a situation
that's not ideal for
a mobile environment and for the concept
of having different apps that have
access to different parts of our account.
The model of storing usernames and
passwords were
requiring the user to provide them every
time also has some other disadvantages.
That we don't really
like in a mobile model.
So let's say that we
have multiple apps again
that we are working with that
we want access to our data.
So we have A1 again.
And we've got a second app.
And maybe you have other apps on
multiple devices, so we might even have.
Other devices where we've got yet
more apps that also are getting
access to our accounts.
There we've got a tablet,
we've got some other things.
So we've got all of these different apps.
Well, suddenly we're storing our password
in a lot of different places, for one.
If these apps are storing it.
Or we're having to type it in over and
over again.
But we're also got some other things.
Let's say that,
these apps are storing our password,
when it's very possible they
are because they want to be convenient.
And suddenly I want to change my password,
because this is something that is a good,
typically considered to be a good security
practice is to continually update and
change your password.
Well every time I change my password.
I'm going to have to go and
change it here, here, here and here.
So, as a user I'm going to start
feeling probably a little lazier, and
thinking I really don't want to go and
update my password in ten different
Apps every time I change it.
So, I won't change it as often.
Another issue is, that, let's say
I decide to give this app access.
There's no way for
the server to participate in the decision
of what this app should be able to access.
So for example, the server may want to
say this app can only have access to
certain things because
that's just my policy.
But the server's not
involved in this process.
You give your user name and password
to this app, and the app goes off and
talks to the server.
And the server doesn't get to decide what
the app can or can't have access too.
You tell the server,
it has access to my whole account.
So, the server isn't involved
in the process access at all.
Another thing is, what happens if I decide
that I no longer trust this app over here?
So, I don't trust this app,
but I trust the other three.
Well, the only way to revoke that trust of
that first app of it storing
my username and password.
Is have to go, and
completely change my password,
on the server side so
that this app can no longer log in.
And the result is that this app is no
longer going to have access, this app will
no longer have access, and that app
is going to no longer have access.
So this user, name, and
password to get a session cookie.
That model just doesn't
really make sense for
the mobile environment where we'll have
multiple apps, that will have access
to our data, and potentially need access
to different subsets of our data.
And we may trust some apps
more than other apps.
But if we're just sending a password and
getting a session cookie back.
And letting whatever app wants it,
use it to get access to our full account.
We're beginning to create all kinds
of security problems that are,
at least not ideal situations for
our cloud based service.
What we really want to do,
is we want to be able to control access to
the resources that are associated
with the user's account.
At a finer level of granularity.
We don't want to train the user
to just give up their password to
any app, at any time.
We want the server to be able to make some
decisions, about which app should and
shouldn't have access to a user's data.
And we'd also like, for
the user to be able to go and
change their password without.
Effecting all of the apps that they
want to have access to their data.
Similarly, we'd like to be able to go and
revoke access to our data
just to a specific app.
But, all of these things
aren't really possible or
easy to do at least,
with the model where you log in, and
get a session cookie back that gives
apps full access to your account