[MUSIC]
One of the benefits of horizontal scaling
in the Cloud, is that we can take
advantage of the elasticity built into
the Cloud to help us reduce costs and
also be able to respond to fluctuations in
demand in our application, automatically.
So, what do I mean by this?
Well, if we are horizontally
scaling our application, and
we are adding machines as we need to,
to handle the load.
Think about what would be required if
this was a application that you were
running in your own data center, or
you were buying computers to
support this application.
If you were running on one machine and you
realized that you needed another machine,
you would have to go and
physically buy a new machine.
Set it up in your data center or where
ever you had that machine co-located, and
then support the infrastructure for
that machine.
So, what that means is.
One, there's going to be a limited
responsiveness that you can provide,
when you need new capacity.
You can't just go and
turn capacity very quickly,
because you have to physically
go buy a machine and set it up.
Similarly, if you go buy a machine and
set it up, you really expect all
that machine's capacity to get used.
Otherwise, it's very cost inefficient for
you, if you see a spike in traffic,
you run off and buy a machine, and
then that spike goes away, and
then suddenly you're stuck with this
machine that you're having to pay for
the power for, and you've paid for
the physical infrastructure for.
So, in the Cloud, however,
we're buying machines, typically on
an hourly basis, or, some other billing.
And we can allocate new
machines very quickly.
This is the elasticity property,
is we can allocate new machines as,
as quickly as we need to, or there's
some limit because we have to wait for
them to start up, but we can usually
allocate them pretty quickly.
And then, when we're done with them,
when we can release them.
And so this is the property of
elasticity that we love about the Cloud,
because we don't have to go and physically
buy a machine and get it set up.
We don't have to try to plan and
forecast way into the future in order to
make sure that we've set up
enough physical infrastructure.
But, what we do have to do is figure out.
When should we go and add a new machine?
When do we go and
set up this N plus 1 machine over here,
to add additional load capacity to our a,
a, application in our Cloud service?
And even though we can set up
new capacity very quickly, and
we can tear down new capacity quickly.
We need someway of
monitoring these machines.
Now, we could have somebody sitting in
front of a console all day long, and
watching the load on each
of these machines and
manually deciding and
pressing a button to start things up.
But that wouldn't be very efficient and
I certainly, don't want to sit there and
do that job for the rest of my life.
But, if for example,
we can know what are servers or,
their behavior's expected to be.
If we can measure properties of them such
as their response time to a request, or
the load on their CPU or their disc.
We can use that information to figure out,
when we need to go,
and start a new machine.
So we can have some
intelligence that decides,
when to bring new capacity online.
And then that intelligence can
automatically interact with our Cloud
provider, to add machines as needed,
or when machines are no longer needed,
automatically tell the cloud
provider what to turn off.
So that we're only being charged for
what we actually need at any given time.
And this id i,
idea of having some intelligence built in,
that can automatically add capacity, and
remove capacity, is called auto-scaling.
So this is what allows us to run
more cost effectively in the Cloud,
and it also is what allows us
to have applications that can
automatically grow to make demand.
Now one of the things we have to be,
you know, cognizant of.
Is it in a cloud environment.
There is a limit to how fast
we can turn machines on.
It does still take time for
machines to boot up, and to for
our application to launch and
initialize and do whatever else it needs.
So, we have to build intelligence that can
either forecast well enough to
predict what the load is going to do.
In the next, you know, few minutes or
hours in order to turn machines on
quick enough so that they will be ready
when our load grows to the rate that we,
is going to overflow a particular
machine or our current capacity.
So we have to think about,
what is our current load?
How fast can we add new nodes?
And then using that we want to predict,
what should be the capacity that we're
going to need to have in the future.
Now all of these things are typically,
you know, server specific, or
application specific things
that have to be analyzed.
But one thing to consider when
you're building your application and
you're going to have
horizontal scalability.
Just thinking about what are the rules
going to be for when I should bring
new machines online, or when I should
take my existing machines offline.
And that's what's going to decide your
auto-scaling policies that will effect how
autonomous your service is and how well
it can automatically grow in response to
traffic, as well as shrink your bill
in response to lessening traffic.
The other thing that's important
with auto-scaling is that, if for
some reason this machine dies, so
if there's a physical failure or
your application crashes.
The intelligence can automatically
see that one of your instances,
one of your virtual machines or
whatever unit you're using,
maybe a container if you're using
something like Docker has died and
automatically go and
allocate a replacement.
Now, you can see yet
again this is an example where
statelessness is an important property.
If we don't have to worry
about which machine died,
if we don't have to worry about
the load on a specific machine,
it makes it easier for us to just add
machines and think of things in aggregate.
We can just think about,
how many machines do we have?
How much load is on them?
Do we need more, or
do we need fewer machines?
If we have specific machines that have
specific state on them then we start,
have to start thinking about
tracking them individually.
And figuring out when a particular
machines state needs to be replicated on
another machine to split the load up, and
it makes it a much more complex decision.