[MUSIC]
So what happens when you build
the next Instagram, and suddenly you
have a mobile application connected
to a Cloud servers that you've built
that's getting hundreds of thousands of
users a day, or millions of users a day?
Is your application going to be
able to handle all of that traffic?
Are your Cloud servers, is going to
be able to scale up to support that?
So this is a key question when
you're building Cloud servers,
is understanding how well they scale or
grow in response to their load.
Now there's kind of two ways
that we can go about scaling.
One way, is we can have requests
coming in to our server, and
if we have 10 requests we may
not need a very big server.
But the, if we go up to 1,000 requests,
we could try to grow and
put ourselves onto a bigger server
that has more horsepower in it.
And then if we go up to 10,000 requests,
we could try to grow to
an even bigger server.
And this idea of
continually scaling up and
getting bigger servers,
is called vertical scalability.
But, there's a problem with this.
And that is, at some point we're going
to reach a traffic load that just,
there isn't going to be a machine
big enough to support it.
It doesn't matter if you're Google or
if you're someone smaller.
At some point it's not going
to make sense to run all of
this load on one single computer.
You can imagine that there's no way
on Earth that Google could run all of
their search operations
on a single machine.
Instead, we're always going to have
the situation where at some point,
we're going to have to
move our applications.
Split it and
distribute it across multiple machines.
And so, that's what we're trying to shoot
for when we're building an application.
We'd like to have it so
that when we have a small amount
of load we can have one machine.
When we grow and get more load,
we can add another machine.
And then when we grow yet again,
we can continue adding machines.
And we can continue adding
machines as much as we
want to support this request load.
And so, in this scenario what
we're doing is horizontal scaling.
And this is really what we're looking for
when we are building Cloud service,
is we want to build services that can
be easily be horizontally scaled.
And what that means is,
is that if new load shows up,
we can easily just go and
turn on another machine.
So, if we need more capacity,
we just add a new machine.
Now, getting horizontal scaling
right is not necessarily easy.
You have to do a bunch of
things in your application.
And optimize it to make sure that you
can just turn on another machine.
And often, we'll end up in situations,
where inefficiencies
in our code prevent us
from actually taking advantage of the full
benefit of a new machine coming online.
So, if we think about this as
the computing power available to us and
how many requests we can process, so
measured in requests per second,
let's say.
This is how we're going to
measure our computing power.
And this is the number of servers that
we've allocated to our application.
What we would expect is, is that as we
allocate servers, we would automatically
be able to have more computing power, and
thus process more requests per second.
But, the reality is, is that
this computing power is not directly
related to how many requests per second.
We can process because of inefficiencies
in the way that we've does,
designed our application.
So we may have something
that looks like this, and
in reality our application may
scale something like this.
So this may be due to,
you know, architectural design
choices that we've made.
We may not be able to just keep adding
machines easily, and have our number of
requests, or clients that we can
service automatically scale up.
So, we have to realize that whenever
we go and build an application,
the design decisions that we're making
are going to impact us at some point and
make it so that there's a limit to
how far we can scale because of this
inefficiency between what we really should
be able to do and what we actually can do.
So this inefficiency here is
going to bottleneck us and
hurt us at some point when we
scale up across multiple machines.
One of the big considerations that we have
to deal with when we're building these
applications, is trying to make our
application as stateless as possible.
And the servlets or
the controllers that we're writing.
We want to make them as easy to just
add additional machines as possible.
Now what stateless means,
is that we're going to remember some
information about
the conversation with the client.
And we're going to have things like
caches, or log in information or
other things on the server
side that are going to
be remembered as we begin
talking with clients.
So that is a stateful application,
if we're remembering things.
If we have a server that's not remembering
anything about the clients it's
talking to, it's stateless.
So we can send, when we have a stateless
application we can send requests for
a stateless application to any server.
So, we can just turn on a new server and
begin sending requests to it and
we can essentially add capacity to our
system simply by turning on new machines,
if we have a stateless application.
If we have a stateful application,
when we turn on new machines,
we're going to have to
think about if we want to
move some of our existing
clients to those other machines.
Or we have some important state
that needs to be migrated to them.
How do those new machines get that state?
How do they get access to it?
How do we decide which clients
to move to those machines and
how do we migrate their state?
So, it becomes much more complicated
when we have to think about turning on
a machine and then migrating or
bootstrapping its
state in some way to match what's already
happened on all of the other machines.
So, statelessness is a property that
we try to achieve in our application.
We try to have as much of the state as
possible not stored in our application so
that we can just turn new machines on.
But that's not always the case and
not always easy to do.
We'd like our controllers to be
able to process any request.
And not have to know about
things that have gone on,
on other machines somewhere else.
So, these are some of
the considerations and
what we're trying to do when we're
building highly scalable applications