[MUSIC]
A beautiful aspect of the cloud,
regardless of if you're using platform as
a service or infrastructure as a service,
is that you can take advantage of
really sophisticated services.
That the cloud provider offers,
that you probably wouldn't be
able to cost-effectively, or
efficiently manage yourself.
Now, many of these really complex
services, things like Big Cable, or
Dynamo DB,
they might going to be outside of your,
sort of, area of expertise for
your particular organization.
Or, you maybe a lone developer that's
building a mobile application and
setting up, and managing something
like Amazon Dynamo DB, and
guaranteeing its performance
could be really hard to do.
Amazon however can hire that really
specific expertise needed to
build something like Amazon DB.
And actually, you know, monitor it and
ensure that it scales and ensure it
meets its service level agreements to
you because they're amortizing their
costs across thousands of customers
that are all using that infrastructure.
Whereas you would just be
amortizing your costs across the,
you know, the level that you could use it.
So it would be harder to amortize
all of the development and
set up and other costs.
So all of these cloud services
that the provider gives you.
Allow you to get access to very
sophisticated capabilities that might,
might not be cost effective, or
might not even really be within the re,
the realm of capability for
your organization to take advantage of
without a cloud provider
there to support it.
So one thing you should think about when
you're building your application is what
to offload to the provider,
versus do yourself.
And there's a number of things
you should think about.
One, the cost, is it really going to
be cheaper for you to do this yourself?
And in many cases it's not,
and this will be cheaper.
It, if the cloud provider is amortizing
this cost across thousands of clients,
many cases they can offer
it cheaper than you can.
So for example, Google Drive is
now incredibly cheap to use.
You can get a terabyte of cloud
storage for ten bucks a month, or
something along those lines.
And who knows it may be even cheaper
by the time I'm done with this lecture.
So it may be very hard for you to provide
an equivalent, you know, highly available,
highly performing cloud
data storage system.
And to compete with Google or
maybe you can.
So cost should be a big,
you know, consideration.
The cost shouldn't just include,
how much it would cost you to go,
and buy the hard drive and
connect it to the network.
The moment that you incorporate that
hard drive into your application,
you're going to have to manage it and deal
with it for as long as you're using it.
And it may be easy to manage one hard
drive but as your application scales and
grows you're going to suddenly be stuck
with managing thousands of hard drives,
or maybe you're going to
be dealing with more.
And suddenly when you
start having failures, and
you're starting to have to think about
scalability and dealing with all of
the issues regarding buying more
hard drives, and plugging them in.
The management costs may not make sense,
so
in the small it may not
make sense to you offload.
In the large you know, particularly
if your organization can't scale up
fast enough, and
hire people fast enough, and
build all of the expertise to manage
the things fast enough, it may be much,
much more expensive to do it
yourself than to use a provider.
Or maybe it is the other way around, but
you have to think about, you know,
what do you really want to do yourself?
If you are a small organization,
it's going to be very hard to
compete with the capabilities that
the cloud provider can provide for you.
And if you are a single
developer building a mobile app
it's going to talk to a cloud service
you're almost always going to want to
tap into the things that
the providers give you.
Now, here's some of the interesting
capabilities you should be aware of,
that are out there in the Clouds.
One is CDN, Content Delivery Network.
So, the providers will give you the
ability to take static content that you
would like delivered very quickly
to your mobile clients, and
to distribute it and
cache it across the world.
So that whoever is requesting it can
get a very close and quick copy of it.
Another one are their database services,
particularly for
their no SQL databases,
where you don't have to worry about,
how you're going to scale up and
manage a databases.
You can just go and tap into something
like Big Table or Amazon Dynamo DB or
whatever it is,
what other database you're using.
Providing all the infrastructure to
support the database and manage it,
takes so, you know, a lot work, and
you know you could certainly go and
set up your own instance of whatever
particular database you want.
If you really want to do MongoDB and
manage it yourself.
You can do that, or you can try to
find a provider who will set up, and
manage Mongo for you, or a provider
who has Dynamo DB and tap in it yet.
So you need to think about
content delivery networks,
databases, cloud storage.
So this is a particularly useful
thing if you're going to be,
for example, uploading videos.
And there may be interesting pricing
symmetries particularly if you're
operating a particular provider's cloud,
that make it make much more
sense to also leverage their
service that they're providing.
So to give you an example of this let's
say you're uploading videos and you,
to Amazon's cloud.
And you can either upload those videos to
your servers, that are running on virtual
machines in EC2, and then have those
servers store them directly in S3, or
on disk or somewhere else or you can have
the videos uploaded directly to Amazon S3.
Well an interesting thing is all
of your traffic into S3 to store
those videos would be free.
You would only pay to serve
the videos out of S3.
However you're traffic to send the videos
if you route them through Amazon EC2.
And then store them on disk or
send them of to S3 or somewhere else.
That traffic isn't free.
You, depending on how you're configured
the IP addresses, you may be paying for
the actual bandwidth, but either way,
you're going to be paying for
the fact that your servers are going to
be tied up to some degree.
They're going to be consuming bandwidth
that's allocated to upload the videos.
They're going to be having
CPU cycles to process and
manage those incoming
requests to upload videos.
And then they're going to be using
up outgoing bandwidth to send those
videos wherever they're going to go.
So in sit, situations like that, although
you might like to have that extra layer of
control, just going directly to something
like S3 maybe more cost effective if
you're already running on Amazon.
So you have to think through those issues.
But if there was one issue that I
think should drive your decision to
use a provider services versus your
own expertise and custom built thing,
is to think about if my application
suddenly scaled up a 1000 times and
it happened next month.
Could I grow fast enough to support that?
Could I grow as an organization and
hire people fast enough?
Could I go and buy physical infrastructure
if I need to do that fast enough?
Could I support all of the things
that are going to be required,
including architectual changes, which
could be very difficult to implement,
in order to support that scale of growth.
And if you would all have an app that
you're expecting to grow like that,
then it's, and you can't answer yes to
that question, then you should go off and
think about using the provider's
services absolutely.
Because the fact that you can simply say
I want more capacity, give it to me,
and I will pay you for it.
And typically a lot of these things
get cheaper the more of it you use.
Your costs may go down as your capa,
as your demand goes up.
Whereas if you're managing all of
these architectural, hiring and other
complexities to scale your organization,
your application up and you don't
know if you can even do it fast enough if
your application starts growing quickly.
It doesn't make sense to try
to do it in the first place.
Build from the beginning
with the plan to offload.
Now some people get worried about,
well what if I get locked into a
particular, service provider and then for
the end of time, I'm going to
have to have my data over there.
It's always possible to build
your application in smart ways.
So using things like dependency injection
and spring, you can build interfaces that
abstract away the details of these
individual services provided.
Now you still have to understand
how they operate at some level so
that you don't treat a no SQL
database like a relational database.
But you can build interfaces
to help decouple you
from their specific APIs and
implementation.
And there are lots of ways to either
migrate out of a particular provider or
to even, you know, distribute your,
your business across multiple providers.
And there are frameworks out there
that can help you to do that.
But when you're building your application,
think about, can you scale up
quickly enough in each of the areas
that you're going to need scalability?
If you can't, very carefully think about
what cloud provider services are there
that you could take advantage of to
allow yourself to scale quickly.
And what would be the cost of doing
it yourself at a small scale versus
a large scale and the same thing for
using a particular provider.