[MUSIC]
OAuth is a specification
that's designed to fix
these issues in the typical log in and
get a session cookie model.
So.
What OAuth does is give you a way to do
a lot of things much better in this model.
One, is it tries to give you finer control
over the resources in a user's account.
So, we can begin to say things like, this
app should have access to upload videos,
but not delete videos in my account.
It give us a way to revoke access,
to individual apps.
So, I can say I no longer
trust this particular app,
I will revoke access to it,
without having to change my password.
It allows things like changing a password,
without revoking access to all of my apps.
Or, if you want it to,
it can revoke access.
But it begins to fix
a bunch of these issues.
It can also provide
a model whereby an app,
it can get access to your data or
some subset of your
data without actually directly providing
your user name and password to the app.
So, it doesn't, require,
user name, and pass going to the app.
So there are models with OAuth,
where you can actually go and
log into a particular website directly
through your browser or some other client.
And then that information that, that app
needs in order to get access to a part of
your account is given to the app
through another mechanism.
So you don't directly have to
provide your credentials to the app.
OAuth is often called the valet
key of the web, and the reason is,
is because to support all these things
that we talked about, it provides a model
where essentially you can create a key
that can be handed off to an app.
That can only access specific
resources within your account,
that you want that app to have access to.
So it's like your car when you're going
to park your car and you give your car to
a valet who is going to park the car for
you, you can give your valet key,
which gives them the ability to turn
on the car, drive it, and park it.
And lock the doors, but not get access
to the glove compartment or the trunk.
Where you might be able to store you know,
sensitive data about yourself.
But I guess if it's a car
you're not storing data.
You're probably putting money or
other things into the glove compartment or
the trunk.
And so
the valet key is something that gives
the valet access to the part of the car
that they need, the ability to turn it on,
drive it, park it, and lock it.
But not access to the parts of the car
that they don't need access to.
In this case,
the glove compartment or the trunk.
So, OAuth has a very similar model.
It allows you to create a key that
you can hand off to a specific app.
And that will give that app only
access to a part of your account.
And similarly at any time you can decide,
you know what,
I don't want that app
to have access anymore.
And you can revoke the key that you've
given into it without revoking your
master key, your user name and password
that you're using to mint these other keys