[MUSIC]
In the cloud, you typically have an
application that runs on multiple servers.
So, for example, if you go and
deploy your application across 100 or
more different servers in the cloud.
One of the big concerns
you have to worry about is
how do the incoming requests from various
clients get routed to the various servers.
So we've seen routing within each
individual server to figure out
which servelets.
But if we have multiple copies
of the servelets all running on
a different machine, how do we decide,
which request should be routed
to which different machine.
And then once we get to that machine, we
know how the routing is done internally.
Internally we use the web.xml, to route.
But, up here, how do we do routing?
How do we figure out which machine
should receive the request?
How do we get, keep track of
the loads on the machines and
all these different things?
Well, what this is called is
called HTTP load balancing.
So typically what we have
is a load balancer that
knows how to look at which
requests are coming in,
and figure out how to allocate
them to the various machines.
And there's lots of different
approaches for doing this.
But one of the simplest approaches is
just, just to do a round robin scheme.
Where when a request comes in
you allocate it to a machine.
When the next request comes in you
allocate it another machine and
so forth and this works very
well in certain situations.
In particular for round robin to work.
We want each of the servlets that's
running on these machines to
be stateless and
not to care about what client it's talking
to at that particular point in time.
So let's think about this and
why this matters.
Let's say that a browser comes in and it
begins talking to this particular machine.
And it's sending requests to this machine,
asking it to do something on it's behalf.
So, the first sets of
requests comes in and
they're all routed to
machine one down here.
And in the process of that,
it says, I'm going to log in.
So we now logged into
machine one down here.
Now let's say we're using
round robin routing up here.
And the next request comes in and
it now gets routed to this machine.
Well one of the challenges is depending on
how we set up our server is this machine
may not know that I'm logged in.
And I may try to go and
access some functionality like view
the balance of my bank account.
That this machine says well you
have to be logged in in order to
actually view that information
that you're trying to see.
So one of the challenges that we
have in a typical scheme where
we're doing round robin,
we're sort of blind routing,
where we're saying let's
balance our load across things.
Is we either have to have a way of
remembering state across all of
these requests.
Or we have to have a way of routing
requests more intelligently and
these things can affect how
we set up our servers and
distribute the work load across.
So how are the ways that
we could fix this problem?
Well, one thing we could do is we could
say, rather than routing each individual
request differently, to a different
machine, what we'll do is instead,
we'll remember which machine
a particular client was talking to,
and we'll always send all the requests for
that one client to that same machine.
So, if one of our mobile phones
begins talking to the cloud and
talking to this individual machine, we
can make sure that all the requests that
are coming in for that one mobile phone,
always get routed to that one machine.
And so if that phone logs in, that machine
will keep that state in memory and
it will remember that,
that user has logged into that machine.
And then if another mobile phone comes in,
we may route those requests to
machine number two down here.
And then if that person logs
in on that particular machine,
from their mobile phone,
we'll keep that state.
And so, rather than routing at
the individual request level.
We can route at a higher
level of individual phones.
So one of the things that
you have to think about is,
at what level are we going to route?
Is it at the individual, and are we going
to route them always to the same machine?
Or is it at individual request level?
And have we built our application in
such a way that it doesn't matter if
each individual request is
routed to a different server?
So one of the important things to know
is is your application stateless.
If your application is completely
stateless routings really easy.
You can route any individual
request in an individual machine.
However if your application is
stateful it's much more difficult.
You have to think about.
How you do the routing.
And so one thing is you may
just route requests to the same
machine that began
the conversation with that client.
So when a mobile client begins talking to
this machine you keep routing to that same
machine and typically what that's
called is sticky or sticky sessions.
And basically what this
means is we're going to
keep routing to that
same individual server.
Now, another way that we could
do this is we could make it so
that we could route to
any individual machine.
But we could do things
like session distribution.
So we could have, for example we could
store all of the information about
who's logged in or who's not logged in,
in a central database.
That all of our individual
machines are talking to,
and so this one says well it's logged in.
It stores that information with
some other type of token or
security information in the database.
And then if another request comes into
this server over here it goes in and
checks and says is this person logged
in or is this client logged in.
And what that will tell us is we
can go and check the database.
But because on a central
persistent mechanism that's
shared across all the different servers,
we don't have to worry about if the first
request is routed here and the second
request is routed there because.
The state is not being kept in this layer.
Instead the state's being
kept at a lower layer.
So these are some of the concerns that
you have to worry about when you're
load balancing or doing HTTP load
balancing across your various servers.
Is figuring out: is your application
stateless or is it stateful?
And if it's stateful.
How are you going to manage that state?
Is the state going to lee,
live on a single machine in its memory?
In which case you need to route
all of your requests from the same
client to the same machine over and over.
Or is the state distributed
across multiple machines?
Either using an M memory, distributed
in memory cache, like memcache D, or
a database that's connected to
all of these different machines.
In which case, if it's stateful, and it's
got a, a state distribution mechanism,
to where all your servers can see
that state, then you don't again,
don't have to worry so
much about the routing.
So, these are important
concerns to think about.
When you're building your
HTTP load balancing strategy.