[MUSIC]
There's a group of participants
that are involved in this idea of
creating valet keys that we're
going to hand out to the web.
So, let's look at what those participants
are, if we're going to use OAuth for
doing mobile authentication.
Now, when I say OAuth,
I mean OAuth 2.0, although I'm going
to be saying OAuth over, and over.
The first one is the resource server.
And this is the entity that is responsible
for managing all of the resources.
The bits of information, or
the services that we would like to be
able to control access to using OAuth.
So this is going to be like
your spring controllers.
The data stored in your database.
All these things are going to
be part of the resource server.
So, this is really your
application that you're writing.
Your spring based application or
cloud service that you're writing,
you can think of as the resource server.
The second piece of this is
the authorization server, and
this is the server that is going
to be responsible for deciding who
should get access to what, and managing
and brokering those types of interactions.
And although the word server is used here,
there's,
these things can be combined
into a single application.
So, for example, when we use Spring OAuth,
Spring provides a controller that plays
the role of the authorization server.
So even though it's a controller and
all of our controllers are also running in
the same application, it's still
called the authorization server.
And then we have the resource server.
And then we have the client
that is going to be
trying to get access to
some particular resource.
And then finally,
we have the resource owner,
which you can think of as our users.
So, we're going to also
say that this is a user.
So, when the client wants to go and
get access to some resource.
What's it's going to do is
it needs to get a valet key
to give it access to
that particular resource.
So, what the client does is it will go and
ask using one
of the OAuth flows for the authorization
server to give it a valet key.
Or in this case what we are going
to talk about is valet are tokens.
So we're just going to do
something like send a request to
/OAuth/token asking for
a particular token that it needs.
Now depending on the particular
OAuth flow we're using,
if the client already has a user name and
password for the resource owner or
in this case the user in our system.
The authorization servers can go and
validate that information and
create the token that it needs.
In the case that we're going to be
working on, we're going to be using.
Because we're building a client for
our own service in the cloud, and
we control the implementation
of that client and
we trust it,
we're going to be using a password grant.
Where we're going to actually
provide the login screen
that allows the resource owner or
user to give their user name and
password, so that the client can go and
get a token or valet key.
However, if we were using one of
the other flows, what would happen is
that the authorization server would send
a request back to the resource owner.
Typically this is displaying
a login page to the resource owner.
The resource owner would log in and then
the authorization server would give it an,
another page saying,
this client wants access to X, Y and
Z capabilities in your account.
Are you okay with that, and
you would say, yes or no.
And then the authorization server,
depending on what you said,
would either give the client a token or
not give it a token.
Now, in the flow that we're talking about,
we're going to be using a password grant.
So, the user is actually going to
provide their user name and
password to the client.
Because we are building the client and
we're building the service, so
we trust our particular client.
So, the user name and password is
going to be provided to the client.
The client is going to do
what's called a password grant.
It's going to send a post request
to the authorization server.
And then Spring, this post request
is going go to /OAuth/token.
And inside of this post request,
there is going to be a request body that
is the URL encoded key value pairs for
the username,
the password.
So these are the values that
were provided by the user or
resource owner, the Client I.D..
So, in this case
an identifier of our client.
We are also going to have grant type,
type,
and that's going to be equal to password.
And then finally, if we want to,
we can have scopes, which is, we can
ask for a specific set of, of resources
that we would like to have access to.
So this is similar in,
in many respects to the roles that we've
talked about with Spring Security.
This is asking for, you know, a, a scope
to have access to on the resource server.
And that will determine what this
valet key is good for or not good for.
So, the scope is determining is this
a valet key that will turn the car on and
allow me to park it,
will it allow me to lock the doors,
will it allow me to open the trunk, will
it allow me to open the glove compartment.
That's what the scope controls,
the scope of access.
So, all of this will be sent to the
authorization server, and this will be URL
encoded into the body of the request.
Now, also in this, Spring requires,
with its implementation of this flow,
that the client authenticate itself.
So, HTTP Basic authen, authentication
is going to be used for
the client and the client's password.
So, this is for client.
Now, the idea behind this is that,
we can have a client that has, that we
trust more or less than another client.
And so, on the server,
we could store secrets that were
associated with specific clients.
So, a client could prove its identity
by providing its ID and its secret.
Now, in this case the client that we're
going to be installing on the mobile
device is sort of out of our control,
it's going on an infrastructure
that we don't control.
And so
if we embedded a secret into this client,
anybody could decompile our app and
simply take that secret out.
So, it doesn't make sense in this case
to actually have a client's secret and
authenticate the client.
So in our case,
we're actually just going to be using
HTTP Basic with an empty password.
We're not going to be,
actually be assigning a password.
The only reason we're doing this is
Spring actually requires that we
use basic authentication for
the client as part of this,
this flow because it is in the OAuth spec.
But in this case we can't have a secret
and have it protected on the client.
So, we're not going to provide a secret,
we're just going to have
an empty password for the client.
Now this may seem like scary,
like why are we using an empty password,
doesn't that mean anyone can get access.
And the answer is no.
Anybody, they, they still have to
have a valid user name and password.
And the token or the valet key
that we're going to be creating is
still bound to this person's account.
So, we're just not able to prove
that a client is a specific client.
But we are using this flow because this
is the one that makes sense when you
write both the client and
the server side of this stuff.
What's going to happen is
the authorization server will then look at
all of the information
that's been provided to it.
And if all of it matches up to its
expectations, so the user name and
password is right and the the HTTP basic
is there, and we have all of the other
parameters that we need, then it's going
to return a token back to the client.
And this token is, is simply a string that
the client will be able to use in a second
when we talk about the next part of
access, to prove that his authenticated.
And when it provides this token
back to the authorization server,
the authorization server will allow
the client to get access to the specific
resources that fall within the scope
of the token that it got, and
the user account or,
of that particular resource owner.
HTTP basic is a authorization mechanism,
or
authentication mechanism, that's
incorporated into the OAuth 2.0 spec.
And in this case,
in the flow that we're looking at,
is being used to try to
authenticate the client.
In our case, we're not actually using
it to do any authentication for
us, but it is worthwhile to understand
how it works and how it's being used.
With HTTP Basic authentication,
the client includes in a header.
And these, all of this
communication should always over be
HTTPS because we're going to be sending
a user name and password with our request.
So in this request,
what we do is we include a header for
authorization, and
the value of that header is basic.
The word basic or
the keyword basic followed by
the username, colon, password.
And this information here
is then Base 64-encoded.
So we ended up,
we ended up with something
that looks like Authorization
Basic.
And then, I have no idea what a, you know,
a proper hash, I mean base 64
encoded value will look like.
But something along the lines of this,
where we have our authorization header and
then the value for it is basic
with the user name colon password.
Base 64 and coded into a string.
And all of this is passed in
a header to the server and
then the server can pull
out this part right here.
It can see based on this
that the authorization, the,
the authentication scheme
is supposed to be basic.
It can then pull this value out and
extract the user name and
pass out of the value, and
then use it for authentication.
Now, you can see why it's so
important that this run over HTTPS,
this is being sent in plain text.
If you don't protect these requests that
have basic authentication with HTTPS,
you're essentially sending
your user name and
password over the network where
anybody could intercept it and see it.
So it's really critical that
this always go over HTTPS.
And in this flow that
we're looking at here,
we're going to be sending that information
to the client, which is the user name or
the client ID,
in this case is going to be the user name.
So we're actually replicating
this bit of information.
We're going to include it both in the,
the body of the request and
in our authentication header or
authorization header.
And then the password in our case for what
we're going to be doing is just the empty
string, because we don't trust
the clients to have a client secret.
If you did trust them, this would be,
the client secret would be
the password down here.
But in our case we can't
trust the platforms that our,
that our apps are running on.
Somebody else's mobile device,
if they took our app,
they could easily extract
the client secret.
So we're not going to
be providing you one.