[MUSIC]
One consideration when you're
building your application and
deploying it to the Cloud, is what
style of, services you're going to use.
Are you going to use
Infrastructure as a service.
Which is typically called IaaS, or
you're going to use Platform as a Service,
or PaaS.
And this is one of the big
decisions that you'll have to make.
When you're trying to figure out how
you're going to build your application,
and how you're going to
deploy it into the cloud.
So let's talk about what each
of these things are, and
compare and contrast them a little bit.
You can think of infrastructure
as a service as the closest thing
to basically buying a new
machine in the cloud.
You're asking the cloud provider to go,
and turn on
a virtual machine typically that has some
configuration that you know how to use.
So there, that cloud provider will go,
and turn on the base virtual machine or
container or whatever it is,
and then you will go and
stack on top of it the different
components of your application,
maybe your, controllers, maybe you'll
go and stack some other utilities.
On top of this thing.
Maybe you'll put a database on a node, and
you'll begin stacking all the different
pieces that you need for your application
on top of this virtual machine.
Now the nice thing that this gives you,
is it gives you the flexibility to
control the type, and
configuration of the virtual machine.
It gives you the ability to control
all of the different pieces that go in
that virtual machine, and it gives you
control of things like security, you can
decide what the controllers can, and can't
access under on the underlying machine,
what APIs are available to them, you can
mix and match things that are written in
C++, and are built just for that Linux
virtual machine you're running on.
With your Java code, and
easily build up a very custom
environment that you want to run in.
Now the downside of this is all of this
customization that you're doing means that
it's something very specific to you.
So you're also going to have to manually
decide all of the auto scaling policies,
and how you scale up.
You're going to have to build your own
infrastructure to configure machines.
So you'll need to have scripts to
automate the setup of these machines,
to automatically monitor these machines.
So you'll need to know what's running and
be able to track it and monitor it.
You'll need to be able to
handle load by auto-scaling.
You'll need to do all kinds of different
things, that are certainly doable and
within your realm of capabilities,
but you become responsible for
all of the aspects of not only setting up,
and configuring these virtual machines.
But launching them, monitoring them,
handling the load and
auto scaling as needed.
So infrastructure as a service gives
you the bare metal to build your
application on top of.
But you become responsible for
all of the monitoring, and
management capabilities of,
of dealing with those machines.
With platform as a service what you
do is you provide your application.
So in this case it would be your web
application, like a war file which would
have the controllers, and other things
that were going to handle the request.
And the platform as a service.
[MUSIC]
Is what takes your application.
Automatically for
you configures a web container.
Configures the underlying virtual
machine that it's running on.
Decides all of the security settings.
Decides when to scale it up or down.
How much capacity it needs.
And runs it for you.
Now the advantage of hte platform
as a service is it takes away this,
this complexity of how do I go,
and actually set up my machines?
When should I add machines,
how should I monitor them?
And it gives you all of the tools to
support the actual execution, and
running of your application.
And to.
You can give it hints as to what you're
expecting in terms of performance so
that it can try to automatically
scale your application for you.
It can also give you all kinds of tools,
that are tightly coupled to that
platform that can tell you things like
collecting the request logs across all of
the machines that you have
running with your application.
So that you can go and look across.
A thousand machines and
see the requests that are coming in and
what they're logging.
Or if you want to go and look at
the performance of how your application is
interacting with the database,
that the PaaS system has created or
the platform as a service,
you can go in and
look at that, because they provide
you tools to give you those metrics.
So with platform as a service,
you get that advantage,
that you have all of the management
infrastructure provided for
you and built for you, and
you are getting to use it for
free you just have to go to build
something that fits into their model.
Now the downside of this approach is that.
You typically have to write your
application to live within the,
the limits of what they will allow.
So you, you don't get the same
configurability you do over here with
getting to decide exactly which
database you want to use.
Or exactly which set of monitoring
infrastructure you want to use.
Now there are some newer approaches
that are starting to blend this.
Model of infrastructure as a service and
platform as a service, but right now
if you have pure platform as a service or,
or pure infrastructure as a service,
platform as a service is going to be more
restrictive on what you can and can't do.
And more of the set up and
management infrastructure is going to be
taking care of one as
a platform as a service.
Side versus an infrastructure
services side,
so over here you can spend a lot more
emphasis on just writing your application,
and then letting the platform
as a service go and
run it and figure out how to operate
your application effectively.
Make sure it's always available and
always running.
Over here you take over that.
Functionality, you have
to keep it running,
you have to scale it, but
you can decide to do anything you want.
If you want to save a file to the virtual
machine that you're running on,
you can do that, whereas over here you
may not have access to the file system.
You may have to use some vendor
specific API to store that file.
So you have a trade off, when you're
using infrastructures as a service versus
platform as a service primarily, and
how much effort you have to put put into
managing, and setting up, and scaling
the platform that you're running it on.
You have a trade off in terms
of how configurable versus not
configurable you are.
And then a trade-off in terms of you,
how tightly coupled you
are to standards versus
a particular vendor's APIs.
So there's a number of things to consider.
If you're a very small developer, and
you don't have a lot of experience
scaling an app up to huge scales.
You might be better off with platform as
a service, because you're not going to
have the capacity to manage
this application at scale.
Particularly not without all of
the tools that have been built for
a platform as a service environment
like Google app engine.
With the an Infrastructure
as a service environment,
just like Pure Amazon EC2 where
you're setting up virtual machines.
This may be great if your in
an application that has deep expertise in
scaling up applications,
and monitoring them.
And you've got all of the tooling and
infrastructure for it.
And it will give you
greater flexibility and
freedom in how you build
your applications.
And not necessarily be tied in to
one particular vendor's platform.
So there's various concerns,
that you have to think through when
you're trying to make this decision,
between infrastructure as a service versus
platform as a service for your cloud
service to support mobile devices.