[MUSIC]
Once we go and send the request
to the authorization server and
get back the token that we are going
to use as our valet key, we can go and
do things like try to get access to
the video service that we've created.
And the way that we do this is
after we've gotten the token back,
whenever we send the request to the
server, Spring is going to have a filter
that's going to first look at the request
and check for the presence of a token.
And then depending on what token is there
and what, security we've set up and
things that we've done like adding
pre-authorize annotations to
our video service, the Authorization
Server will decide if we can get access to
a particular controller or controller
method that we're trying to access.
So let's say that we wanted to go and
access the Video Server, and
we sent a post request to /video.
In order to tell the Authorization Server
that we, we've already authenticated and
we've gotten a valet key,
we add an authorization header
like we did for basic authentication.
But rather than using
basic as the keyword,
we use bearer meaning a bearer of tokens.
Whoever has this particular token is,
should get access and get whatever rights
associated with that token, and then we
provide the token we received before.
So we go and use our password grant
to send a request to OAuth token and
we get a token back, and then in all
future requests when we're going and
send in a request to get access to
something like our video service,
we add an authorization header.
And then the value of it
is the word Bearer, and
then the actual token that
we received back up here.
And then what happens is, is that
the authorizations server will look at and
it will check the request coming in,
it will look at the bearer
token that we will provide.
It will see if it's a valid token and
if it, and then based on the token that's
provided, it will figure out what
user that token is associated with,
what account that associated,
token is associated with,
what scope that token has.
So, what resources
should be accessible and
then it will look at the video service or
whatever else you're trying to access and
the security policies
associated with it and
it will make a decision based on the token
the user that it's associated with,
the scope that the token has and
the policy associated with
the video service and
decide if that request can proceed or not.
And then if it can, it will be sent to the
video service and you'll get a result back
to your mobile client which will then
be displayed to the resource owner.
And then, in the next request that
we send, yet again, we will go and
we will provide this authorization and
bearer token as a header,
in all of our requests, so
as long as we want access we
have to keep providing this authorization
header with the bearer and the token.
And the moment that we stop
providing that, the server will say,
the authorization server will say
this person isn't authenticated.
It's possible that these
tokens can expire,
in which case if the token expires
the authorization server is going to say,
yay you no longer have access, and
then you'll have to go through
the flow again to get a new token
back from the authorization server.
So this is the flow that
we're going to be using.
Now just like with basic authentication,
it's really important that this flow,
that anything we access with
a token always goes over HTTPS.
There's no way that we can
protect that token unless we
are sending all of our
requests over HTTPS.
So whenever you're providing
the authorization header with a bearer and
a token, you always need that
request to go over HTTPS.
Otherwise it's insecure and
anybody else could take that token, and
they began using it to get access
to the resources on the server.