[MUSIC]
The OAuth specification, or
the second version of it,
OAuth 2.0, was really designed
to solve a whole host of
different authentication
problems with Web-Based services.
Now, there're a variety of different,
what are called flows within OAuth 2.0,
that can be used to authenticate and
control access to different
web-based applications like the ones that
we're building in our cloud services.
But we're going to focus on one specific
flow that is most relevant if you're
building your own
application to access your
own cloud service that you've created.
And this type of flow
doesn't make sense if
the application you're
accessing is not your own.
So if you're, if you are either accessing
a cloud service that you didn't build,
or it's somebody's else's application
accessing your cloud service or
your application accessing somebody else's
cloud service that doesn't make sense.
This only makes sense when you are the
creator of both the application and
the cloud service.
So this part of OAuth is called
the Resource Owner Password Grant.
Or basically an approach for
replacing the original username and
password approach where we can get
a session token back, but with
something that's more flexible and makes
more sense from a mobile environment.
So the idea behind this is,
that we have something that's
called the Authorization Server.
And then we have our Resource Server.
And these are just using OAuth terms.
What the Resource Server is,
is it's really the controllers and
stuff that you've been writing.
This is really the logic behind your
application that you're building.
So, the term Resource Server,
it doesn't mean anything new,
it's just all of the logic that
you're trying to provide access to.
The, the resources, the cloud service
that you're trying to provide.
The Authorization Server is
the thing that's going to
control access to resources.
So, it's the thing that's
going to decide and
manage who can access your controllers in
the different methods in your controllers.
It's the way to think it.
So, with OAuth 2,
the way this works with a password grant,
is a client comes along, and
just like before, because this is
our own client that we're building and
not someone else's, and
this is a really important point,
it describes, it shows a login form.
So this is going to be like
on our mobile client, and
then it sends a request to the
authorization server for a password grant.
And this is really just a fancy way of
saying that it's trying to login
with your username and password.
And what the authorization server does,
is it returns something that is
similar to a session cookie, but
it's called a token, and it's going to be
a piece of data that you can then use.
It's the equivalent of that valet key for
the web.
So when you go and
you're parking your car, and
you want to give access to
the valet to park your car, but
you may not want to give them access to
your trunk, you give them your valet key,
which only gives them access to a subset
of the capabilities of your car.
Well the tokens that an authorization
server returns, can be setup so
that they only grant access to
a certain set of resources.
So, the client then gets this token, which
is long lived and when it wants to go and
access a resource,
it has to use the token to get past and
get access to the resource that it wants.
And so what happens is,
that the token is provided to essentially
establish your identity just like
the original session cookie was used to
establish your identity, except that this
token has not only a user identity, but
it also has the allowed resources that
the client is allowed to get access to.
So you could have different clients or
different apps, use this grant.
Although just to be clear here,
if you are the password grant,
you should be the one that is
writing the client application.
But the idea is, is that you don't
have to give up full access.
You can login essentially with the
username and password and get a token back
that provides access to an arbitrary
subset of the resources on the server.
The other thing that's important, is that
what the client is actually storing,
which is the token,
is not your username and password.
So if for
some reason your token is compromised, or
your client is compromised, you can
just revoke that token without having to
invoke your username and password.
Similarly, you can set it up,
so that you can go and
change your password without
necessarily revoking all of the tokens.
And you can control the timing and
expiration of these tokens to make it,
the client's essentially have to log in
again at the intervals that you want.
So OAuth 2 looks similar to the typical
log in with your password, and
get a session cookie back,
but it's more sophisticated.
It provides token-based access,
that makes more sense for a mobile client.
It also provides finer granularity
over the control of your resources.
And then your resources are really
the methods on your controllers.
So defining which methods on your
controllers can be accessed and
you can change that depending on the
request and what the client is asking for
you can send it back a token that only
gives it access to the resources or
the controller methods
that it needs access to.
And then the client, each client,
can have its own token that it sends to
the authorization server in order to gain
access to some resource on your server.
And again these resources
are just controllers.
So you get a more fine grain access.
There're other flows in OOP that allow
other clients that aren't created by you,
to get access to tokens
without having that app
show a login screen that's
controlled by that client.
But, those flows are not exactly relevant
to us at the moment because we're going to
be creating our own client and our own
service and consuming our own service, so-
But if you're interested in them,
there're other flows that essentially
allow these clients to go and
ask for access, redirect the user to a
webpage that's controlled by this server,
where the user logs in and then accepts or
denies access for this particular client.
And you've probably seen these types
of web pages when you're trying to
access Google services or
Facebook services potentially from
a client that you are writing.
Now, if you were going to implement
all of this infrastructure for
going in, receiving tokens from a server
and deciding which clients should and
shouldn't get tokens, and which clients
were allowed to ask for tokens, and
which token represented access to which
resources, it'd be a lot of work.
But Spring has a built in implementation
of OAuth 2, and Spring Security.
And so what we can do, is we can simply
configure the existing implementation that
spring security provides,
rather than trying to
build our own implementation of
the complex OAuth 2 specification.
And Spring Security's implementation
provides implementations of all the flows.
Not just the password grant flow that
we're talking about for our mobile client.
But luckily for
our password grant flow, Spring already
provides an implementation of that flow.
So what we have to do, is if we go back
and look at the way this works, is we have
our Auth server or Authorization server,
and then we have our resource server.
And again, this is your controllers, and
the methods on them
which are the resources.
So you have your controllers and
methods of the resources that are,
that resource server.
The OAuth server, this is a controller
provided by Spring Security,
that knows how to provide tokens
and check tokens on incoming requests.
So, this is basically going to
have a separate endpoint for
getting tokens that's going to, depending
on how you configure it be something like
OAuth/token and
those requests will be piped into
this controller from Spring Security.
And then when you go and send a request,
there will be a filter,
that's actually going and
intercepting the request and
checking for a token.
So, Spring Security is doing
all of this token work for you.
And then depending on what token is
in there, it figures out what user
is accessing it so you can get access
to information about the user.
But the other thing is, is you can provide
additional security information or
annotations on your controllers, so
you can basically provide
security restrictions-
Based on OAuth.
So we can go and say for example, that,
if the client is sending a request
with a token, that, that token must
have a particular scope applied to it.
So, scopes in OAuth terms are the sort of
controls over the sets of resources
that a client can access.
So, similar to, we had users had roles
when we were doing Spring Security before,
which is simple session management.
OAuth has the concept of a-
OAuth has the concept of the scope, so
we can go and add assertions about the
methods in our controllers saying that,
if a client is accessing a particular
controller method through OAuth,
the token that they're providing must
have a certain scope associate with it.
So it's not just a user, but
it's a particular scope that then defines
the actual methods or controllers that,
that client can get access to.
And so, you can take the same username and
password and dish up different tokens
that have different scopes attached to
them, and then use the different tokens to
either be able to or not be able to access
a particular controller and method.
So, each time a client goes and
asks for a token from the server,
the server is going to decide what
scopes to put into that token.
So, the client will say, I would
like a token that has these scopes.
The server will decide if that's okay.
If it is, it will create a token
that specifically has the scopes
that the client asked for, and
then when the client sends a request,
if its token has the scope that it needs,
to get access to that controller method,
then the method will proceed.
But if the token doesn't have the scope
that the client needs to get access to
that controller method, the request won't
succeed and the client will be told
that it's authorization denied,
or something like that.
Access denied.