[MUSIC]
How do we create this idea
of a session on top of HTTP?
One of the nuts and bolts for a client
beginning a dialog with a server and
being able to continue that dialogue
across multiple HTTP requests.
Because as we remember, the client's
going to send a request to the server, so
let's go ahead and draw this out.
And we're going to have our
mobile device that's our client.
And the client's going to send
a request to the server, and
it's going to get a response and
then it may disconnect.
And then it may send another request,
get a response, and disconnect.
So, when we send this second request,
let's say this is the first and
this is the second.
How does the server know that this is the
same client that sent the first request?
Well, we could try to do this with things
like the I.P. address of the client.
We can try to say well,
if they're sending it from the same I.P.
address, or
the same MAC address on the network.
And if you don't know what these things
are, don't worry too much about it.
But the problem is all those types
of identifiers can be spoofed.
There's all kinds of tools
that an attacker could use to
send false data to the server about the IP
address or MAC address, or other things.
And other than ways that the,
the attacker can try to conceal
that data from the server.
So, how do we know that this second
request is coming from the same client?
Well, the way that we do this with most
typical web applications is by sending
a session cookie back to
the client with the first request.
So, what we'll typically do is have
a first request that something like slash
login, and this will be over HTTPS,
because we don't anyone to intercept this.
And we'll provide, you know,
the user and the password
in the HTTP request,
maybe as the body or something else.
And this'll all be encrypted and
sent via HTTPS.
So the server is going to see this.
It's going to validate who that user is.
It's going to check their password
against the password in the database and
then it's going to decide whether or
not they want to establish a session
that's associated with this user.
So, server may say yes,
I believe that this is Bob or
I believe this is Alice, and
I've verified their passwords.
And so, then the server's
going to send back a cookie, and
remember a cookie is just a little bit of
data that the server is sending back to
the client and asking it to remember.
So the server is going to
send back a session cookie,
which is a little bit of data
that the server is going to
use to help re-identify that client in
its session the next time it connects.
And so what'll happen is the second
request, because the server sent a cookie,
the cookie will be sent by the client
back to the server on the second request.
So, a cookie is a piece of information
that the server wants the client to
remember, and
wants the client to send with each
subsequent request back to the server.
So, on the server, you can see it's
going to send this session cookie and
it's going to associate this
session cookie with Bob.
So we'll call this cookie one, and
it will say Bob's cookie is one.
And then the session cookie one, when it
shows back up, it will go and it will say.
Whose cookie is cookie 1?
And it will say,
Well that's Bob's cookie, here.
And so it knows that the second request
must be coming from the same person,
or the same client,
that sent the first request.
Because that first request had a cookie
sent back, a session cookie or
a little bit of identifying data.
The client is providing that bit
of identifying data again, so
now the server can say I know who that is.
That's that same client that sent me
that original login request for Bob.
And so I'm going to treat
this request as if it's Bob.
I'm going to give them all of
the rights and privileges that Bob has.
Because previously, they provided me
with Bob's username and password.
And I sent them this cookie back.
They provided me that cookie again.
So, unless somebody compromised them,
I can trust that this is Bob
sending the same request.
Now, this is why it's so important
that this always be done over HTTPS.
At least for cases where there's
anything consequential and there's data.
Or anything consequential that
Bob can do on the server.
Bob doesn't want exposed,
that's his data that lives on the server.
So, when we are sending this log-in,
obviously, the username and
password needs to be protected.
So that needs to go over HTTPS and
encrypted.
The other reason is we want the response
to be encrypted because this session
cookie then gives whoever holds it
the ability to tell the server and
pretend to the server to
be a particular client.
In this case to be Bob.
So if somebody could intercept this
session cookie, they can then go and
provide it to the server and
impersonate Bob.
And get access to his bank accounts or
whatever else it is.
So this is why HTTPS is so
important when establishing and
maintaining sessions, is because we
want to be able to prove our identity,
get back a cookie and then we want to
be able to provide that same data or
proof of identity to the server and
do it securely.
So, this connection also
has to be over HTTPS.
Any time we're sending the session
cookie we want that data over HTTPS and
encrypted because don't want someone
to be able to intercept this.
If somebody can intercept
the session cookie,
they can impersonate the client
that's logged in with it