[MUSIC]
One of the key functions of Spring
Security is to help determine
when particular methods on our controller
should or should not be invoked.
So if we have a controller and we have
some
method, and we're going to call this our
uploadVideo method again,
we need to be able to establish the
identity of a client, like a mobile
device, that's sending an HTTP request, to
the server.
So, if this client's sending the request.
We need to have Spring Security sitting
here so that it can figure
out based on the request, who this session
is who this
session that's been created from
this client is associated with, which user
is associated with this client, and have
they
established a session, have they logged in
or done something else to establish a
session?
Now, a really important piece of that is
if Spring Security is
going to look at the request and decide
whether or not a
session exists and if a session does
exist, who the user account
is associated with, Spring Security has to
know about your user accounts.
So the way that Spring Security does that
is with something called the User Details
Service.
And this is a simple interface that you
can implement if you want
to create your own user details or some
way of storing user accounts.
It's simply a interface that allows
Spring to look up, a user, by name.
So, if you think about this.
If a client goes and tries to
connect to some protected method, like
uploadVideo, and
they haven't established a session, Spring
is
going to redirect that client to some
log-in mechanism.
Typically a form-based log-in for web
clients.
And then the user is going to go and type
their username
and password into that form, and send it
back to Spring Security.
And Spring security is going to go and
look up, based
on the user name, the appropriate
information about that user's account.
So when the user name comes back in,
Spring Security is going to call whatever
user detail service, has been
provided to it, and ask it to look up that
user
by the main provided in the look-up form,
I mean, the
log-in form, or whatever mechanism they
were using to log in.
So, Spring needs to know, based on the
user name,
I need to find the account associated with
that particular user.
And then that account information should
have their password or a
hash value of their password or something
else that Spring Security
can go and verify to ensure that the
person that's trying
to log in really is that user associated
with that account.
So, the user detail service is the part
of Spring that provides that notion of
user accounts.
So whenever you're trying to log in, and
this doesn't have to be HTTPS, I mean
this does have to be HTTPS but this
doesn't have to be a form-based log in.
This could be something like BASIC
authentication, which is
another way that you can do off, with
HTTP.
Or it could be some other mechanism.
But the key thing is, Spring need to know,
how do I take a username or
some other identity, and find the account
and
the information about that account
associated with that identity.
And so it has a name-based lookup
mechanism, provided by the User Details
Service.
So if you want to create your own
mechanism
for providing an account information to
Spring, you
need to go and look at the user
detail service and implement the user
detail service.
And all this does is, it's an interface
that has a
single method to go and look up a user by
their name.
And you simply return a user details
object.
And this is an object that has some
important information.
One, it has their name.
So when you do a look-up, you should get
back the user details with that same name.
It has password information.
It has some information about the validity
of their accounts.
So their account isn't locked or anything
like that.
And then finally it has a field in here
that you'll
want to know about which is called the
list of granted, authorities.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And what these granted authorities are.
Is if you go and add, like, app
preauthorize, or
something else, into your, on to your
methods in your controller.
So if you say,
at preauth, and I'm just going to
abbreviate this.
And you're looking for the role user.
And we'd have has role as an expression
there.
Granted authorities, you are basically
saying granted authorities,
one of the entries here, is the user role.
So these granted authorities are basically
different
authorities or roles that have been
associated
with this account, that then you can
go and check in things like, app
pre-authorized.
So when Spring goes and sees a request,
it'll automatically handle the
login process, talk to your User Details
Service that you create, find out
the appropriate account and then you tell
it which of these granted authorities
or roles that are associated with the
account are part of that user.
So, when a, a request comes in, it can go
and
look at the method that the client is
trying to invoke.
Look up their account and say, does the
security expression that you're specifying
here, like, has role user, match up to the
granted authorities in the account?
So this is a way of, providing sort of
attributes
or information about, what are the
capabilities of that user's account?