[MUSIC]
When you have multiple mobile clients
talking to a web application,
which we'll say down here, in a servlet
within that web application.
One of the things you have to think about
is, how does this server remember
all of the information in the state
related
to the particular client that's talking to
it?
So for example, let's say this is our
mobile device, and we're writing a banking
application.
And every time the user goes and checks
their account balance, one of the things
we want to
make sure of, is that, that mobile device
has
logged in or established its identity with
this servlet.
Now, the way that we do this in HTTP is by
establishing what's called a session.
And basically, this is an ongoing
communication or
dialog between the mobile device and the
servlet.
So, the session is the dialog, or the
conversation, between the mobile device
and the servlet.
And a session is where the servlet, or the
server, keeps
track of the state of the conversation,
what's been said so far?
What do I know about this client?
What do I want to remember the next time
that they send me a request?
So, what is a session and why is it
important in terms of talking over HTTP?
Well, if you think about the way that this
mobile device is going to begin talking to
the server, is it's going to send a
request and it’s going to receive
some data or some type of response, that’s
going to be sent back by the server.
So, that data will come back.
And then later, on it may go on and
send another request, and get some more
data back.
And so there’s a connection that gets
established, some data that gets sent,
sent back, and then that mobile device may
disconnect for some period of time.
So for example, you may go into your
banking application.
You may log into your banking application.
Now, then your phone is with you, you're
on a train, or on public transit.
You know, we wouldn't want to be texting
while
we're driving, or checking our bank
account's while we're driving.
But maybe, we're on the bus.
And suddenly as we're driving along, we
lose our signal and our connection.
And so, the next request that we send in
order
to check our account balance, it doesn't
have the same connection.
It is a completely new HTTP request that's
being sent
to the server and a completely new
response that we're expecting.
So, one of the things that the server has
to
do, is maintain that conversation, even
though that mobile device
was out of contact for some period of
time, and
there was no direct underlying network
connection to the device.
We still want the server to remember that,
that conversation, that dialogue with the
device, was ongoing.
And that maybe, that first request was a
login and the
second request is going to be, you know,
view the account balance.
And we still want that person to be able
to view their account balance.
We still that, want that device to be
able to access that information, because
we still
trust that session or that communication,
that dialogue
that was ongoing between the device and
the server.
So, sessions are this whole process of
maintaining a dialogue with a device and
maintaining information about that device,
in a
state of the conversation, across multiple
HTTP requests.
So that, if you use one HTTP request to
log in, and
then ten minutes from now you use another
request to access the account
balance, the session and the way that you
track sessions determines if you'll
allow that to go through and you'll
remember who that mobile client is.
Or, if they don't have a session, then
you'll force them to log in again.
But sessions are the way that we maintain
and remember those conversations with the
mobile clients.
Now, an important consideration on the
servlet is, and on the
server side are things like, how long do
we maintain a session?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Because, if we maintain a session too
long, maybe we're wasting resources on the
serve.
So, every time we begin a conversation, we
start a new session, well, that session's
going to
allocate memory on the server, that's
take up resources that aren't available to
other clients.
So, how long we maintain sessions will
affect the
resources that we have to keep on the
server.
It also may have security implications.
Maybe we want to force the person to log
out and log back in every
so often, to ensure that, that device
hasn't been taken or stolen, or something
else.
So, we have to maintain a bunch of
information.
What information should we maintain?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Is in the session?
So, what information is in the session?
So, what do we care about in this
communication dialogue between the server
and the device?
These are all important questions about
sessions, when we're
designing and building a cloud-based
service to support mobile devices.
And then, we typically want to use some
type of authentication framework, so that
we can strongly authenticate and trust
mobile clients, and
associate data with them and ensure that
if they begin a
session, that somebody doesn't come along
from outside and steal a session.
So, we have to worry about and insure that
once we
begin tracking a session, that there's no
way that somebody can
intercept that session data and use it to
exploit the server
in some way, or exploit the client's data
in some way.
So, these are all important
considerations.
So, how do we normally track sessions?
Well, the first thing that I, I want to
emphasize is that you should very
rarely reinvent the establishment of
session and
the tracking of sessions in those
mechanisms.
There are many libraries and frameworks
that are out
there that have been battle-hardened, very
carefully audited for
security purposes, and your first thing
that you should
do is go and look for one of those
libraries.
You do not want to reinvent your own
authentication mechanisms or session
mechanisms, wherever possible.
Instead, you want to use something that's
well understood, well tested, and
has known security properties and is
continually being analyzed for security
quality.
So, go and find a session library first.
But just to give you a, a rough idea
of how they understand work, there's a
couple different ways.
One is, session libraries normally take
advantage of sending back to the
mobile device, some form of cookie that is
used to
help remember the session for the server.
So, when the mobile device is going to
send a
request, it will normally send a cookie,
with session info.
And what session information you send will
depend upon
how sensitive the session is, and how
paranoid you are.
So, the, the very simplest thing is you
don't
want to send anything to the client, other
than an identifier.
So, you store all of the really juicy
details about the session
on the server, so you can have purely
server-side sessions.
And you have no data on the client.
So, that's one extreme.
At the other extreme, you could have a lot
of data on
the client, and only just store sensitive
things on the server side.
So, you can also have you know, partial
data on the server.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And partial data on the mobile device.
So, there's a variety of different setups.
The cookie is typically what's used if
you're going to store some data on
the mobile device, typically that will be
communicated back to the device through a
cookie.
Now, if you're using a mobile client, you
can do more than that.
You could send back data and have your own
protocol built off of HTTP, where you send
other
things back and you just expect the device
to
know how to handle those things and store
them.
Maybe you encode information in the
headers that are sent in the request.
But there's mult, multiple ways that the
device can store data, or
cookies, or other bits of information that
it then sends to the server.
And then whenever the server sees that bit
of data,
it can use it to establish the identity of
the device.
And remember, this is the same device that
sent the log
in request five minutes ago, that's now
accessing the account data.
So, what that bit of data is that the
mobile device
stores, is a little cookie, a little, a
little bit of
information that helps the server figure
out the identity of that
device when it reestablishes communication
with the server in a later request.
So, sessions are the maintenance of the
conversation, and
the state of a conversation, across
multiple HTTP requests.
Cookies are a common way that we store
information on the mobile device to
help the server figure out that this is
the same person sending multiple requests.
Or, the same device sending multiple
requests, and
therefore, it should associate them with
the same state.
But, we can have any type of information
sent back to
the mobile client, in order to help the
server establish that identity.
The most common types of things that get
sent back to the mobile device
are cryptographic tokens, a session ID,
some
form of information that would be very
hard
for the mobile device, or some other
client, to guess on its own, and send to
the server in order to establish a session
that maybe wasn't his, its own.
Or, to confuse the server, and something
that
will be unique across all of the different
clients.
So, we want to create sessions that are
unique, typically, across each individual
client so we can associate state
information with each individual client.
So, this is the concept of a session, and
the
basic idea is, how do we track state when
we're
going to have multiple individual
conversations or HTTP requests that are
going to be sent between the device and
the server?
And we want all of those
different requests, conversations, to be
considered one
conversation, one solid session, between
the mobile
device and the server and it's
communication