[MUSIC]
When we're maintaining a session one of
the important things is to
protect the data that's being sent from
the mobile client to the server.
And especially if we're going to do
something like operating a banking app
that's going
to be sending data about the person's
account to the server and receiving data,
rec-,
regarding the balances and the
transactions
and other things in the account.
It's really important that we protect that
data in transit.
So the very first thing we have to know is
that if we have, let's say a server.
And we have a client, like a mobile
device, that is talking to it over HTTP.
Particularly if you're talking over some
public WiFi network or something else.
All of the data in this request is plain
text.
Or should be plain text by default.
And what this means is, is that, if
there's
another attacker, who happens to be
nearby, or someone who's
on the network that can see the traffic
going
by, they can steal everything that's in
this HTTP request.
So, there are all kinds of tools that are
available that are simple to use tools
that attackers can download that can
readily grab all of your HTTP traffic.
So if you ever go and you go to a public
coffee shop, let's say, and you log onto
the WiFi there and
you begin browsing web pages and you see
that the URL for
the web page is something like http://,
this is just plain HTTP.
And so what you should be aware of is that
everything
that you send in those requests, what
pages you're browsing, all
of the data returned in those pages,
anything that you send
in the body of your HTTP request or in the
request parameters.
All of that can be intercepted by somebody
else.
So anytime we just see plain old HTTP as
the protocol, we need to be aware that
what
we're sending is in no way secure and can
very easily be grabbed by someone else in
the network.
Now, that might be somebody else that has
access to your
wireless network or it could be somewhere
else in the network.
So, for example you may be on a WiFi
network that's secured and you are talking
to an access point that nobody else has
access to, but once that traffic leaves
your access
point and travels out on to the Internet,
anybody who happens to have that traffic
routed by
them could look at it and see what you are
asking for or what data you're receiving.
Now there is a protocol that can stop all
of this from happening, and that's
the HTTPS, or the Hypertext Transfer
Protocol, the secure version of it.
So, whenever you see HTTPS, this is no
longer plain text, but encrypted.
So this is the protocol we want to use
whenever we're going to send
really sensitive data we wouldn't want
anybody
else to be able to view or intercept.
Now, HTTPS is based off of a particular
type of cryptography, or the, the really
important piece of it is based off
a type of cryptography called public key
encryption.
So, what we do with this, is when you want
to communicate with the server
the server gives your client a special
encryption key.
And whenever you're client needs to go and
send some
data to the server it encrypts all of the
data that it's sending
in a request and uses the key provided by
the server.
And so what this means is, is that
somebody else that's on
the network or someone else that happens
to see your traffic pass
by them, they can intercept it, but
because it's encrypted, it's more
than likely that they can't actually read
the data that inside of it.
One of the questions you may be asking
yourselves is, if the client goes and asks
for the key that it needs to use to
encrypt the data, how do we prevent
somebody else, some attacker that can
already see the
traffic, from producing its own key
that's.
Let's call it the a key or the attacker
key.
And we'll call this r key or the real key.
How do we prevent somebody from getting in
the
middle, or performing a man-in-the-middle
attack, where when the
server sends back the key the attacker
actually actually
receives it, passes a different key to the
client.
And then when the client begins to go send
data it doesn't
know it, but it actually begins encrypting
with a key, sending it
to the attacker and then the attacked may
forward it on or
change it by using r key that's actually
meant for the server.
So, we could end up in situations
where we have what's called a
man-in-the-middle attack.
Often abbreviated MITM.
And, we don't want to end up in a
situation where the server returns a
key that gets intercepted by the attacker
and
then the attacker can substitute a
different key.
So how do we know that this particular key
that we're getting back is really the key
that's associated with that server and the
one that it wants us to send data with.
That's one of the hard challenges that
HTTPS helps solve for us.
So to solve this problem of an
attacker potentially intercepting the key
that is going
to be used by the client to encrypt
the data, HTTPS relies on public key
cryptography.
Now, the idea behind public key
cryptography is that we want to be able to
have data that we can encrypt with one key
and only decrypt with a second key.
And, the idea behind this is that we can
share a
public key with everybody that we want to
communicate with us.
And if they encrypt data using that public
key,
then it can only be read by our private
key.
And similarly, if we encrypt data with our
private
key the receiver can decrypt it with our
public key.
So if we encrypt data with our private key
and the receiver can decrypt it with our
public key,
then they know that it must have come from
us or at least somebody that has our
private key.
Similarly, if they encrypt data with our
public key then only
we can read it because only we have our
private key.
So another way of thinking about this is
an analogy
of a mail box, or a lockbox, or a safe.
And the idea behind this is if we put data
into it using the public key,
the only way once we lock the lockbox with
the public key.
The only way to unlock it is to use the
private key.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So if we, public locks, private unlocks.
Similarly, if we put data in here with the
private key.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So the private key locks the box.
The only way to get it out is by using the
public key,
to unlock it.
And so what we have is this situation
where I can put something in the box and
lock it, and somebody can take my public
key
and unlock the box to get that data out.
And this is basically an identity
operation.
If I can put information into the box and
you can use my public key to unlock it,
you know I must be the person that put
that in there, and data that was put in
there
must be from me because if you used my
public key to unlock this box, then you
know that,
that means that I was the one that put
the data in there because I used my
private key.
Similarly, if somebody uses a public key
to put that
data in there, in the box, they know that
once they've
put that data into the box the only way to
get it out is for me to use my private
key.
So, they can have a confirmation or sort
of
a, a, a faith that if they put data into
this box, that only the holder of the
private key
can then unlock the box to get the data
out.
And this format is the basis for how HTTPS
manages to exchange the keys
that are used to protect the conversations
between the clients and the servers.