[MUSIC]
Now, if on your own, you had to go and
write all
of this infrastructure to create sessions
and properly protect them and maintain
them.
It'd be really difficult to go and write a
cloud service that's using HTTP to talk to
clients.
So, one of the nice things is that Spring
provides a framework, or an
implementation, of sessions on top of HTTP
that we can use in our applications.
So the way this works is we have a client,
that is talking to, our,
dispatcher servlet that Spring is
providing for us.
And remember, we don't normally do
anything directly with the dispatcher
servlet.
It's just responsible for going in and
invoking our controllers.
And we may have multiple controllers, so
we'll just say S here.
So we have all of these controllers.
So, all of the requests are going through
this dispatcher servlet.
And I'm going to start using https now
because we're going to emphasize the fact
that we want these things to be
secure when we're beginning to establish
sessions.
So, when we're talking to our dispatcher
servlet, and we want to establish a
session, there is a framework that we can
use called Spring Security.
And this is part of the Spring framework.
And basically what the Spring Security
framework does is it automatically
provides the ability to log in and then
send session cookies back to the client
and then using a filter that's right here,
in the front of the request.
So the filter is basically an object
that's receiving and looking at the
requests as they come in and then
checking the data and automatically
pre-processing them.
So, using a filter, what happens is, is
when the clients
send a request, if there is no cookie
here, and you're
sending a request to some controller and
some method on some
controller that's supposed to be
protected, or associated with the users.
So let's say we have a video upload
controller, and every time
somebody uploads a video, we want to know
the user that uploaded it.
Because we're going to track how much
space they're using up in their account.
We want to know which person uploaded
which video.
So we want to force somebody to log in,
and establish
a session, and prove their identity,
before they upload a video.
So, if you go, and your client tries to
send a request to that controller to
upload a video.
Basically, Spring Security is going to see
that you
have said, I want slash upload to be
protected.
Or this might be slash video, slash post,
or whatever the, the URL is.
That you may have some set of URLs that
you want protected.
Like I want anything to slash video that's
a post to require somebody to log in
first,
so that, in that controller method I can
see
who the person is that's trying to do it.
Who's trying to upload the video and in
order to get
access to who, you need to force them to
establish their identity.
So what the Spring Security framework does
is this
filter looks at the incoming request and
it says, is
there any type of session information in
here that
I can use to establish the identity of
this client?
So, it may look at this request that's
coming in
and it may say, oh, I see a session
cookie.
I will go and look up the user associated
with
that session cookie and I will attach it
to the request.
And then when the controller is invoked,
the controller will have access to the
user.
So, or it may go in and say there's
no data in here that provides information
about a session.
There's no session cookie.
There's no other data.
I'm going to redirect this client to the
login page.
And then after they log in, it would look
at the
next request and say, oh, there's a
session cookie here now.
I'll allow this request to go forward.
So Spring Security is this gatekeeper that
sits the front
and looks at what are you trying to access
down here.
Is the thing that you're trying to
access down here something that requires a
session?
That requires an identity of the client
and then based on that identity, it can
make a determination about whether or not
you should have access to it or not.
So Spring Security is this gatekeeper that
looks at the
request, decides the, what the identity is
of that client.
And decides whether or not that client
should have access
to that particular resource or that method
on that controller.
And that's what Spring Security is doing.
So, Spring Security can make this
determination in a number
of ways, but as we've seen, it can use
sessions.
So, Spring Security can automatically
check a request,
to see that if it has a session cookie.
If it does, it can look up the user
associated with that session cookie.
And then pass the request down, if
appropriate, to a method and
a controller, and the controller can see
the user associated with the request.
If it doesn't have a session cookie, it
can redirect the client to
the login page, and force the client to
provide a username and password.
Which Spring Security will then validate
against the list of
users and then return a session cookie to
the client.
So Spring Security can handle that log in
aspect as well
as the checking of the incoming requests
once somebody's logged in for
session information that it can then use
to automatically decide which user
is sending the request, and forward that
information on to the controllers.
And we're going to talk in detail about
how we access the identity information
from
a controller, and how we configure the
Spring Security framework to know about
our users.
And using this framework, we don't have to
worry
about, how does the session cookie get
sent back.
How do we remember when a session is
associated with a particular user?
All of that is provided by Spring
Security.
We can customize it, but we can build on
top of
it and just focus on telling Spring
Security, here are my controllers.
These are the methods on my controllers
that are
sensitive, and I want to know the identity
of the client.
Here are the types of clients, and
identities
that I will allow to access different
methods.
All of that type of determination about
who gets access to
different methods and controllers, is
controlled and guarded by Spring Security.
And it does all of the identity
establishment based on
the information in the requests coming in
from the clients.