[MUSIC]
A nice thing that Spring Security provides
for us
is the ability to control which of our
controller
methods can be accessed based on the
client that's
sending the requests and the identity of
that client.
So let's say that we have a controller
like our video controller.
So we have public class and I'm going to
call this VideoService again.
And I'm going to leave out the annotation
for, well, we'll go
ahead and put the controller annotation
here just so we remember it.
And I'm going to leave out some of the
other annotations.
So let's say we have a method, like,
upload.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And this takes a video or some other
information.
And this is a sensitive operation.
We don't want anyone to be able to upload
video.
If they upload something, we want to know
their identity
and be able to control who can upload and
how much they can upload, and other things
based
on the identity of the client that's
sending the request.
So, let's say that we have a series of
clients up here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And the first one is Bob.
The second one is Alice.
If we send a request from Bob and it gets
routed into this method, we want to do one
thing.
If an, a request comes in from Alice, we
may want to do a separate thing.
So for example, let's say that Alice is
the administrator of this website.
So Alice we might want to have access to
delete
videos, for example, whereas Bob is just a
normal user.
So, we don't want Bob to be able to delete
videos
necessarily, but maybe we want him to be
able to upload.
Alice, similarly, can be thought of as
also being a user.
But Alice is also an admin, so she can do
more.
So one of the things that Spring Security
provides for
us is this ability to associate roles with
different users.
So we can say this user is an admin and a
user, whereas Bob is just a user.
And then Spring will automatically go and
look at the rules that we provide
based on who can invoke different methods
based on their role.
One of the things that we can do with
Spring Security is we can add annotations
like @PreAuthorize.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then we can add some assertion about
the user that's accessing it.
So we can say, hasRole(admin).
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And what Spring will do is it will check
that the user that's associated with
the client that is sending this request
has the admin role associated with it.
And if it does, it will go ahead and
invoke the method.
If it, if that user does not have the
admin
role associated with it, then it will
block the request and
send back the appropriate HTTP response
code, like unauthorized or
whatever the particular code is that you
set it up for.
So, Spring Security gives you the ability
to go and annotate your methods and
provide assertions on security so that not
all clients can access a particular
method.
They can only access a method if they meet
the security preconditions
in the @PreAuthorize and other annotations
that Spring Security provides.
So in this case, anybody that tries to
send a request to the, that would be
routed to the upload method, would have to
have a admin role associated with their
user account.
They would also have to log in before they
send the request.
If they send the request and they weren't
logged in, Spring Security is going to
see @PreAuthorized, it is going to say,
there's no session established with this
client.
I don't know the user account that's
associated with this client.
And it would send the request back.
It's not going to allow that contact,
request to
continue, it's going to send back an HTTP
response
code that indicates that that was an
unauthorized access,
and that probably redirect the client to
the login page.
So, Spring Security can manage this idea
of deciding which users
should have access to which methods in
your different controllers
or your other resources that you create
like REST-enabled repositories.