[MUSIC]
Now to use public key cryptography, to
actually exchange keys securely, we have
to get a little bit more complex because
we have to introduce a third party.
And that's going to be our certificate
authority that we trust.
So what we have to do, is that we have
to agree on a authority that has a private
key,
that we trust.
And so, let's say that I am the client.
I have predistributed the public key,
for the CA.
And similarly, we have a server.
And the server has the public key for the
CA.
And so what the server does is it, before
it gets set
up or runs, it goes and says, here is my
public key.
And I would like you to sign or verify
that this really is mine.
And the CA returns a sort of
digital signature or certificate
validating the authenticity.
Now rather than going deep into the
details of how this works,
basically what the CA is doing is it's
using its private key.
It's encrypting the server's public key
and the address, the URL of the server.
So if this is foo.com, and it wants to get
a key, it's going to send
foo.com or its domain, and the public key
to the certificate authority.
The certificate authority is going to
encrypt both
of those pieces of data using its private
key.
Or basically, put them into the box using
its private key.
And then it's going to send the box to the
server.
Now, any time the server needs to get its
public key
and the domain that it's running on to a
client, so
that the client can verify the
authenticity of its certificate or
the key, it basically sends, and we're
going to call this the box.
This is really a certificate, but for, to
keep going with
the analogy that we used before, we're
going to call this the box.
So, we sent the public key and the
domain, something like foo.com, to the
certificate authority.
The certificate of authority took both of
those pieces of data and
put them into this secure box and locked
them using its private key.
Now, the certificate authority sends them
both back to the server.
It sends the box back to the server.
And now whenever the server needs to give
its
key, it to a client to communicate with
it.
In this case, give it its public key.
The server sends that box that has the
public key in it for the server,
and the client can guarantee and check
that nobody has
intercepted, and this also has the domain
by the way.
So in this case, it would be food.com, the
client can use
the public key that it already has for the
certificate authority, once you hit trust.
It can unlock the box, take the public key
out.
Look at the domain and say, yes, this
public key is attached to this domain.
And so if it's trying to communicate with
foo.com, it can unlock the box and see
that
foo.com is in the box as well as
the public key that should be associated
with foo.com.
And then, the client knows I can use that
public key
to communicate with the
foo.com server, in order to send it data
that nobody else can intercept.
And essentially, what the client and the
server do is
they use this public key in this initial
conversation to setup
a key in a secure communication channel,
the public and
private keys are not continually used from
that point of view.
They actually are used to set up
additional encryption information and
start a session.
But this initial start up of the session
is boot strapping is done through public
key encryption.
So this happens one time at the set up of
the server, so when food.com
decides I want to be able to allow my
clients to connect to me in a secure way,
they go and send a request to the
certificate authority to get their public
key attached
to their domain and they get that box
back or that certificate back from the
certificate authority.
And they do that once.
And then whenever any new client comes and
connects, they just
keep sending that box back with their
public key and their domain.
And the client whenever it wants, or
whenever it
gets this thing, because it should be
doing it every
time, can unlock the box with the public
key to
verify that this is the correct public key
for foo.com.
If an attacker gets in the middle here and
they try
to send a different box back to the
client, when the client
tries to go and unlock that other box,
that the attacker substituted
with the public key of the certificate
authority, it's not going to unlock.
And the client will detect, that they
received a box or
a certificate that wasn't the proper one
from somebody in the middle.
So the public and private key system
allows the client to
detect and verify that the key that it's
about to use
to communicate with the server to set up
this secure session,
really is the key that's supposed to be
associated with that session.
And the way it does it, is by using the
public key of the certificate authority,
to make sure that it can unlock the box
that it's getting back from the server.
If it can unlock this box, verify the
domain,
and very, and get the public key out, then
it feels trust to encrypt the data with
the
public key that it needs to set up the
session.
And send it with send it encrypted to the
sever using this public key.
And again, once any data that this client
sends and encrypts with this public key,
the
only person who's going to be able to read
it is that server on the other side.
Now, I keep saying session over and over,
and there can be sessions at multiple
levels.
The key thing to remember here is that.
The client and the server are exchanging
data to establish an encrypted connection.
And so, when I'm saying session here, what
I'm talking about
is that ecryp, encrypted con conversation
between the client and the server.
You'll also, typically with HTPS establish
a session at a higher level, another
session which is you application level
session
which will have other information in it.
But this lower level secure communication
is
based on this idea of public, private
keys.
And the fact that if I have a private key,
I can prove my identity
by putting some information into a box
that
only you can unlock with my public key.
So if you have my public key, you can
verify that information came
from me by seeing if you an unlock the box
with my public key.
Similarly, you can hand off information to
me by putting it in the box and locking it
with my public key, because you know only
I can unlock that box with my private key.
And so using a series of these box
analogies of locking data into a
box with a private key and unlocking it
with a public key and locking it
in with a public key and private key, and
adding this idea of a
certificate authority that we already
trust and
establish some key relationships with on
our clients.
We can dynamically set up and trust our
encrypted communications.
Now unfortunately, sometimes there are
errors in
how these things are implemented, as we've
seen from some recent vulnerabilities that
have
been discovered in things like open SSL.
But, the fundamental idea for this is a
sound approach for,
you know, using encryption and special
relationships between these keys to
securely establish a conversation between
the client and server that nobody
else can sit in the middle of, and
intercept data for.
When do we want to use HTTPS, or the
secure variant, instead of HTTP.
Well, one way of thinking about this, is
we can divide our data into two buckets.
The first bucket is data that's for
everyone.
There's no restrictions on it.
This is the, the free data zone where
anything that we put into this box,
we assume that anybody else can read, so
anything in the everyone category anyone
can read.
And
anything that we put in the everyone
category, if we accept a post
request or a put request, or a delete
request, or any of those things.
Then potentially anyone,
can write.
So if we accept those other types of
request like click post, delete,
then anybody can write them too.
Now, the second bed of data that we are
going
to talk about is, we are going to call the
restricted,
so if there is even a single person who
shouldn't have either read or write
access to all of the data in here, then we
need to put it in a restricted box, box.
So is there a, any
client, that
shouldn't
read, write, all,
of, the, data.
Any time that we answer yes to this
question.
If there is a single client that shouldn't
have access to all the data, or shouldn't
have access to write all of the data then
more than likely we want to use HTTPS.
So we think of this a HTTPS communication,
and we think of this as HTTP
communication.
So anything that we are doing that is
for everybody, we're not trying to hide
anything.
We're not trying to restrict anything then
HTT pre, HTTP probably makes more sense.
If there's any restriction in anyway.
Let's say, some of this data is owned by
one person and some of it is
owned by another person and they shouldn't
have
access to each others data, then HTTPS
makes sense.
Or some of the data is public and I can
get to it, but
other parts of the data are private and
only the administrator can get to them.
And where, where, it sort of implies that
we're going to have HTTPS.
Anytime we have something that isn't for
everyone,
anytime we have operations that aren't for
so maybe all of our data can be read, but
only some of it can be written
to, like with put post, or delete, and who
can write to it changes based on
what data it is or, certain people can
write to all of the data but others can't.
Anytime we have these restrictions on the
data, and we have two
buckets, the bucket for data for everyone,
and the bucket that's restricted.
Anytime we have the restricted bucket,
anytime we don't
want everyone to have read access, or if
we're writing
data, every time we don't want everyone to
write
access, then we need to switch over and
use HTTPS.
If you're serving up email, you should be
over
a web, you know, browser, you want to use
HTTPS.
If you're returning the person's private
contact
deals, details, you want to up HTTPS.
If you're returning the weather, in a
particular region, you're
going to use HTTP, because that's public
data, nobody cares.
So this is how you want to think about
when you're
building your clients, whether or not to
use HTTPS, or HTTP.
Do you want anybody to have access to all
of the data?
And if you are allowing data to be written
to, do you
want anyone to be able to write to all of
the data?
If the answer is no, to any of those
questions, then
HTTPS should be involved somewhere in your
communication with the server.