[MUSIC]
To start this next example, it's helpful
to look back at the previous video service
controllers so that we can understand some
of
the inefficiencies in the code that we
created.
In particular, if you look at the video
service controller from the video
controller with JPA example.
If we open this controller up, one of the
things that we'll rapidly see is that
we've created this video repository that
is dynamically
provided by Spring and @Autowired into our
controller.
And then most of our controller methods
are essentially just delegating to the
repository.
So when somebody wants to add a
video, we're simply calling videos.save
and then returning.
When somebody wants to get the list of
videos, we're simply getting
the list of videos and returning it to
them from the videos.findAll.
When somebody wants to find a particular
video by name, we're
simply delegating to the repository and
asking it to do the work.
So, it seems like there should be a way to
eliminate all of this delegation.
Why should we provide all of these
mappings?
Shouldn't there be a way that Spring can
automatically figure out how to
provide all of these services through a
web and a RESTful interface without us
creating a separate controller and
providing
separate methods that are essentially
going and
providing all of the right annotations to
delegate to simple methods on the
repository?
Well, luckily there is.
As we've discussed, Spring Data REST can
automatically take a repository
and expose it and its various methods
through a RESTful interface.
So it can automatically create a
controller that will expose a video
repository and all of the methods on it
like save, or findByName, or
Delete through a RESTful interface that
can receive HTTP requests.
So we don't even actually have to go and
create
a controller that can delegate it, to, to,
to it.
We can if we want to, but if we don't have
to if we don't want to.
So, the way that we do this is we've take
our initial video repository
and we've added an annotation to it,
@RepositoryRestResource.
And we've provided a path to it, which if
we go
and look at the path, we'll see that that
path is /video.
So what we're telling Spring to do is take
this repository and expose it
as a service, a REST service, that can be
invoked via HTTP.
So if we go and look at all of the methods
like save and find, in
particular putObject or findAll and get a
list of all of
them, what Spring is going to do is
automatically create paths, request paths,
that if an HTTP request is sent to them,
will invoke those various met, methods.
So in this case, if you want to get a list
of all the videos, you can just send a
get request to /video and Spring Data REST
will automatically
invoke the repository's findAll method and
return all of the videos.
Similarly, if you send a post request to
/video, Spring
Data REST will automatically take the body
of that request,
turn it into a video, call the save method
on
the repository and then return an
appropriate response to the client.
So, by adding this simple annotation,
we've told
Spring to go and automatically expose our
repository
using a RESTful interface and create all
of
the infrastructure to allow it to receive
HTTP requests.
Similarly, if we go and look back at our
application, we'll see that there's
essentially nothing new here.
All we're doing is create an application.
And again, we're not providing an
implementation of the repository.
All we're doing is telling Spring that we
want to go and start up.
Now, what's interesting is if you see
in the last version, we had a
magnum.mobilecloud.video.controller
package that had our video service in
it, that provided all of these delegate
methods.
In this version of the application, we can
actually completely eliminate the video
service controller because we can simply
add this single annotation to our
repository.
And suddenly, it will go and expose this
entire
repository through REST and allow clients
to send HTTP requests.
So we're actually getting more
functionality than we had before because
not only do we have the simple methods to
add and
list, but we also get methods to delete,
to search them
by all kinds of different mechanisms that
we didn't have before.
And we're not even having to write a video
service controller at all.
So, not only have we taken our
code and eliminated an entire class, we've
eliminated
complexity from our code because we don't
have to write an implementation of a
controller.
We've also got in more functionality of
it and we know that it's dynamically
connected
to our database and guarantees that it
will
save things correctly based on what we
want.
So, this simple annotation is providing a
significant amount of power to us to
take a simple repository interface that we
define and automatically create all of
the infrastructure to allow us to save
videos and delete them and to
store them in a database, and to make all
of that accessible via HTTP.
So yet again, this is an example where
some simple annotations allow us
to connect HTTP requests to complex
infrastructure that Spring automatically
generates for us.
The other new interesting annotation that
we'll add is we want to be
able to have methods to find by name and
find by duration.
In this case, we've actually added a
findByDurationLessThan method, which
Spring is going to provide an
implementation of that will find all
videos
with a duration less than what we provide.
But one thing we need to do is tell it how
to
map the parameters from an HTTP request to
these particular repository methods.
So the way that we do that is we add these
@Param annotations.
And what this annotation says is go and
look at the title
parameter, which is the title parameter in
either of the query stream
or whatever, however it's send to the
server, extract it and provide
it as the title that we're searching for
in this findByName method.
Similarly, we're saying go and get the
duration parameter out of the request.
In this case, marked by @Param.
And provide it for the duration that we're
going and searching by in the database.
So, again, the more that we leverage the
features of Spring,
the simpler our code becomes, the easier
it is for us
to guarantee that our code is correct
because Spring goes and
generates correct implementations of all
of these complex functions that we need.