[MUSIC]
Once we've created our video repo, we
still have
to worry about how we expose it to the
mobile clients who are going to be sending
HTTP
requests to store videos and to do things
with it.
Now, it may seem fairly straightforward.
We could just go and create a Controller,
and
let's say it's our video controller, or
our video service.
And inside of this controller we could go
and have, the
repository, that we had just created,
automatically wired in by Spring.
So, we don't actually even have to define
it in our configuration.
We can allow Spring, to go ahead and find
it
in one of its internal configurations and
auto wire it in.
So we have our VideoRepo, and then we'll
just call this repo.
Now, what we'd want to be able to do is
allow clients to send videos to store.
So the first method we might add would be
public void save.
And we take a video.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then inside of this thing, all we're
going to do is say repo.save and the
video.
And we could return a response to the
client if we wanted.
And we'd probably want to go and just put
a request mapping on this.
To something like /video/save.
And you can imagine that, and again we
would need
annotations on the parameters, like on the
video to do the body of the request.
We might want to return some type
of different status codes depending on
what happened.
But the primary thing that we are going to
have is methods over and over that look
like save.
And then we delegate to the repository.
And we're probably going to have another
method
for delete, so that people can remove
videos.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And it'll take some data.
And then we'll probably have another
method for searching.
So we might have a method that returns a
list of videos.
And we have some findBy, let's say name.
And you can imagine that we're going to
have lots and lots of methods
where all of these methods in the
controller are just providing a request
mapping
that essentially takes a video and then
delegates to this video repository that we
created, that actually has all the logic
for storing this data in the database.
But it's a lot of work to go and
have to individually create each one of
these methods.
It's doing very little work.
It's essentially just delegating to the
repository.
Wouldn't it be nice if Spring had a way of
just automatically exposing our video
repository as a service that could be
accessed via HTTP.
So clients could directly talk through
Spring to this video repository.
And we didn't have to write all of this
code that's very repetitive
and isn't really what we want.
We'd really like to eliminate this stuff.
And simplify, so that we can just write
the things that matter,
our logic that matters, and we can ask
Spring to go and
do repetitive boilerplate things that we
have to do over and over,
like save, delete, and find videos, and
delegate to the video repository.
Luckily, Spring provides a way to do that
through something called Spring Data Rest.
And the basic idea behind this is that we
can take a repository and we can
automatically expose it through a series
of request
mappings like /video or /video and a
particular property.
And we can send different HTTP request
methods to take actions on those
resources, because
Spring provides a rest based mechanism
through Spring
Data Rest to interact with a video
repository.
So each of the pieces of data in the
repository is considered a rest resource,
and then the actions like get is
essentially a retrieval of a resource.
Put is the replacement of a resource.
Post is the addition of a new ray,
resource to the list of resources.
Delete is the removal of a resource, and
so
Spring Data Rest gives us a way to do
this.
To use Spring Data Rest to make our
repository videos accessible via
HTTP, or to make any other repository of
data accessible HTTP.
We have to make two important but small
changes.
The first one is, on our repository
interface, we need to add the
@RepositoryRestResource annotation.
And we're going to add two different
attributes to this annotation.
One of them is going to be the
collectionResourceRelation.
And we want something like videos, so if
you
have a collection of them how do you name
it?
And then we're going to have the path,
which is going
to be the path that we're assessing this
stuff with.
So, something like video would turn into
the ability
to access this stuff through a request to
/video.
So, the path is determining where this
thing gets exposed.
It's similar to how the request mapping is
built.
It's telling Spring where to expose this
thing.
Now this is the first thing we have to do
and we add this this annotation to our
repository interface.
So, we call VideoRepo, and
it extended a bunch of stuff.
And all we have to do is go and add this
one annotation to the actual repo,
and the interface for it, and Spring will
automatically
know that this is something I need to
expose.
And here is where I need to expose it.
And when I'm having multiple instances of
the resource
that I'm returning, here's what I'm going
to call them.
I'm going to call them videos.
Now, the second thing we need to do
is somewhere we're going to have a
configuration.
So, in some class we've got a
configuration that
we're using to define the components of
our application.
So we're just going to call this,
app.
We're going to assume it's in the
Application,
class.
And we have this configuration that's
defining
all of these different components in our
application.
To enable Spring Data Rest, we need
to import its configuration information to
automatically set
up its controller that its using
internally
to route and send requests to our
repository.
So in order to that, we need
to import an additional
configuration, and it's the
RepositoryRestMVC Configuration.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
This is quite long, it's starting to
extend past my writing capabilities on
this board.
But I think I just barely gotten it into
the video, hopefully.
So by adding this one annotation
right here, importing the
RepositoryRestMVC Configuration class.
And adding this annotation to
our repository interface, the
RepositoryRestResource, we
simply told Spring to go and automatically
take our repository, and
expose it using rest to mobile clients
through HTTP, or through,
to any other client, to a browser based
client using HTTP.
So we can now send, because we've designed
the path to
be video, we can send GET, we can send
POST, and other
requests to this URL in order to
automatically go and add and
remove and change the data that's within
that repository.
After we've created the repository
interface
for our video repository or any other
repository to save and retrieve videos or
other objects that we want to persist,
the last thing that we have to do in order
to enable those
repositories, is tell Spring to
automatically
create the implementations of those
repository interfaces.
And the way that we do that is in our
configuration for the application.
So let's assume that we have a
configuration
on a class that we'll call Application,
we'll assume it's in the core application
class.
And we have some various components that
are
being defined as beings or otherwise, in
this configuration.
The last thing that we need to do is add
an annotation @enableJPARepositories.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And this is the last key thing that we
need in order
to tell Spring to automatically go
and create the implementation of our
repositories.
Spring needs to know that I need to go and
create those implementations.
Now, there's two way that it can discover
the implementations.
The easiest way is we can add
@ComponentScan,
and then some package, like
org.mobile, let's say.
.data.
And let's assume that this is where our
repository is.
By telling Spring to go and do a component
scan, Spring is automatically going
to look at all of the classes in this Java
package that we've specified.
So we're just dispecifying fully qualified
name of a Java package.
And then Spring is going and automatically
scanning that
package and discovering all of the
interfaces that extend
to something like CrudRepository and the
other different types
of data repositories that we would have in
Spring.
And each time it finds one of those
interfaces,
it then automatically goes and creates an
implementation of it.
And then, anywhere where we want to use
that particular repository, and we've
added an, @AutoWired for, for example, the
video repo.
Spring will automatically, after having
gone through
this package, finding the video repo,
seeing
that it's a repository, it will create
an implementation of the repository and
then dynamically
find all the places where that repository
type is referred to with at @AutoWired,
and then place that repo implementation
object
into all of those AutoWired variables or
methods.