[MUSIC]
>> Spring Security can control access to
the methods in your controllers
without you ever having to do anything
other than annotate those methods
with information about the roles or other
expectations you have about the
user accounts associated with the clients
that are sending you the requests.
But there are cases where you would like
to have information about the user
possibly to add information that you're
persisting
in the database or do something else.
So, let's take an example.
So, let's go to back to our video service
and let's say we have our video service
controller.
And this would have all of the nice
controller annotations, other things, and
we have a method in this controller like
public we'll just call this boolean.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Upload video.
And there might be a video object or
something else.
But let's just say that it's a, we're
going to ignore all the other parameters.
Now, inside of this upload video method I
might want to do something
like, video v equals new video.
And depending on how you are passing all
of this stuff in you might set
some things, and then what I'd really like
to do, is I, before I persist this thing
in the database, I'd like to say setUser
and pass in a user,
or a username or something like that, in
order to store it in the database.
So, now when I'm persisting the object I
have a notion of who uploaded that video.
Now, if Spring Security is handling all of
this and I've
never seen the users, I can't do something
easy like this.
So what we have to do is tell Spring
Security
that it should pass us the information
about the current user.
And the way that we can do that is all we
have
to do is add an additional parameter to
our methods called principle.
And then we can do something like this, we
can say, string user
equals p.getname.
And basically what this is doing is
telling Spring,
whenever you invoke this method, we want
you to pass
in the principle, or the current
authentication the information
about the user that's sending the request
into this method.
And so it will pass that into you as an
object.
And there are ways to extract the actual
object
that you would get from a user detail
service.
If you provided your own user detail
service you
can get that user details object out of
the principal.
Or you can just get basic information like
the name of the principal out of it.
And then use that information to
associate, for example, resources that are
being uploaded with the actual user
account that uploaded that resource.
So.
Simply by adding an additional parameter,
and it
doesn't matter what the ordering of that
parameter is,
just if you have a principle parameter at
all, you can get information about the
current user.
So this parameter is going to be the
current user account.
And if no one is logged in this would
obviously be null.
So, these types of methods where you're
taking a principle as an
argument almost always need @PreAuthorized
or secured or one of the other
annotations to specify some security
information so that
no matter what Spring knows that before
you call this method, you
have to force the person to log in so that
Spring can get the principal and provide
it to you.
There's other ways to do it without
the annotation in your configuration of
Spring.
You could just say that this is a method
that requires full authentication.
In which case, Spring will always make
sure that if a client sends a
request, that they have to authenticate
and
create a session before this method gets
invoked.
And that way their principle information
will always be there so that
you can find out about the current user
account that's invoking the method.
Although we can get access to the
principle in our methods, a lot of times
we don’t actually need to do that in order
to provide some more advanced security.
So, let’s take an example with the upload
video.
So let’s assume we have this video service
and the users
can go in and post videos that are
going to be uploaded.
There postings in JSON that's being
converted
into a video object by Spring for us.
And inside that video object one of the
fields that
we have is some information about the
owner of that video.
Or this could be a delete method where we
are going to go and delete a particular
video.
But one of the things that we might want
to do is enforce the rule that
when you upload a video, whoever is listed
as the owner has to be the user that's
currently logged in, because we don't
somebody to
go and upload a video they don't own
or to upload a video and then have
the owner set to someone other than their
account.
We always want the owner to be associated
with them.
The way that we can enforce this is, in
Spring
we can use a more complex expression in
our @PreAuthorize.
We can actually say, hash video, because v
is the
parameter, .owner equals principal name.
And what this is telling Spring is, in
order to invoke this method, not only
must the client have a current session
established, that's associated with
a user that's known, but the video that
you're sending here, in this case, v.
The owner member variable of that video
down here has to match the name
of the current principle, or the
user-account
associated with the client that's sending
the request.
So we're not only restricting this method
and saying
certain users, for example, could have
access to it.
But we can also restrict the format or
the requirements in the data that they are
sending.
So, in this case we're creating a
relationship between the video
and its owner and the currently logged in
user and the name.
So this is the username of the client.
So whatever client has logged in and
established a
session, this is going to be the username
of that.
And this is going to be data that's coming
from the user, this video.
So this came from the user, or the client.
So, we're forcing them to make sure that
when they upload
a video that they are matching the
ownership to their username.
And so, we can have all kinds
of sophisticated expressions in these
@PreAuthorize annotations to
control access and control the
relationship between the
data and the user that's sending the
request.