[MUSIC]
One approach that you can use,
for optimizing for
reads is to try to group all
the data that you'll need for
a particular query into an entity that
you can fetch by a, a key in one go.
So let me give you an example of this.
Let's say that I have, the comments
page that we described before.
And so for each of these comments,
we're going to have
the user name that posted it, we're
going to have their particular comment and
then we might have maybe the home town or
the country of the.
user.
And maybe we have Belgium,
some other information.
And so we have a set of these comments.
Now, one way that we could support this,
is we could have a set of user entities,
where each one has a name.
And a country.
And then we can have a set of comment
entries, where each comment in,
in as well as having the text for
it has the user ID.
Or key for the user that created it.
So every time we want to go and
create this particular page,
what we have to do,
is we're going to first query for
all of the keys or all of the comments,
for that particular page.
So we'd probably also have some,
you know, page or
product ID or something to associate
comments and go and search for comments.
That are relevant to display here.
So we get the list of
all the comments back.
Now, once we've gotten that list
of comments back we can go and
get the user ID's for each user that are
in this table and hopefully be smart about
it and, and only then query for
the name and country of all the users.
That are in this table, are that are in
this list of comments, and then we go and
get back to user and name and
country for each particular
user that posted a comment.
Now, this is certainly one way to do it
and helps us, you know, keep our database
more normalized, because we're only
storing name and country in one place.
With the down side is, is that we go and
get this list of comments and then we have
to go down and get this list of users,
in order to display the users name and
the country that their from.
So, when we display this
page we essentially have two
round trips that we're dealing with.
Another way to do it would be.
Rather than having a separate comment and
user, what we can do is we
can have a separate user.
But our comment can
directly embed the user,
name, and country into the comment object.
So this way, when we need to go and
display this page.
So let's call this approach 1,
and we'll call this approach 2.
We'll put a little versus here to show
that these things aren't related.
When we need to display this page,
all we do is go down and
fetch the list of the comet entities,
or objects.
And return it, and
we can instantly display the page, because
we have all of the information we need.
So, if this is a mobile device, and
we want to very quickly give it
all the information that it needs.
Now, obviously, the server would
be doing these two round trips.
So, the mobile device, hopefully,
isn't doing theses round trips.
This should be something that's done on
the server, even if we doing it this way.
But either way, we're going to
data back to that mobile client to
display much faster if we have an entity
that has exactly the information
that is needed to display this
particular page in the mobile interface.
So, if we design our entities in ways that
give us exactly the data that we need,
it can make it much faster.
Another way that we could do this
is if we new we weren’t going to
have to many comments, and we weren’t
going to be writing to them to often.
We could even take all the comments for
a particular product, and have a single
comments, for let's say product.
Entity that directly inside of it
stores the raw text of all of this.
So, in this case, we have multiple of
these comment objects that we're going to
be fetching, that we could just as
easily have a single aggregate object.
That puts all of
the information that we need to
display this page into one entity that we
just look up with one key value look up.
So there's lots of different
approaches and they'll give you
different performance and different ones
will makes sense in different cases.
Probably in most cases if your
really trying to optimize for
the reads, it maybe makes more sense to do
something like this, but maybe it doesn't.
Maybe it makes sense to have comments for
product and embed them all.
ANd you really have to look at each case.
Now the downside is,
here we have normalized data, so
if the user wants to go and
update the country that they live in.
They, they are currently in the US and
they are moving to France.
Now they're going to have to go and
update their France, you know,
their country, if they're currently,
in France and they're moving to the US,
we're going to have to go and
update their country.
Well, here, that's no big deal,
we just go and update the user entity.
If we do it here, now we have problem.
We have to, if we, they update their
country we also have to go in and
update every instants in the comment
entries, where their countries shows up.
So we have to find every
one of that users comment,
we then have to find the country field
in it and that were in the value or
however it's been stored and
update it, over and over.
And similarly we'd have to do
something like that for here.
So that, that denormalization,
and these different approaches,
they can make reads really, really fast.
But they make, make writes or
changing just one entry in
the data really expensive.
So, you have to be careful that if you're
going to go for a model like this.
Or a model like this, that the data that
you're denormalizing into these things,
hopefully is not something
that will change frequently.
So if you were duplicating over and
over, you don't want that data item that
you're duplicating over and over, to be
something that will change frequently.
So, username for example,
you can have a system where you could say,
a user cannot change their name, as long
as they are having an account with me.
I'm going to have them have the same
username, they can never change it.
They can change their email address
to their hearts content, but
the can't change their username.
So going in duplicating username,
in all of the comments,
probably isn't going to hurt you.
But if they can change their username or
you're doing first and
last name and the person can
change their name potentially or
you're going to allow them to,
then suddenly it is expensive.
So you have to think through those
issues when you're trying to
make a design decision about whether
you're going to do something like this.
Or you're going to try to optimize it and
make it a really fast read that has all of
the information already embedded into
the entities that you're getting back,
or the single entity
that you're getting back.
But you are understanding that you
are going to pay a price if any of
this duplicated data ends up changing.
And that price is,
is you're going to have to search through
all these entities and change it.
And ten or 100 or
1,000 places rather than one place.
So, every time you duplicate that data
you're adding write overhead if you try to
go and update it in some way.