[MUSIC]
One of the nice things about the cloud
is that it doesn't require you to do
everything yourself from scratch.
So, although we may want control over
the database that we're using and
we may want to set up
a particular database and
configure it a specific way,
we don't have to do that necessarily.
We can also essentially
outsource the management, and
scaling of our database to somebody
else by using database as a service.
Now there are lots of different
databases of services that you can use,
we're going to talk in particular on
this lecture about Amazon's DynamoDB,
which is a DB that's backed
by solid state devices.
And has a nice property that
you can specifically ask and
allocate the number of reads or
writes per second that you would like your
application to have and then Dynamo will
charge you for that provision to capacity.
So, this is a nice capability in that
not only can we outsource our database.
And, you know, not deal with
how we set up and maintain, and
manage it, and try to scale it.
But we can also specifically
buy them out of
reader right capacity that we
actually need for application, and
be guaranteed that we can get
it by contract from Amazon.
So, what we're going to do now is, again,
we're going to be using spring data,
just like we did before.
And we've seen how we can use spring
data within memory, we can use it
with H2, or HSQLDB,
we can use it with Mongo.
And now we're going to see how we
can take this same abstraction.
And we can use it to connect to Dynamo,
where Amazon's database is a service, or
their high performance key value score,
if you want to think about it
in terms of a key value score.
So, very quickly we can go and again
switch over to a new type of database.
So let's look at this
example in specific code, and
what we need to in order to connect
our application to DynamoDB.
So, if you'll open up the video class and
we're going to start by looking at
this specific changes to the video class,
because they're connected to
the configuration changes that
we have to make in Amazon.
So if you open up,
the video class underneath the
org.magnum.mobilecloud.video.repository,
package and open up this video class.
What we'll see is we have the same
video class that we had before, but
we're starting to see a theme here.
We've seen it throughout this course,
we're just changing the annotations or
the meta information.
In order to support persisting or
saving these objects in DynamoDB.
So we're still doing the same
thing we did before,
we're mapping our objects into a database.
So let's take a look at this
very first annotation, and
we're going to look at the work,
the work we have to do on the Amazon side
in order to support this annotation.
So the first thing we're going to
do is we're going to tell.
Spring the data dynamo,
the particular dynamo table that
we want to store these objects in.
So in this case,
we're adding the @dynamo table annotation,
and then we're specifying
the table name is videos.
So what this means is,
if we go to our AWS console,
is that we need to create a videos table.
So, we'll go ahead and
create the videos table.
And then the next thing we're going to
see, is that there's, it's asking us for
the type of primary key.
Now, Dynamo is a key value store, but
it has this concept of a hash key and
a range key.
So the way to think of the hash key is the
hash key is just purely the typical keys
that we've seen before.
So we've had a, a key mapped to a value,
the way to think of the hash key
is that if we want a key that's
a combination of a key,
where the key is something like,
let's say we want to store all of
the events for a particular conference, or
we want to store all of the videos
uploaded by a particular user.
We can make the first part
of the key the user, and
then the range part of the key
the particular ID of a video.
So if we wanted to quickly go and
scan through all of the videos that have
been uploaded by a particular user,
we could use the hash part of the key,
which would be the user ID, to go and
scan all of the unique keys that were
created by that user ID plus
an individual video ID.
So.
Really, what a hash and range key are,
is they're a composite key,
where the key part is something that's
like a common prefix, almost like,
the user ID that stored the video.
And the range key is an extra bit of
information that when combined with
the user, there are,
when combined with the hash key,
creates an overall unique key.
So there'll be, there could be
potentially if your using a hash and
a range key there could be potential
multiple keys that have the same hash key.
But they all would combine
with their range key,
the combination of the two will be unique.
If you don't use a range key, then the
hash key always have to, has to be unique,
so if you use a hash key, just a hash key,
it always has to be unique for
each object that you're storing.
If you use a hash and a range key, then
the combination of them has to be unique,
but the individual hash
key may not be unique.
So, this is kind of a nice
capability of Amazon's DynamoDB, and
it can be helpful in many situations.
In this case, we're not going
to use a hash and range key,
we're just going to use a hash key.
So if we go back and
we look at our video class,
we'll see this ID which looks suspiciously
like an ID that we've been using to
store our videos before although we're
using a string rather than a long.
And if we go down to the getter for
the ID,
what we'll see is it's
annotated with @dynamoDHashKey.
And then at that arrow
DB autogenerating key.
So basically what this is telling Spring
Data Dynamo is that you should use this
particular property, this ID property,
as the unique hash key for the object.
And you'll want it to be automatically
generated by Spring data DynamoDB when
it's saved into the database and
assigned to this value.
So if we go back to
the setup of our table,
what we need to do is choose a hash key,
since we only have a hash key in
this class and
we need to set it to the ID property.
So this, whatever we're putting into
the hash attribute name needs to match up
with what we're specifying as the DynamoDB
hash key in our particular object.
So, once we've done that and
aligned that, we can continue on.
Now we get to another interesting
part of DynamoDB, and
that's the ability to actually specify
the read and write capacity, or number of
reads per second that are 4 kilobytes, or
writes per second that are 4 kilobyte.
That we like to have Amazon support for
us.
So, this is a nice capabilities that
we don't have to worry about how we
scale our database up to that
particular quality of service.
We can just ask Amazon for
it and pay for it.
We're going to go ahead
in this case just use
a simple example of one read per second,
and we're going to click through and
finish completing this table,
which will now show up in Amazon.
When we go back, we have now created,
our Dynamo table, for
the videos, and the other thing we've done
is we've annotated the particular get
method that has the ID that we care
about with the appropriate DynamoDB
hash key and auto generated key
annotations that we need to tell Dynamo,
that's what we want to use as
the unique ID of the object.
And we want it to be automatically
generated by Dynamo.
Then we also have the app
DynamoDB attributes that
are then placed on each of the different
member variables, the getters for
those member variables that we
would like to persist into Dynamo.
So one thing to note is if
you have other methods.
That are simple get named methods,
like get foo, and
foo is some property that you calculate
but isn't necessarily a member variable.
If you add @dynamoDB attribute to it,
dynamo will try to store that.
So you want to make sure that if
you add @dynamoDB attribute to
a particular getter,
that it's actually a member variable in
something that you can persist and set.
But that's the main work,
just like we did before with Mongo DB and
when we did with Data JPA.
We had to go and
add annotations to our video class to
explain how to map it into the database.
We've done the same thing with
that half DynamoDB annotations.
We can now go and
take a look at the video repository.
And one of the nice things that
we'll see in this particular case,
is we don't have to make any
changes to our video repository.
It's still extending the cred
repository that we extended before.
And just like with Mongo DB, we're not
making any changes to the underlying
find methods, we still can support
the custom queries, like find by name.
All of these things are still working just
like they were before, so, we're, we're
getting this benefit of having spring data
as an abstraction layer between our app.
And our custom code and all the different
databases that needs spring data that we
might want to go and use.
So just by plugging in
the right annotations,
we can swap out the database underneath
because of this nice abstraction layer.
And with some simple annotations
with our objects we can change.
Repository implementation creators, so
just like with the other examples where we
used spring data, we're not actually
creating the implementation of
the repository ourselves, we're just
providing the interface for it that we
want to be created based on the underlying
database that we're connecting to.
So, this is another example where this
abstraction spring data separates us with
just a little bit of annotation
changes we can get to a new database.
And there will be cases where
it's helpful to know and
look at a particular database's format and
how it does things like the hash and
range keys in DynamoDB or the ability
to provision through put in DynamoDB.
Or a more understanding more about
Mongo's documented oriented data store.
But we can still very quickly move between
these databases, and then figure out
what other things that we need to know
about that particular database, and
will they affect our application at all.
And in many cases they won't, and
we won't have to worry about them,
we just can swap out underneath
Spring Data if we focus on key value is
a sort of abstraction that we're using