[MUSIC]
A lot of times, we also want to
optimize for writes, as well as reads.
So, let's say that we have that
same page that we're going to
display all of the comments.
And we decide that at the top of
the page we want to in one place display
the total number of comments or
reviews or whatever it is.
At the top of the page so that the person
knows without even having to go scroll
through the list how many comments have
been, put in on that particular product.
Now one way that we could
do this is we could have a,
let's say this is a product page,
we're going to say number of
comments, per product.
Now this would be really good from
a read perspective because we
can just look up the particular product
and we'll get the number of comments.
Now you can imagine though if this is
a really hot product and you have hundreds
of people who are simultaneously
commenting on this particular product,
what that means is is that
we have simultaneous writes
to this particular object.
So what's going to happen is,
is that writing is going to become
a bottleneck because each of
the writers is going to have to lock this
particular object, is going to update it.
And then release that lock before the next
writer can get in and, and update it.
So, this becomes a bottleneck for writing.
This is not ideal if we are going
to have heavy write contention.
Now one way we could deal with this is,
we could go back to the model where we
have multiple, product entity,
entries or entities.
And then we have all these different
products and we can simply, you know,
query and count how many there are.
But obviously,
that's not as fast as we'd like it to be.
Another interesting way that we can
do this, so we can start with here.
We could also try something like this.
Another way that we can do it,
is we would like,
lets say to increase the number of, of
writes that can go through simultaneously.
So we'd like to allow to parallel writes.
Is rather than having this,
we can move to a model where we
have, number of comments, product,
and we'll call this shard one.
I'll say what a shard is in a minute.
And then, we have number,
comments, product,
shard N, and the idea is, is that,
we create multiple copies of this
number of comments per product.
And then when we want to write an updated
value what we do is we come in here and
we randomly choose, one of the particular
entities that's in here, or
we have some selection scheme,
but we can just randomly choose.
And if we know, for example,
that there are N different shards, and
basically what a shard in this case is
is we're going to take the counter, and
we're going to split it
up into multiple counts.
So, if we want to split this counter into
ten different shards, what we would do.
As we would create ten different entities
that are entires that count that
have a partial count inside of them.
And at any point in time,
if we want to go and
get the true count then we query and
count up to, N entries.
So where is this one, over here,
we're going to query and
count all entries, of the products.
Alright this should actually be
comment of the product comment.
Rather than going and querying all cont,
counts, of the product comments,
over here, all we have to do is go and
query up to n entries of comment products.
I mean, comments for produc,
for a particular product.
And we get back all of these different
shards, we basically query for
all of them, and
then we sum up their values.
So, rather than having
just a single value,
we will get all of these and
add them together.
Basically, we will sum
values, to get the count.
So, when a, a comment is added,
basically what will happen is,
if we add a new comment here,
when we go to write to the database we
will randomly select one of the shards.
That we are going to update the count for.
We'll pick that shard,
we will increment its count,
and then save it back in the database.
If another writer comes in,
they at ex, exactly the same time,
and they randomly choose,
hopefully they will get a different shard.
So, we can control the contention that
we have on our different shards by,
deciding how many
different shards we have.
And we can also balance how
much effort it is to go and
read the count, by determining how much,
how many shards we have.
The more shards we have,
the more expensive it is
to read the count back out.
But, the more shards we have
the greater the greater number of
writers that can come in and
write concurrently to the count.
So, we can balance and
basically trade off reads and
writes by determining how many times we
duplicate and have partial counts in here.
So, we are essentially duplicating data
we're basically taking an object breaking
it apart, in this case taking a count,
breaking it apart into multiple entries.
And then allowing writers to select
any of the entries to update and
then when we go and
actually get the true value, we're getting
all of the entries and summing them.
But, whereas over here when we had
individual product comment entries and
we were counting all of them,
we had just a,
our work was proportional to
the number of product comment entries.
Over here, our work to sum is proportional
to the number of shards we create.
So we can flexibly balance out
the number of shards that we have.
Now how does this work in
terms of randomly choosing?
Well, when we go to get the key,
let's say that product ID is
the first part of the key.
The second part of the key can be a number
between zero and the number of shards.
So if you want to randomly select a
particular entity, you put in the product
ideas the first part of the key, and then
you randomly choose a number between zero
and the number of shards, and you provide
it as a second point part of the key.
And then you simply grab that object,
update it, and save it.
And then if you want all of the product
entities, and you want to sum them up,
you simply go and get all of the entities
that have a particular product ID, and
then the number of shards you get
product ID one, product ID two.
And depending on your database,
it may even support Some type of
prefixed based query across the keys.
Where you can ask for all of the keys
that have a particular prefix.