One of
the first things you
need to do when you're going to
optimize your MySQL database and
your interactions with it, is to think
about do what to optimize a particular.
Piece of data, and the access
to that data, for read vs write.
And this is a really, a fundamental
question that you need to ask,
because it vastly changes how you want
to store and interact with that data.
So, lets take an example, and
we'll relate it back to our original
Java Map example to help understand why.
Knowing if you're going to go for reads
versus writes is critically important.
So let's say that we have a form and
we would like users to be able to post
comments, let's say on our videos.
So, users can go and
they can post a comment.
And on the page we would
like to be able to display,
the number of comments,
that have been posted by each user.
So, somewhere on the display if
the user's comment is there,
we might have user foo and we might have
some number of comments that they've.
Posted across all the forums,
let's say just for sim, simplicity.
So, one of the things we need to be
able to do, is we need to be able to
keep track of this count, of the number
of comments that they posted.
So, there's kind of two
approaches we can do.
One approach is,
we can have a table where.
Every time the orig, sum structure where
every time the user posted a comment,
it would be entered as a center
entity in this particular store.
So I'm using this entity.
Name very specifically here, because
we're going to go and create a Java class
to represent a comment, and we're going to
annotate with something like add entity,
and each time they create a new comment,
we're going to create a new instance of
that object, and we're going to store
it in the, list of comment objects.
So, we've got.
These comment entities are objects,
stored objects, that represent each
time the user goes and posts a comment.
And so
there might be some number of these.
Now, the way that we're going to
generate the number of comments is,
each time we load this page,
a request will go to this table.
An we will search, for all comments that,
where the users of particular users.
So find all comments with particular user.
And count them.
So, as you can see, this is an operation
that is very cheap from write perspective.
And very expensive from
a read perspective.
So if I want to write and add a comment.
Then, what I have to do, is just,
create a new instance of a common object.
And add it.
And store it so it's persistent.
But there's no, locking or any other
things that I have to worry about because,
it will never be the case
that multiple writers.
Hopefully are writing to the same
comment at the same time.
If the user is on the page
entering a comment and
hitting save, they're going to be the only
one, theoretically, creating that comment.
They're hopefully going to
be on one page at a time.
But they're creating one comment.
And there's only one person logged in and
even if there were, they had multiple
browser tabs open or for some reason.
Their, their child is commenting,
as well, simultaneously.
None of those comments conflict with
each other because they're all, each,
you know, atomic entities that
would be edited separately.
So each time they click Add,
it's adding a new entity in here.
So comic creation,
the write, is really cheap because
there's no locking of the database.
No worries that, that multiple people
would write to the same person and
comment at the same time.
However, our reads are really expensive.
If we think back to that job of map
example, where when we wanted to know
which, people have bought a particular
item, we had to go an search through and
scan through all of the data and
all of the values.
Looking for ones that match
our particular cr, criteria.
In this case we're doing
something similar.
When we want to know the count for
particular, user,
what we have to do is count all
their comment entity objects and
then create the sum of that and
then return it.
So its an expensive read operation so,
read.
Is slow, write,
is going to be fast in this case.
Or at least they're optimized to
make reads slower and writes faster.
Now if we really cared about was
getting the number of comments quickly,
what we could do instead we could have.
Another table, and, and we have could
have entities in this, which it were,
comment count.
Now, in this case, and
we'll just go ahead and make this by user.
So if you want to know.
The number of comments that
a particular user has left.
We're going to do something equivalent
to what we did with the maps in Java.
That is, we're going to create a new map,
or a new table, or
whatever you want to think of it as, and
the entities in here are these comment
count objects that we are persisting.
And, every time you want to get the
comment count, all you have to do is put,
pi, push in the, the user as the key,
and the comment count pops out.
So it's a very simple key based lookup to
get a particular user's, comment count.
But, the difference is, that every
time that we go and add a comment now.
We're going to also have to go and
update the comment count.
So read, or so writes are getting
more expensive, because now if
we add a new comment object, we also have
to go here and update the comment count.
And we might want to do this in
a transaction, so that it's atomic, and
you can't add an object here and then not
have it update here, or update here and
not work over here.
So we might have some transaction issues.
We also might have the case where if now,
if this users child is,
is creating comments at the same time
we can't just assume that we don't
have to worry about locking.
We have to lock this object particularly
if there's any situation where
the user could be multi,
logged in multiple times.
Somebody else is using as a count.
Now, maybe that doesn't make sense,
but you could think of scenarios where
you could have multiple
writers to the same object.
In this case, we have multiple
potential writers to the comment count.
So if the user posts multiple comments in
a very short order from multiple tabs or
something else in their browser.
They will all simultaneously be trying
to create common objects here, and
then simultaneously trying to
be write to the common account.
So we'll have to do some locking on,
this particular account,
to make sure that we don't end
up with inconsistent data.
Also we'll probably want to have some type
of transaction to make sure you can't add
a comment and not update the account.
Or vice versa.
So, in this style over here, the writes
are slow, and the reads are fast.
So, this is a thing you're
going to see over and
over when you're designing for NoSQL.
And trying to figure out,
how do I design my entities to fetch them?
Well, we can go and
we can duplicate some of the data.
We're suddenly having another
representation of the comment count, and
we can just make this a Java class called
comment count, there's a key for users,
but the downside is that suddenly we are,
sort of, making our writes more expensive.
However we don't have to have this thing
we can just have a list of comment
objects, that are essentially being added
each time we persist a comment object
their being added to the table or whatever
it is that you're storing these things in.
But when you need another comment,
count you have to go and actually
scan through all the data like we were
with the map, and get that count back.
So, before you begin doing anything, and
you want to look at a particular, query,
you need to understand,
how often am I going to be writing?
How often am I going to be reading?
Is it more important
that my writes be fast or
more important that my reads be fast?
And that's what you're going to need
to know in order to begin to make
reasoned decisions about how you
should structure your classes that
are annotated with entity and
store, or how you're, structuring
your classes that are annotated
with whatever you're going to use to math
them into the underlying NoSQL data store.
If you're going to be writing a whole lot.
People are going to be writing lots
of comments and you want to make
comment writing really fast, then you'll
probably go for something like this.
If, however, every time that you load this
page there's thousands of comments, and
getting the number of comments for,
for each user is incredibly slow and
is the bottleneck, then you're going to
want to do something like this.
And so until you know, what is the, the,
what is it you're trying to optimize for?
Are you trying to optimize for writes or
are you trying to optimize for reads?
You really can't go forward with figuring
out how to structure your data to make it
easy to access.