[MUSIC]
We've talked about NoSQL databases,
primarily from the point of
view that they're simple key value stores,
where we have a key and
we have a value, and the database doesn't
really care much about the value.
Well, let's talk a little bit about
a different type of database that's
a document oriented database.
So, when we have documents,
we can have a database like MongoDB,
which we're going to be talking about,
that can view a, a value that's
stored in it as a structured document
that has different properties or fields.
So, MongoDB is a document
orientated database, and
we can use it in Spring, just like we have
other databases that we've connected to.
The In-memory databases that we've
been using for the examples.
But, we can simply,
doing a little bit of work,
we can swap out that in-memory database.
And use a much more powerful
data store like Mongo.
Now, to do this, it's helpful to
understand a few of the concepts.
One of the concepts is that natively
internally Mongo views documents
as JSON objects or BSON as is what it
uses internally or calls its documents.
But you can think of them as essentially
JSON objects that are being stored.
So when you go and
you put in a key, the value for
this key is going to be JSON that's
being stored in the database.
So just like you had before
where you could go and
look up and object by a key, you can
still do that, except that you have,
know that what you're looking up is a
document that has a JSON like structures.
They call their BSON, but
it's essentially a JSON like structure.
Now, this is really nice because
we're very familiar and, and
understand how JSON objects
work after going through all of
the different spring examples
that we've been working with.
So now we can take the concepts of how
we've been marshalling objects in JSON,
and we can move that into our database as
well, and begin thinking about how we go
and do searches on the database and store
things in terms of JSON like objects.
Now, it may seem like it's going to
take a lot of work to get from the,
the video service, and the other
applications that we've been building so
far, to something that's
connected to MongoDB.
But what we can see is that
the distractions that we have,
where normally we have our
application that we produce, and
then we're sitting on top of Spring data.
And our repositories,
so we might have one or
more repository interfaces here
that we're using from spring data.
That spring data can isolate us from a lot
of the changes of the underlying database.
So if we've been using this
HSQLDV that maybe in memory,
we can suddenly swap to Mongo and
spring data can isolate us from a lot
of those changes to our application.
You would think you would have to
make in order to make that switch.
And the other part of this that's
helping us to do that separation is
this idea of you know,
object relational mapping to a database or
mapping our objects into a database.
Because you can think about it, we,
we're, we've gotten really good at using
Jackson to map our objects into JSON.
We've gotten really good
at using spring data, and
the repositories, and JPA to map our
objects into database rows and columns.
But with Mongo,
we can simply switch over and
begin having spring data map our objects
into the documents that Mongo cares about.
Now, one thing that I should also mention,
before we get too much farther along here,
is that, because Mongo is
a document orientated database,
it doesn't have this concept of a strict
schema that has to be adhered to.
So, the values, as long as they fit the,
the sort of JSON, or
VSON model,
that Mongo's using underneath the hood.
They can have any number of properties and
be flexible.
So they still fit this noSQL model,
gret flexibility in what we're storing,
being able to change things over time.
So, what we're going to do now is let's
take a look at the actual code and
the changes that we need to make to
the video service that was built on top of
spring data rest.
And see what we get and
how we get to Mongo DB.
So, the first thing we're going to do,
is we're going to open up the application
class that we've seen in all of
these examples.
And it looks very similar
to what we've seen before.
We still have a repository
rest in VC configuration.
So we know that we're going to be using
Spring Data Resp to serve data out of
the database, and
to give it a restful API.
We still have our original date
video service API for the client.
That allows the client to find
particular videos by name or duration.
Go and list the different videos
that are in the repository.
And then if we go and
look at our repository, we're going to
begin to see something slightly different.
So if you'll remember before,
when we were using JPA,
we were extending a CRUD repository.
Now, the one of the main changes that
we're going to have to make in order to
switch over to Mongo.
Is we're going to have
to tell Spring to begin
using a Mongo repository
instead of a CRUD repository.
Now, we're having to change our code,
but the nice thing about this is,
that all of the users of
the interface from a,
from a, a used user inner you know,
approach to using that interface,
there's no real difference in
what we're going to be changing.
So we're not changing individual methods
or return values on this interface,
all we're doing is changing the interface
that this interface extends.
So, the classes that
depend on this interface
wouldn't be impacted by our change of
switching from one database to Mongo.
So this is one of the nice things
that we're getting from Spring Data,
is that this abstraction layer is helping
to separate us from the details of
the individual database and
allow us to decide.
We, we know longer want to target
this database we want to target this
database without breaking all of the users
of that particular repository interface.
So, as we'll see, we still have all of
the same things that we had before.
We still have the annotations and
the same parameters for
Spring Data Res, we're still
passing parameters the same way.
And we're still inheriting the normal
find methods and delete methods and
other things from the parent
repository that we're extending.
Now the other change we have
to make is we have to go and
update our video object to no
longer use the JPA annotation, but
instead to include the annotations for
Spring Data Mongo.
And in, in this case it's
actually quite simple to do this,
because all we have to do is to
have one annotation in order to
get our videos stored in Mongo DB and
that's to add an add ID annotation.
When specifies the member variable
that we want to be the key when we're
storing these objects in the database.
So with very little change,
all we're doing is taking changing
the annotations in our video objects, and
then if we go and look at the repository,
we're changing what we're extending.
But all of this is working within the same
framework that we've gotten used to
with Spring Data and Spring Data Res.
We're just slightly changing
how we're annotating and how
we're extending this interface, but we're
still not implementing the interface,
trying to figure out how we go about,
in change and use queries for MongoDB.
From the, the programmatic point of view
of storing objects and retrieving objects,
we're still doing all of the same things
that we did before with spring data, and
we're still exposing all of these
objects via spring data reps.
So, this is the beautiful thing again.
By using spring and
spring data, we're, separating us from
the details of these underlying databases.
And how we query them, and, and
deal with the different variations
in their representations.
But, we also gain all
of these benefits of,
one person is going to go, an,
an expert presumably, is going to go and
create the different mappings
down to these databases.
We also gain from their domain
knowledge of knowing the right way to
go from objects to
the particular database.
So we can reuse all of this, this great
knowledge from the domain experts to know
how to do this translation layer
down to each individual database.
So, this is the complete application for
Spring MongoDB.
If you want to go through and
add some extra customization,
you don't have to have this annotation but
we have the at enable Mongo Repositories.
And if you wanted to go and configure some
of the ways that Mongo DB gets setup,
you can add this to
your application class.
And then again setting it up.
One of the other small changes that we
have to make is in our build.gradal file.
We have to go and add the dependency.
For the MongoDB database driver and other
dependencies that are needed by Spring.
And then the final thing that's
helpful to people is this example is
going to assume that you're
running the database locally.
But if you decided that you wanted to
go and connect to a remote database.
There is an applications.properties file
underneath source main resources, and
if we go and look at that file,
we see that we have the ability to change
the database host where this MongoDB
database lives, as well as the port.
Now, or we could go and specify
the connection URI with user name and
password, or a specific database
that we wanted to connect to.
So, what we've seen from this is,
is that spring data, and
spring data rest gave us this
great abstraction that protects us
from complicated changes when we
decide to switch between databases.
Now there may be circumstances
where things are hard to map into
another database, and it may not
fully protect us to those things.
But in most cases we can simply
switch to the appropriate subset of
spring data that we want to use for
the particular database that we want.
And spring data can figure
out the right way to map
our objects into that new database.
So in this case, by simply adding the at
id annotation to our video and changing
the, the, the annotations describing
how we want to persist that object.
And by changing,
slightly our repository interface to
extend a different interface
rather than crud repository.
Suddenly we're able to
take our objects and
automatically map them into
the documents that Mongo DB stores.