[MUSIC]
NoSQL databases are a hot
topic in cloud computing.
So what exactly are NoSQL databases,
and how do we change the way
that we interact with our data if
we are using a NoSQL database?
Well, generalizing about exactly what
a NoSQL database is, is a little bit hard.
But at the most fundamental level,
one approach to
thinking about many new SQL databases,
is to think of them as giant hash table.
And, and second we'll give an example
of how this can be used to
help understand what is going to be and
efficient or, or less efficient design,
when interacting with a NoSQL database.
At the basic level NoSQL databases
do what they say in their title,
they don't give you full SQL like your
used to with a relational data base.
So you can't necessarily go and
do table joins easily or
other things that you would get with SQL.
Now, if you don't know what SQL is,
if you're not familiar with relational
databases, don't worry about it too much.
You'll still be able to get
an understanding of what the key
principles are behind NoSQL databases and
how to work with them and
design and optimize for them.
There are a variety of
styles of NoSQL databases.
So, one of the common styles
is a key value store.
And this is really the most most,
the closest thing to a pure hashmap.
So you have keys, and you can go and
look up values associated with them.
And these types of
databases often give you
really high performance through this
very simple but powerful mechanism.
Another type or style of databases is ones
that look like Google's Big Table, and
these provide some greater
capabilities in terms of the query and
structure and layout of the database.
Isn't there a number of open
source alternatives that
provide capabilities very
similar to Big Table.
Another type,
is document-oriented, databases.
So these provide much
greater structure and
flexibility in the values
that are being stored, and
the schemas of the particular values
that are being stored in the database.
And some of them even store pure JSON
inside the values, so you can go and
think of the values as JSON, or, or
object data that's very flexible.
And then the final type,
which we are not going to talk about
much is a graph database that's optimized
for doing traversals on a graph.
Like finding the shortest path or
finding nodes in the graph that
have a specific relationship.
So, these are a variety of
styles of NoSQL databases.
What we're going to focus primarily,
initially on databases that have
this style and this style, and
then we'll talk a little bit about Mongo
DB, which is a document oriented database
that we will understand how
to operate with that as well.
To help get an intuitive understanding of
how NoSQL databases work we're going to
generalize a little bit and pretend NoSQL
databases all look like Java hashtables.
And then we'll use that to help us
understand how we can improve our
structuring and interactions with
the databases, if we have this mentality.
So let's assume that our
database is a big hashmap.
And rather than parametrize this thing,
I’m going to say were going
to store purchases, by user.
By user.
Then we can go and
construct a particular hash map, or
some other map structure to store this.
So what we'd like to do, is the keys will
be the user, or the ID of the user and
the value will be a list of
the purchases that that user has made.
So if we wanted to go and
run a query to find the purchases,
we could say something like list
purchase P equals purchases by user.get.
And we pass in some particular user.
Now what happens if we want to go and
search for
the list off all users that
have bought a particular item.
Well suddenly, this query gets a lot
more challenging in this map world.
So suddenly, we have to go and
iterate through all of the values
to try to find a value that
matches what we're looking for.
So in this case, we might have to
do something like for, list purchase,
PN purchases, by user.values.
So now we're going to iterate
over every single value, and
then we're going to say for, and
we're going to iterate over the purchases.
We'll call this PS, P and PS.
And then we're going to search for
purchases that match the particular,
one that we're looking for.
And if we find them,
then we're going to try to get
the associated key, of the the user.
And in, in this case this
actually would be hard to do.
That we, we're not iterating over
the keys at the same times, so
it's going to be kind of challenging.
Now there are ways we could do it.
We could iterate over the keys,
get the purchases for
each user, then search the purchases.
Which might be the better way to do it.
But, the challenge is, as you can see
either way, it requires a lot more work.
If we have to go and search for a
particular user that meets a criteria, so
suddenly we need to know which
keys have a specific criteria for
their value, it becomes harder to go and
get this data out.
Whereas if we just want to know,
what purchases does a user make,
this map is really fast.
But the moment that we want to know which
users meet a particular criteria we have
to go into a lot of work.
And, in this case we're not
even doing the work correctly.
We'd have to go and iterate through
the keys, get the list of purchases for
each key.
Oh, for each purch,
purchase we'd have to iterate over it.
We'd have to check if it met some criteria
that we were looking for, and then if
it did we'd have to store the key in
another list and then finally return it.
And that's a whole lot more work than
a simple map lookup on a hash table,
where we would go and just provide the key
and immediately get all the values back.
So how can we get around this problem?
Well in relational databases normally
we're trying to do something that's called
normalization, that is we don't want to
have duplicate data in our data base.
We want to have the representation
of some data item only exist once
in the database we don't want to have
duplicates of that data over and over.
But in this case,
we can do something to vastly improve
the rate at which we can query things.
And that is, if we want to be able to
query by particular purchases too,
if we want to be able to find all of
the users that made a particular purchase,
we can do some renormalization.
That is, we can make,
do some duplication to make this faster.
So we can have a second map, and
we can make this users by purchase.
And we would go and construct this map and
populate it in some way.
And then if we want to know
which users have, created, or
have purchased a particular item.
We could go and List, you know, User, and
we could call this buyers, equals users,
by purchase.get.
And we could pass in some particular
purchase that we were looking for.
And that would instantly give
us all the users that had
bought that particular item.
And we still have the ability
to go in the other direction.
If we wanted to say, list,
purchases, they bought.
We can still do this and say,
purchases by user, get user.
So in this case,
we can do either query every efficiently.
If we want to know all the people that
bought some particular purchase or item,
which we're going to call a purchase,
we can simply provide that key and
we'll get back all of,
the list of those users.
If we want to know all the purchases for a
particular user, we can provide that key.
And so, by duplicating the data,
we've got the purchases in here and
then, as values, and then we've got
the purchases over here as keys.
And similar, we've got the users over here
as keys, and then down here as values.
So sense, in a sense,
we're duplicating the data.
In order to make our query faster, we're
being able to look things up easier rather
than having to go and scan through
all of the values and look for them.
But in the process,
we're duplicating this data and
so we're going to have to
do a little bit more work.
When we, whenever we go and update.
The part, purchases for a particular user.
So a user buys something.
We're now going to have to
update it in two places.
So the downside is,
is that our data isn't normalized anymore.
We're now having duplications, so
when we go and try to update, we have
to update it in more than one place.
And if we want to go and
do some type of restructuring of our
database, we're going to have to and
update multiple places and
relationships between that data.
But, the positive side is, is that we
can get the queries really quickly.
So, if you think, sort of,
from this mentality,
this gives you a bit of an intuitive
sense of how NoSQL databases work.
Is, on some level,
they operate like hash tables.
Even though many of them give
you additional features and
capabilities, this is one of the primitive
ways that one can conceptualize how to
improve the performance of the.