[MUSIC]
The Java technology that's used to handle
incoming requests on a server, is
typically Servlets.
So what Servlets do, is when a browser,
where
in our case a mobile device, sends an HTTP
request.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
This request gets routed to what's called
a Web Application Container.
So this is often just called a Web
Container,
and inside of the web container, there are
one or more Servlets
that handle and process the HTTP requests
that are being sent to it.
So the request will reach the web
container and then be routed to one of
many individual Servlets typically, that
are running inside of that web container.
Now, what a Servlet is, is it's just a
Java object, that
has special methods for handling incoming
HTTP requests.
And the key methods that a servlet has,
are doGet,
doPost, and you can probably see a pattern
here.
You have do methods for the various
request
methods, that are part of the HTTP
specification.
So this Servelet is nothing more than a
Java object,
that inherits from Servlet and has
implementations of the various request
handling methods, that correspond to the
various HTTP request method.
So if somebody sends a Get request for
some resource
like Foo, it's going to pick out a
Servlet, it's going to route
that request to the Servlets doGet method
and then that doGet
method gets access to all of the different
pieces of the request.
Namely, the request line where we can look
at for
example, the resource that was requested,
it gets access to the
Headers and it gets access to the request
body, so
they can go and do any processing
associated with that request.
So, Servlets are the underline and most
commonly
used technology in Java, for handling the
incoming request.
Now, one of the key questions is, if we
have multiple Servlets here, how do we
decide which Servlet should handle a
particular HTTP request?
Well, inside of most web containers,
there's
what we call basically a routing function,
or
some router which decides based on the
request
that's coming in, which Servlet should
handle it.
And in Java, the way that Servlet handling
and routing is specified, is through a
web.xml file.
And this is a specialized file that tells
the web container when a particular
request comes in, so let's say we get a
new request here for slash-bar
and it's a post to bar, it looks in the
web.xml file, finds the Servlet
that it should go to, and then routes the
request to the appropriate Servelet,
based on what's specified in that web.xml
file.
So this is essentially the routing of
requests.
This is where routing is specified as in
web.xml.
The web container handles the life cycle,
and uses this routing table to
decide which Servlet should receive
requests,
and then the individual Servlet's process
request.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, this is the overview of how the
Servlet system in, in Java works, to
handle requests.