[MUSIC]
What we've seen by our attempt to map the
video service onto HTTP, is
that a protocol like HTTP can have other
protocols layered on top of it.
In our case, we're layering a protocol for
interacting with our
video service, on top of the HTTP
protocol, and this is one
of the important principles to understand
with, you know, network communication
product
protocols, is that you can layer them on
top of each other.
So, often you'll have a protocol like
HTTP.
And it may be layered on top of something
else like
TCP/IP which again may be layered on a
series of other things.
And then above HTTP may be other protocols
that we
create like the protocol for interacting
with our video service.
So we're specifying rules for interaction
and exchange of messages and
formatting of those messages, and where
layering them on top of HTTP.
And similarly, if we defined a nice
interface, other
protocols could even be layered on top of
our protocol.
So it's important to understand that HTTP,
although it is what we're
primarily targeting, is just a protocol
layer among many in the application.
And we have to understand the underlying
protocol
layers that are involved when we're
building our application.
But particularly, we want to understand
what the
different options are for building on top
of HTTP.
As we've seen, there are a lot of design
choices
that we're making about how we use the
interface and
constructs provided by HTTP to encode the
data about our
videos and send them to the service that
we're talking to.
Similarly, there's all kinds of design
decisions such
as how we design the URLs, how would
we encode parameters, do we use it in a, a
query parameter or a request body?
Do we send request bodies that are
multi-part encoded or form URL encoded?
And there's all of these decisions that we
have to make in the design of our
application.
And we do them by building layers of
protocols in.
Now an important, thing to know, of some
of the common
names for protocols that are built on top
of HTTP, or some of the common
design methodologies, that are built on
top of HTTP, that describe,
how you take messages or services and
describe them using HTTP-based
interactions.
One that you may have heard of that gets
built on top of HTTP is web services.
And as anything that becomes very popular
at some point.
And is very technical.
At some point, it gets taken and
it's original true definition becomes
watered down.
So originally web services had a very
specific definition.
It meant that we were doing things like,
describing our
services with things like WSDL or Web
Services Definition Language.
Or sending messages that were based on
SOAP, or simple object access protocol.
But later on, what's happened over time is
as sales and marketing
and other folks start talking about web
services which is inherently technical.
They start talking about it in a more
watered-down fashion.
Web services, over time evolved from
meaning that you were using WSDL and
SOAP to just meaning that you had a
service that was accessible over HTTP.
Similarly, the really popular thing that
you hear these days is about REST.
And a REST API is a representational state
transfer API.
And this was something that was laid out
by Ray, Roy Fielding in his di, PhD
dissertation,
and it's a very specific set of rules for
building a protocol and interface on top
of HTTP.
Most, of the, the people that you say that
have a REST API aren't actually doing
what's described in full in the REST
vision
that Roy Fielding laid out in his
dissertation.
What they're doing is building a service
that can
be interacted with over HTTP and has
REST-like properties potentially.
So it maybe doing some of the things that
REST describes but
not all of them or not doing any of them
at all.
Everybody has started taking things that
were inherently technical, web services
or REST and they start describing them in
a very loose manner.
So when you hear web services, the true
definition is
something like WSDL and SOAP and other
things being used.
The true definition of REST is something
very specific laid
out in a PhD dissertation, but they get
used very loosely.
So someone says to you, do you have a REST
API?
You need to figure out do they mean, do
you have the watered down definition of
REST API, which means do you have some
service that you can talk to over HTTP.
Or do they really, specifically mean do
you follow all of
the rules of REST, all of the design
principles of REST?
And the answer is probably no.
That's not what they mean.
But it's important to understand that web
services
and REST are basically methodologies for
building on top
of HTTP, that describe very specific
formats and principles
that you use when you're building things
on HTTP.
But, what we're going to focus on, and we
will be building
things that are REST like, but are not
true REST necessarily.
Well, some of the things will be true
REST.
They're provided by the Spring framework
that we're going to talk about.
But most of the things we're going to be
talking
about really fall into, it is a service
that is.
I, you know, accessible via HTTP, and it
may have REST-like properties or it may
have web
service-like properties, depending on how
you design it,
but this is the core of where things sit.
This is where cloud services really come
into play, is
we're building in some object which can
live in the
cloud or some service which can live in
the cloud
and can receive information and be
interacted with over HTTP.
And depending on the design of that
service, those interactions may
follow a REST model, or they may follow a
web service model.
And it just depends on how they're
actually implemented.