[MUSIC]
Whenever you're building a server side
code
base that's going to receive data from a
client, like we are in these examples
where
we're receiving data over HTTP from a
client.
And then we're going to process and do
something with that data,
something that we have to be very
concerned about are injection attacks.
And so, to summon up what this is, is when
the client sends us some
data, that because of the way that the
client sends that data to us or formats
it or some other aspect of the data or the
request, we end up rather than
interpreting that data as data we end up
interpreting it as a command and executing
something.
We have to be very careful of these things
because we don't want the client to be
able to
manipulate our execution paths and our
logic on the
server, or on other clients that are
accessing our website.
So it's very important that we always, be
cognizant of the potential
for the client to send us some data that
causes to take some command or
action that we didn't want to take or that
we don't thinks is secure.
So, let me give you an example using the
echo servlet that we've seen in our coded
samples.
So, with the echo servlet a client
can send a request to
the server with a message that should be
occur, and
the server then returns to the client a
message
back which is the content of the webpage
so its going to send echo
plus the message.
Now, in our example that we were using, we
were sending this echo plus message back
as plain text.
So whenever the client gets back, it's
just going to hopefully
look at the content type header and
interpret it as plain text.
But let's assume that we were actually
setting the
content type to HTML, so that when the
client
got this echo plus message back, we could
have
HTML in it, and the client would display
it.
So you can imagine we might go and add
something like a HTML tag, and then we
might add
a body tag, in front of our content we're
sending back, and there might be a closing
body tag.
And a closing HTML tag, so now whenever
we, the client
send us a message they could provide some
HTML formatting on the message
that they sent to us and when I got echo
it back
they could make it bold or different
colors whatever they wanted to do.
Now the, the challenge with this is what
if they make this message, some JavaScript
code.
So suddenly, the client is going to send
us, some
JavaScript code, which we are going to
echo back to them.
Well the challenge is now, when we echo
this HTML page back to them, It's going to
have java script code in it, which will be
executed by the client when it gets it
back.
Now you may say, well then, why, why do
we care about this If the client's sending
it to
us, why should we care about it executing
it because
it sent it to us so it must be okay?
Well, the challenge is, is think about in
this case, If we had a second website.
So, we have another website and the client
then goes and visits this website, and
part of what the
website returns is a URL to this server so
a link,
to the echo service.
If that link encodes some java script in
the message,
then this website can trick the client
into clicking on this
link, which when they visit it will cause
JavaScript to
be injected into their browser that goes
and does something malicious.
So for example, if our server was sending
private cookies or other data
back to the client or maybe our, the bank
balance was coming back.
It wasn't just a simple page, web page but
it was actually something to show them
their account balance.
The script that they injected into the
client,
would have access to all of that data when
it came back to the client and that script
could tell the client to go ahead and
for the data secretly to the attacking
website,
so this is just one example of where the
facts that we're taking in data from the
client can lead to some type of injection
attack.
We want to be very careful, that whatever
data we take
from the client, that we treat it very,
very carefully.
Another one of the top types of injection
attacks, that we'll
talk about later in the course, is called
a SQL injection attack.
Where, because of the data that the client
provides, the server
goes off and accesses or manipulates the
database in an inappropriate way.
So, the moral of this story is, whenever
you are taking in
data from the client, you must consider
this data to be highly untrusted.
Even if you were expecting only your
mobile client to be
sending the HB request to the server, it
doesn't mean that
some other Entity could just directly,
create HTTP requests outside of
your client and send them to the server to
do something.
So, you always, always, always must be
very, very careful and don't trust client
data.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
You always must validate it and segregate
it, and make
sure that it can't manipulate your server
in some way.
So what are things that you should be
careful of?
Anytime a client is going to be sending
you HTML, or some type of code
that could potentially be interpreted as
commands or logic.
Be very, very careful of that, because
that's a direct case
where, if you're going to interpret what
they send you as
logic, then there's the potential that
what they send you, could
manipulate the logic on your server to do
something very bad.
If you're going, they're going to send
something to you that
you're going to temporarily store and then
send back to other clients.
But what you send back is going to be
interpreted
as logic in some way or executed in some
way.
Be very, very careful of that, because
that's another case where they could
inject some type of command data, that
later gets served up to your visitors
or store other clients of your website and
causes attacks to be generated on them.
So, always take client data and validate
it
very, very carefully, If there's the
potential that it
could be executed, you must try to
sanitize
that data and strip out anything bad in
it.
And the best approach is to only allow
very certain things in.
Rather than trying to go and manipulate
the data after the
fact, and remove bad things, or try to
catch just bad things.
It's very, very difficult to take data in
from a
client that's later going to be executed
as logical commands in
some way, and do that securely It's a
very, very
challenging thing to do, be very careful
whenever you do it.
Any data that you're taking from the
client, if you're expecting
it to be of a certain type, validate that
it's that type.
If you're expecting it not to be empty,
validate that it's not empty.
Always you know, treat client data as an
attack on your system.
Validate it, and then prove that it's not
an
attack before you do something with it
that is sensitive.
So, the moral of the story is anything
that comes into a servlet, anything that
comes into the controllers, the spring
controllers
that we'll talk about later in this
course.
Any of that type of data that comes in,
you
must be incredibly careful with what you
do with it,
and ensure that doesn't lead to an attack
on you,
and your server or the clients that are
visiting your server.