[MUSIC]
Our simple servlet has all the logic that
we need to handle get and post requests.
But the one piece that we haven't talked
about
is, how do we route requests to this
servlet?
So how does the web application container
that our servlet is running in
know when should it invoke our servlet and
which operations it should handle?
So, if we think about this, a request gets
sent with a particular path.
And then the servlet container
needs to know, depending on the path, when
should the individual servlets, should
actually handle the request?
So we need to set up a routing
relationship so that we
know, based on the path, which server,
servlet should it be routed to.
That's what this web.xml file provides.
We're going to talk about web.xml files
first because they're the traditional way
of specifying these routing relationships
to decide
which paths get handled by which servlet.
But, as we'll talk about later, there's a
newer method for doing this that's
based on Java-based configuration, where
you can
still do all of these configuration
parameterizations of
your application, but you have type safety
of Java and so it's easier to make
sure you do things correctly because you
can make a mistake in a web.xml file.
So here's a simple web.xml file for our
video
service that we created and the servlet
for it.
So we see that there's a web-app
declaration saying that this is a web
application.
And what we're doing is we're describing
in this XML file the parts of our
code that the servlet container or the
web [INAUDIBLE] application container
needs to know about.
So when it loads our code, it needs to
know what are the servlets
that it should care about and what path
should it route to which servlets.
So that's what this web.xml file tells it,
is information about our code
and how to load it and how do you map
requests into that code.
So in this case, all we have is a
simple servlet and a single mapping for
that servlet.
So the servlet is declared here and we see
the
servlet's got a name and then we've got a
class.
So, this tells the servlet, go and load
this particular class that I wrote, which,
you're telling
it, it's going to have to inherit from
HttpServlet
and then give it this name in this file.
So whenever I'm referring to this name, it
means this class.
So we're describing a servlet that the web
application container should go and load,
and then
we can refer to that name later in the
file to route requests to that servlet.
Now down here, we see there's a mapping.
Up here is where we're declaring the
server.
So we are defining a servlet.
And down here, we're doing routing.
So we're mapping a request to our servlet.
So in this case, we see that we're
referring to the original name of that
servlet we declared and then we're
specifying a
url-pattern that should be routed to that
servlet.
So in this case, we're going to route all
requests to the /video path to that
particular servlet.
The url-pattern can take on a number of
forms.
You can have regular expression matching
in the url-pattern.
So you can do things like match all URLs
that
begin with /video or match any URL that
ends with /video.
And you can have all kinds of different
schemes and the pattern here will
determine how
the web application container looks at
paths and
decides which paths should be mapped to
your servlet.
And if you have multiple servlets, you
simply define
multiple servlet tags and you simply
define multiple mapping
tags for the servlets describe how the
different paths
that are on the request map into different
servlets.
Now, as we'll see later, we'll going to
actually
use a finer-grained and more advanced
routing mechanism, but
for now, this is the basis, is this, this
is what goes inside of a web.xml file.
And a lot of newer applications don't use
web.xml.
They use, you know, Java-based
configurations.
But the vast majority of applications that
are out there still use
web.xml, so it's important to know what it
is and how it works.