[MUSIC]
We're going to walk thru a more
complicated
servlet that does a little bit more
to actually extract parameters and
validate them
that are being sent by the client.
So this servlet is moving towards the
direction of
building the video service that we've been
talking about.
So we're going to create a simple servlet,
and walk through it here.
That actually allows clients to send the
metadata
for videos, just the names and titles and
durations.
We're not talking yet about actually
sending video data,
but just the, the basic information to the
server.
So that it can store in a list, in memory,
and then when's client
send get request to the server, it can
return a list of those videos.
So let's take a look at how this actually
works.
So you can see here that we've got a
project called video servlet.
And within the project you want to take a
look in the source main
java folder and underneath this we'll see
two important classes that we'll be using.
The first one is a video object that we'll
be
using to store or represent the metadata
in the videos.
So let's open that object up and what
we'll see
is this is just a very straight forward
Java class.
It doesn't inherit from anything unusual
or exotic.
It's just a simple Java class that we're
creating.
And it has member variables to store the
name of
a video, the URL, and the duration of the
video.
And it takes those as constructor
parameters
and sets some values, and that's it.
That's everything that's in this file.
There's nothing else that's going on here,
just a simple video object.
So that's not as interesting.
So let's take a look at the video servlet.
So if you open up the video servlet,
immediately we see something a little more
interesting.
And that is we got a class that actually
extends.
HGDP servlet, which is the base of classes
that are going to be servlets.
So it extends job at x dot servlet dot
HGDP dot HGDP servlet.
So there's the import, if you need it.
And, as we discussed, this class is going
to receive
the HGDP requests that are coming in
through the server.
It's just like if we were building an
application that could take arguments
from the command line and receive those
arguments and invocations from the command
line.
This is a class that has methods to
receive
commands that are being sent across the
network as HTTP.
So one of the first things that we see
that we previously discussed is a do get
method.
And the do methods in a servlet, each one
of them corresponds to one of the http
request methods.
So, this servlet is going to respond to
two http request methods.
It's going to respond to the get
http request method and the post request
method.
Now, if we look at the code, what that
means is we
should see corresponding do get, and if we
scroll down do post methods.
So both of these are the handler methods
that are going to be
invoked on this class, when either a get
or a post comes in.
So, what's going to happen is, that
the servlet container that's running our
servlet.
So we have our video servlet that's inside
this servlet container.
Is going to rout requests that come in,
either to do post.
Or doGet and
all of this is going to be determined via
the request method.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
That's what's going to determine this
internal
routing to which method is getting
invoked.
Now there's a second layer routing that's
also going to happen
and that's the selection of servlet to
handle the request.
And that's what we're going to see in a
second
when we look at the web.xml file in this
project.
So right now, all we're looking at is
the internal handler methods within the
servlet once
it gets routed a request, that are going
to decide how the server responds to that
request.
So let's look at the implementation of
these methods.
So the do get method is fairly
straight-forward.
The first thing we do, as we did in the
simple
servlet that we created is, we're going to
set the output type.
We're going to tell the, set the content
type so that the
client knows what we're going to be
sending back to them.
So in this case, we're just sending text
plain back to
the client, so that it knows how to
display what we've got.
Now, the second piece is, we're getting a
prep writer again, and this
is exactly the same thing that we did in
the first simple servlet example.
We created a prep writer that allows us to
send data back to the client.
So the print writer is being used to write
data that's going back to the client.
So our mobile client over here is getting
data
that's coming in to the print writer's
write method.
So, whenever printrider.rider's called,
that's sending
that data back here to the client.
Also, the setContentType Method is going
to be important because that's telling
headers or providing headers that are
going to be put into this request.
So, when we call setContentType, we are
providing headers.
That are going to go back to the client as
we saw.
So this is how these methods are mapping
into the requests that we're creating.
Now, the actual bulk of the work of what
this method is
actually doing is down here in this For
Loop at the bottom.
We're looping over each video that we
currently have added and have in memory.
So, if we scroll up a little bit, we can
see
that this list of videos is simply a in
memory array list.
There's nothing fancy.
We're not connected to a database, yet.
And, we are looping over the list of
videos in this, in this, a for loop right
here, and then for each video we're simply
writing
out the name and the URL to the client.
So this is just a simple loop that's
outputting text that's being fed back
to the client so that it can go and do
something and read it.
Now, this actual get method isn't that
interesting.
It's just a simple method, and it's doing
something very similar to
what we saw, in a simple, servlet that we,
we looked at before.
Now let's take a look at a more complex
method in the due post.
Because suddenly, we're going to start
accepting more data from the
client that we have to look at and
actually validate carefully.
So let's look at the work that we have to
do in
order to accept that data from the client
and then validate it.
So we go down to the do post method, the
first thing we'll see here is that we're
accepting or expecting to accept a series
of parameters from the client.
So in this case, we're expecting
to receive name, URL, and duration
parameters.
And just like we did with get request, we
can extract these parameters from the http
request body.
In this case, it's a post body that' being
sent
to this due post method with the get
parameter method.
Again, if the client is sending query
parameters they can be extracted with get
parameter.
And if the client is sending, you know,
url encoded body, parameters in the form
body of a post, then we can also extract
them with the get parameter method.
So, we're extracting the values of the
name, the URL
and the duration keys that the client is
sending to us.
The next thing that we have to do is
something that's making things getting a
little more interesting.
And that's, we're going to have to
validate that one
of the parameters that we're getting is
the expected value.
So in the prior example of sample servlet
we expected that all of
the data that the client was sending to us
was just a string.
And we didn't really care about what the
content of it was
cause we weren't doing anything with it,
we were just echoing it back.
In this example, what we're actually
going to do is
we expect one of the parameters to be a
number.
So, we have to validate that we're
actually
getting a number back that is a java long.
So the first thing we do here is we're
going to actually create a java long to
store the value,
and then we have to try to parse a long
out of the string the client sent to us.
So you can imagine this is important,
because we don't want the
client to be able to send garbage data to
us for the long.
If they make a mistake and send an invalid
video duration to us, we want
to be able to catch that and tell the
client that they made a mistake.
Similarly, if they're doing something
malicious
and sending us data that isn't actually
a valid video duration, we don't want to
have that data stored on our site.
So, here, we have to actually go and check
that we have received a correct duration.
And, there's lots of, of checks that we
could do for the duration.
But in this case, the first thing we're
going to do is, we're just going to check
the format.
The next thing that we do, but as we
did before, is we're going to set the
content type.
So, I'm going to move on past that,
down to where it starts getting more
interesting.
Because we're accepting data and there's
the possibility, that the client might
not have send us correct data, we have to
use this if
statement, to look at, all of the
different parameters that the client's
sent to us, and make sure they meet our
expectations and format.
We have to remember that we have no
control over what the client sends us.
The client can send any data it wants in
its HTTP request.
And this is a really important point to
remember.
Even if you are writing your own client,
you should not write your
server to expect that all of the data is
correctly formatted, or non malicious.
You always need to realize anybody can
send an HTTP request across the method,
anybody
can prot, pretend do be your client,
and send you arbitrary requests to your
server.
And so you have to be able to handle
those arbitrary requests and make sure
they're actually valid.
So, as we see here, we're doing several
different checks.
One, we're checking that the name isn't
null, that
the url isn't null, and the duration
string isn't null.
And then we're checking that the actual
link of the name, and the
link of the url, if you strip out all of
the white space.
So that's what these trim methods do.
Is they actually strip out all of the
white space
in the string, or as long as we would
expect.
So we're saying that we expect a URL to be
at least 10 characters long.
And then we're also going in checking that
the duration
that we got was at least a, a certain
length.
We're not expecting any durations that are
zero, or less.
Now we're actually doing some extra work
that, now
that I look at it could probably be
eliminated.
We could just check the duration here, and
see if it's correct, but
we're actually checking the string as
well, but that could probably be
eliminated.
The key then, is that if any of these
things are wrong,
we need to tell the client that the client
made a mistake.
And the way that we do that is by sending
the 400 response
code back to the client which is
essentially a bad request response code.
So if the client has missed one of the
parameters or
provided an invalid value, we're going to
send an HDP400 response code.
And then as we see here in the second part
we're going to provide
the client sort of a nice hint as to what
it did wrong.
We're going to give it some information
about the parameters,
that we were expecting to see in the
request.
Now, you could make this fancy or not
fancy, it's rally up to you.
But the important thing is that, we're
sending this 400 response
code, which is telling the client that it
made a bad request.
If we get lucky, and we've gone through
all of this work up here.
So this is a lot of work, this is all the
work that we're
doing to extract the parameters from the
request and validate that they're actually
correct.
So if we go through all of this work up
there at
the top, finally at the bottom we actually
get to do some work.
So most of this method is just extracting
parameters that
the client sent us, and validating that
they meet our expectations.
So if we go thru all of that work,
down here at the bottom we finally get to
construct
a video object, which is what we're trying
to do
is take the client data and construct a
video object.
We get to add it to our list of videos,
and then finally we
can write back a message to the client
saying hey, we added the video.
So if you look at this video added method,
er
message, it's just a video added is the
value of it.
So this is just a constant we've defined
up top.
So this is a huge amount of work to
actually do something simple.
And that is to take a request from the
client, take in the data
they they provides us, construct a video
object and add it to our list.
A massive amount of work, is going
into all of this parameter extraction and
validation.
Now, it makes sense, that we have to do
some work here, because again, we
always want to remember, the values that
we're getting
in an http request, they could be
anything.
We don't know what the client is sending
us.
So as a developer, of a web based service
that's going to
receive http requests, you always need to
be diligent, to check the content
that you're getting in any you know key
value pairs that are
encoded in a foreign body and any query
string parameters and any headers.
Anything else you're getting from the
client, you must not trust
it, you must validate it yourself and
ensure that it's actually correct.