[MUSIC]
Servlets, as we've seen, provide a
mechanism for our code to
receive HTTP requests and then respond to
them in some way.
So, let's take at a, look at a code
segment
to begin implementing this video service
that we talked about originally.
That we want to be able to send commands
to it to add videos and we
want to be able to query the list of
videos that have been sent to the server.
So, this is a very simple servlet.
What we see is that we have a class up
here that extends the HttpServlet.
And so, what that does is that
automatically creates a class that has a
super class with the doGet, doPost and
other methods for the HTTP methods.
So we can go and override some of
those methods to begin adding logic to our
server.
Now, one of the important things,
obviously, is this servlet
is providing the parent HttpServlet class
is providing a number of
different functions to our class, and
we're just overriding a certain
subset of those functions like the doGet
method that aren't implemented.
So we're just providing extra logic to
implement our business-specific things.
In this case, the things related to video
that
we are layering on top of the servlet
framework.
So, what we've got is we've got a servlet,
and then it
has a list of the videos that have been
sent to the server.
Now, this is obviously a very simple
example.
We're only storing things in memory, so if
you shut the server
down, the servlet's not going to remember
what videos have been uploaded.
But we want to start with something simple
so that
we can build up and understand some of the
things
that servlets give us, as well as some of
the limitations and why we might want to
use another framework.
Particularly, the spring framework, which
we're going to talk about later.
So we're storing a list of the videos that
have been uploaded.
And videos are just simply an object that
tracks information
about a video, its name, its URL and its
duration.
So, we have this list.
And then on our doGet method right here,
if someone goes and sends a get request,
what's going to happen is this doGet
method
on our servlet is going to be invoked.
And what we can see is is that our servlet
and its
doGet method, the first thing it does is
it sets the content type.
[COUGH] And the idea behind this is the
servlet wants to
tell the client how to interpret the
result it's sending back.
And for this case, we're just doing
something simple.
We're just going to send black, back plain
text, so what
we're doing is we're setting the content
type to plain text.
And what this is is the MIME type that's
going to be send back to the client.
So when the client receives this, it will
know, I don't need to
interpret [INAUDIBLE] this as HTML, I just
need to interpret it as plain text.
Similarly, I, I don't need to interpret
this
as a video or an image or anything else.
It knows exactly what to do with it.
And then a little later down in our
servlet, what we see is that we're
looping through the list of videos that we
have in the servlet.
And then for each video, we're simply
writing out
a string that's being sent back to the
client.
In this case, we're writing back the name
and URL
of each video and we're just separating
these by new
lines, so you'll essentially have a plain
text list of
the videos that are being currently stored
on the server.
Now, this is a very, very simple example
and we can
see it's relatively straightforward to go
and implement this basic logic
for storing a list, looping through the
list and displaying the
results to the client, sending them back
in a plain text format.
The doGet method of the servlet's pretty
simple.
But when we look at the doPost part where
we're actually going to send some data to
the servlet in order to store a new video,
things start to get a little bit more
complicated.
So let's look at the work that we're
having to
do in this doPost method that isn't ideal
and is going to
help motivate why we're going to use
another framework built on
top of servlets that provides us a greater
level of abstraction.
And will help us to construct cloud-based
services from mobile devices even faster.
But let's take a look at this doPost
method
to help understand why we're going to do
that later.
So, if we look at the doPost method, we've
got a, a simple doPost method that we've
overrided from the super class here, which
is HttpServlet.
And this is part of the same servlet that
we were just looking at.
And then we've got something interesting
going on.
The first thing that we're doing is,
because we want the client
to be able to send us information about a
video that we need
to save, the client is going to in encode
that information either as query
parameters or as a body of an HTTP post in
this case.
Because we've got a post request.
So, the first thing we have to do is we
have to extract that data that
the client is sending to us in order to
get it out and do something with it.
So, one of the very first things we see
over here is we have extraction
of data from the client, so we've got a
series of method calls that are being used
to get out information like the duration
of the video or the name of the video.
So, once we've done that, [COUGH] the next
thing that the post does
is it actually goes and it sets the
content type [COUGH] of the response.
Because we want the, the client to know
that we're just going to send plain text
back, just like we did in the
doGet method, and we don't want it
misinterpreted.
We're going to send a response back that's
plain
text hat tells the client what happened on
the server
and gives it a little bit more information
than
just the HTTP response code that we're
going to be sending.
Now, things start to get a little bit more
complicated because we
have the situation here where we have to
worry about the fact
of what happens if the client fails to
send the parameter that we're
expecting, or the client sends a value
that isn't what we need.
So, for example, we're checking not only
for these values not being present and
null.
So if up here when we're extracting the
values, if one of those values doesn't
exist,
if we're asking for a parameter that
wasn't
provided by the client, it's going to
return null.
So down here, we have to do error checking
to make sure that all of those parameters
are there.
So this is error checking.
We gotta make sure that the client sent
us all of the information that we actually
need.
And if for some reason, the client failed
to send us a
parameter that we need, we need to tell
the client about that.
We need to have an error code sent back to
the client
and we need to have an error message sent
back to the client.
So in this case, we're sending back the
400 status code, the,
the 400 response code which tells the
client that its request was malformed.
It was missing data in its request that
was needed.
And then down in the error message, we're
just telling it here is the,
the data that we expected to see in that
request that wasn't there.
So we were expecting a duration and some
other things.
And you'll notice that we're starting to
build
sort of our own protocol on top of HTTP.
We're specifying things that we expect and
the client has
to know about them, and the client has to
make
sure that it encodes them into its request
and provides
them in either the query parameters or the
post body.
Now, assuming that we get past all this
[INAUDIBLE] checking, we don't have any
empty strings.
Then we're going to go down and we're
actually finally going
to start doing some actual logic related
to the video.
That is, we want to create a video with
the data we've
been given and then we want to add it to
the list.
But even when we get down here, we've
still got
a little bit more error checking to do and
some conversion.
So, if we see here, one of the things that
we're having to do
is we're having to actually go and take
this string that was extracted up
here for the duration because all of these
parameters are being sent as strings
in the HTTP request and we have to convert
it into the native type.
In this case, we have to convert it into a
long, which is what we expect in Java to
have.
So we actually have to do the parsing and
extraction of that long before we can do
anything else.
So this is going to be a data type
conversion that we're doing.
And this adds a little bit more complexity
to what we have to get, get done.
On top of this, all of these things are
then
being extracted, and once we finally get
all of this data
out of the request, you know, this simple
process or what
should be a simple process of getting all
this data out.
Once we finally do that, then we actually
go and construct
the video that we want to store in memory
in this list.
And then finally, only down at the very
end,
do we get to actually do some real logic.
And we can actually create and add the
video, in this case, to the list.
So it took us a whole lot of work to
extract parameters,
to error check the parameters, to convert
them to the correct types.
So before we could finally create an
object that
we needed to and do something with that
object.
And then finally, we tell the client, hey,
good job you did, it worked.
We got your video, we've added it to the
list of videos that's there.
Now, this is a very simply servlet.
And you can imagine, for complex cloud
services that are
supporting mobile devices, it could take a
lot of work
if we were having to do all of these
things
for every single different piece of logic
that we wanted.
This was a very simple piece of logic.
And yet, we were having to do a lot of
work to
go from, really, what this is about, is
going from HTTP to Java.
And then making sure that we have correct
values,
in our Java that we've extracted.
Doing any conversions we need to.
And then finally at the end, doing logic
related to our actual application.
And we would really like to be focusing
down here on this part of the application,
but you can see that in this case, most of
our code is focused on this part.
And that's a lot of work that we'd really
like to not have to do.