[MUSIC]
It's helpful for the rest of the course to
understand what people
mean by REST, typically, when they say you
have a REST interface.
And the piece of, of REST, what they're
probably describing, is the idea that
you're interacting with resources, rather
than specific objects or services.
Instead, you're, you're acting, you're
interacting with resources and
your interactions are specified through
URLs that address those resources.
And there is a common way that people
tend to build URLs to address resources,
that is
what, when you use that common format,
that's what
they mean by, do you have a REST API.
Is they're not meaning the true
definition, the
full definition of REST, what they're
meaning is,
you build up your resource URLs in the
particular format that I think of as REST.
So let's talk about what that format is,
since
it's helpful to understand what a lot of
people expect.
So let's say that we're accessing the
videos in our video service.
A way to represent a particular video
would be
/video, and then slash an identifier for
that video.
So let's say, video1.
So this is a very specific format, saying
this is a video.
Now let's say we wanted to go and find out
the url of that
video, or let's say we wanted to find out
the duration of that video.
We might go and say video/1/duration.
And this could be a addressing scheme that
said, go and access
videos, the first video and get its
duration, and return it to me.
So, this is going and accessing, resources
sort of in finer and finer
granularity of which, you know, resource
we're
accessing, and which part of that
resource.
Similarly, we might go and say /video, and
expect to get a list of all videos back.
Versus here we're getting specific,
and we're getting one video.
And then here, we're getting a part of a
video.
And when you hear people say a REST
based interface, or a REST based API,
typically, this
is what they're referring to, is that you
have
some URL addressing scheme that looks
something like this.
That you define resources in this sort of
generic format that
then gets more and more specific as you go
down the line.
And if you say /video it will give you all
of them.
If you say /video/ some identifier it will
give you a specific one.
Or you can ask a specific one and for a
specific part of that resource.
And this format, is what people think of
as
REST, and are commonly referring to when
they say REST.
The other component that they typically
are referring to,
is how you interact with these resources
through HTTP methods.
So, if you want to access a resource and
get its value, you send a GET request.
So GET, to video would give you the list
of all the videos.
However, if you went and sent a PUT
request to this.
It's going to create that collection of
resources, or if you send a PUT request to
down here
its going to create or replace, this
resource.
similarly, if you went and sent a POSt to
this resource, what you're
actually going to be doing is creating a
new one and adding it to the video.
So you would create a new video, it would
be added to the list, and
then a new resource address for that
resources
that you added would be returned to you.
And it's these types of interactions that
get labeled REST.
This sort of url addressing scheme and the
fact that we're using
POST to go and add, we're using PUT to
replace, we're using GET to access.
And also, we can go and potentially
delete, using the HTTP verb, some specific
resource.
And, that's really what's getting referred
to
as REST, is this loose definition that's
much
looser than what's actually described in
the true
definition of REST, but it's important to
understand.
What the basic idea is behind what people
think of as REST.
It's accessing resources in a format that
looks similar to this, and you can sort
of still choose how you describe, you
know, finer and finer granularity in your
resource.
And then using these HTTP verbs to
describe the deletion of a resource, or a
replacement of a resource, or addition of
a
new resource, or access to a new resource.
And so when we see most of the
applications that we're
going to be building in this course, we're
going to be using
URL schemes that look something like this,
and we're going to
be using verbs in HTTP in a similar manner
to this.