[MUSIC].
A challenge with mobile devices, is that
if we use HTTP as the primary protocol for
communicating with the cloud we run into
the
issue that HTTP is a client driven
protocol.
So what do I mean by this?
Well, in all of our interactions that
we've seen, we start with a client like
a mobile device, that initiates the
communication
with the server by sending in a request.
And so, the client is always driving the
communication.
And asking for a particular resources on
the server.
But one of the challenges we have is the
client decides
the timing of when it goes and checks for
updates from the server related to data.
So anything that's going to update data or
the state of the, the client.
Is going to require the client to make the
decision about when it
goes and actually talks to the server and
tries to retrieve new data.
So, if you think about this if you
have multiple clients that are interacting
with this server.
So, let's say we have a second client,
that's sending requests to the server.
And the second client sends, sends a very
important message which
we will just do a little, yo u know,
exclamation point.
Sends a very important message to the
server that this client needs to know
about.
Or some update to the data that this
client
just pulled in has shown up on the server.
There is no way.
.
For the server to easily initiate
communication with the
client to tell it to go and update that
data.
If we use the standard request response
model for
communicating with the cloud over HTTP,
we'll always run
into situations where we can't have the
server push
data that it needs to send to the client.
At exactly the time that the client should
have it.
So how can we design around or handle this
issue of,
the fact that all of the communication is
driven by the client.
The client decides when to grab the
information from the
server, and the timing between when it
goes and pulls information.
One way to handle this issue, is to let
the user decide when data is fetched from
the server.
So a common way that you'll see this done,
is you'll see a user interface,
particularly with list views, where we
have data,
and there is a pull down to refresh.
So there'll be some status refresh
indicator and if you pull down.
What's really happening is that when you
pull down far enough, the client is going
and sending a request to the server and
then getting the response back.
So this time that you see that little
spinner driving around.
What's actually happening is the client is
waiting for the data
to comeback so that it can update its list
that it's showing.
And this can be an effective way to handle
the issue of going and fetching data from
the server.
You can let the user decide when they want
to update the display.
And in many cases they will have an
appropriate.
You know, appropriate knowledge and make
good
decisions about when to go and update
things.
So this is certainly one valuable
approach.
You can do other approaches, where for
example every
time this view is opened it automatically
updates itself.
Or every time the app is launched, it
automatically goes
and synchronizes its data with that that's
on the server.
And those are all valid approaches that
use sort of an event driven model.
Where the events are coming from user
interactions with the app.
And the nice thing about this approach is
that the user
isn't going to typically go and just
refresh over and over.
Or at least for not expend, extended
periods of time.
At some point the user is going to stop
refreshing and give up.
And you're going to stop sending requests
to your server.
So the user gets to kind of make the
intelligent decisions about when it
makes sense to actually go and fetch
something from the server and when it
doesn't.
Another model that you can use to try to
keep the
client up to date with information from
the server, it's called polling.
So, the idea behind this is, the client
starts up, the server is available.
And while the app is running, or while
some service in the app
is running, the client, at regular
intervals, continually requests data from
the server.
And you'll have some time interval that is
decided by the client.
Some time interval like T and every T
intervals time units of T, like every
three seconds the client will go and send
a request to the server to try to refresh.
The problem with this is that.
You run in the situation that if you have
a client open, even if
there is no actual data on the server for
it, the client doesn't know that.
It just has to blindly continually end
request
to the server hoping that it gets
something back.
So, while you're sending all of these
requests to the server.
You're wasting resources on your server.
Because every time you send a request to
the server and there's
nothing there, the server still has to
allocate resources, process the request.
Check if anything is available for the
client.
And then if nothing is, send back a
response.
You're using up network resources, memory
and cpu on the server.
And if you have lots of
clients, they're continuously requesting
data, you're multiplying
the traffic and the effect on your server
in terms of the resource usage.
So, polling certainly can give you the
effect of very up to date
results to the client, but it can come at
a very significant cost.
To the resources that are being used up on
your server.
Sometimes approaches are used to try to
make the client adaptively
decide and adjust it's time interval when
it's not getting data back.
So the idea behind this is, is that.
If things are updating rapidly in the
server,
then each time the client sends a request
or every few times that the client sends a
request, it should get a response back.
And so the adaptive approach is
essentially start
off with a single time interval that's
short.
So we'll go and pull it you know, every t
seconds.
And then if a certain number of requests
come back with no updates,
the client will automatically switch to a
new polling rate like two T.
So it will wait twice as long to send the
next request.
So rather then waiting six seconds, I mean
three seconds, it'll now wait six seconds.
Similarly, if some number of requests come
back empty, then the client will
automatically see
it's wasting resources in the server, so
it'll switch over to a new model like 4T.
And continue to increase and typically
it's
an exponential increase of the time
between when,
it receives a request a response for a
request, until it sends the next request.
So the client can begin adaptively
tapering off
its requests to the server, because it
sees that
there's not a lot happening that, not a
lot
of updates that are of interest to that
client.
And typically, there will be some ceiling
to this update link.
So at some point, you'll get to maybe an
hour between
updates, and the client will no longer
update any faster than that.
Up until the point that it gets some
results back, in which
case that it can switch back to the more,
rapid polling rate.
So, once you do get something back, you
can back to the lower polling rates
and continuously check to see if things
are coming in, that you should know about.
So, this model really tries to adapt and
improve
the resource utilization on the server by
having a client.
Only poll when things are happening that
it can detect.
Another approach to handling this issue of
trying
to get updates from the server to the
client
when you're using HTTP, is to rely on one
of the newer HTTP based protocols, like
web sockets.
So with web sockets, the idea is that,
when the
client connects to the server, it can ask
to upgrade the connection to a web socket.
And once a web socket has been created,
the
idea is that the client goes and sends a
request.
It updates the connection to a web socket.
And rather than being purely client
driven, once this web socket is
established either party can send data to
the other one.
So the server at any time can push data
down to
the client, and the client can push data
down to the server.
All of this however, depends upon the
client being connected to the server.
Now the nice thing about web sockets are
that, we don't necessarily incur the
message overhead that
we typically do with each request and
response
from a server if we're using the HTTP
protocol.
So, normally if we send an HTTP request,
we're
going to send all of the header data all
of
the other information, the resource, the
URL, all of
this stuff is going to be sent to the
server.
And then every time the server's going to
send back the content
type, the body, any headers that it wants
to send back.
And there's a lot of communication
overhead.
And if we know very specifically about the
protocol
that we're expecting the server to speak
to us.
We can write simpler protocol on top of
web sockets that has lower overhead.
We can send smaller messages that don't
include all of the typical HTTP.
Headers and other things that we need.
We can just simply send binary messages or
some other format back and forth in a
server.
And so we can potentially have an increase
in efficiency.
We can also have the ability now to have
the server push data whenever it wants to
the client.
So in a number of aspects, this is
a much improved approach to just directly
using HTTP.
The downside of web sockets with a mobile
client is we still run
into the issue that clients are mobile in
nature and their connections drop.
And so, a web socket can be used to push
data from the server to the client.
But only as long as the client is
connected to the server.
So if we do use Web Sockets.
We have to deal with the fact that we may,
let's say for example lose cell signal.
And then, we need the client to
automatically go and
reconnect and then upgrade its connection
to a web socket again.
So, if we go with a web socket type
approach, we have to deal with
the air handling of doing the reconnect
whenever
we notice that a connection has been
dropped.
So we have to have our own event mechanism
and notifications
to detect that something has happened,
we've dropped this web socket connection.
Keep going and trying to reconnect until
we get connected again.
And that in itself is its own sort set of
logic that you have to think about is.
How do you decide when to reconnect?
Do you wait until you get an even from
Android telling you that the internet
connection has come back?
Do you test the internet connection to see
if
it's fast enough to support what you
want to do?
There's a whole host of sort of logic that
has to be built in to decide.
Or you may just regularly try at different
intervals to reconnect.
And also what happens between if you have
changes in the client
and changes in the server and how do you
synchronize and other things.
So, web sockets is a nice approach.
You just have to be cognizant that you
have to go deal with your own reconnection
logic.
The other issue is that web, web sockets
can be more heavy weight on a server.
So, for, you can imagine if you have a
client that's sending HTTP requests, if
it doesn't actually need any data, it can
let go of the connection to the server.
And no resources are being taken up on the
server.
With a web socket we're going to have a
persistent connection, which
depending on how the server is
implemented, could be substantially more
overhead.
It may make it so that we can't support as
many simultaneous clients.
Or it may be that the trade off in the
reduction in message overhead,
particular for polling, is much better
with web sockets, and so we get more out.
But, we have to be cognizant of that
keeping an open connection can have
substantial resource impact as well, if we
have millions or hundreds of thousands of
clients.
It's something to consider with an
approach like this.