[MUSIC]
So let's return to our example application
for inserting video
into a database and cataloging that
information about the video.
So that we can later go and retrieve these
videos off
the file system and the meta data that
we've inserted for them.
From this database of metadata.
So, if we remember, we were sending
commands to the application.
And we were doing this from the command
line.
But what we like to do is have a mobile
application that's somewhere else.
That's not on the same host.
And we'd like this application to be
living, in the cloud.
So we'd like all of this to live in the
cloud somewhere.
So how do we get, the, mobile device to
send these commands
which are received by the application and
stored somewhere in the cloud?
Well, now that we've learned about HTTP.
We know one of the communication protocols
that we could use to send these commands.
So we can imagine that we are using HTTP
to send the commands to the application.
So, for example, we might want to use a
PUT command to
go and insert video into the application.
So we might have PUT be the, the HTTP
method
that we're using when we're going to store
a new video.
Similarly, we might want to get a video
that's already been previously posted.
So we might send a GET command to query
video or fetch the video.
And then the application would receive
that GET command.
Go and process it.
And send the results back to us.
As an HTTP response.
And
we even have HTTP request that are being
sent to carry out commands.
Now, if we're going to send a request to
put a video, we're
probably going to need to include the data
for that video with it.
So for example, we could encode data for a
video, inside
a multi-part request.
Or a multi-part body, to be more specific.
A multi-part body that's included with an
HTTP request.
So we could, create a request that has
this multi part
v, body that includes the video and we'd
go and store it.
Similarly we might have inside that body,
not only the video,
but we might also have, the name, as a key
value pair.
So we have name, and then the actual name
of the video.
We might also want to tell them some
extra,
information, about that video to help
process it.
So we might want to do something like we
could pr, print the content type.
In a header.
So that they would know information about
the format, or
encoding of the video, that we're sending
to the server.
So as we see, suddenly these HTTP
constructs that we learned about have
direct
relationship on this application scenario
that we've
got where we're sending video to an
application.
But suddenly, rather than doing this on
the command
line, we are sending HTTP request to the
video.
And we're encoding parts of those request
as multi-part bodies, or we could
use URL encoded bodies, so for example if
we're sending video it probably makes
sense but if we're doing a simple GET
query, it might make sense to send the
query as parameters in the URL, so we have
query param-
params.
So how do we identify particular videos?
Well each video might have a URL.
So that we can address that video, we know
the host its stored on, and we know the
path to that video on the server, so that
it can go and access it some way.
So the resource naming schemes are giving
us the ability to
go and address the resources that we're
storing in this case.
Similarly, on the response side, we need
to know what happened with our commands?
Did our commands work or not?
So the HTTP response can have the HTTP
response code.
And so we can look and say, you know, is
this a 200, did it find the video?
Was it able to store the video?
Or is this a error 500, did the server
crash in some way?
Or is this a 404?
Did I request a video that doesnt' exist.
So the response code can give us
information about what's happening
on the server when our commands are being
sent to the application.
Similarly the response can include the
body, which will have the data.
And this may be a video.
Or this might be just text coming back
that's, you know, a set of key value pairs
or some other information in response to a
query that we're issuing on the metadata.
And again, we could tell the client what
it's getting
back, either the type of video or the how
the key value
pairs are encoded using the content type,
[SOUND] header.
So, suddenly we are getting the ability to
express not only
what we're sending the server but
information about what we're sending back.
So HTTP is giving us a framework to
build an application where we are sending
commands
or messages to the service that's in the
cloud and that's all we're going to term a
service.
It's just an application that we moved
into the
cloud that can receive these HTTP requests
that carry
commands and then provide the output back
as HTTP
responses and that's what we're going to
call our cloud service.
Is it's just applications, just like
you've built before that maybe took
parameters
off the command line, but suddenly we're
taking them from the internet using HTTP.
And we're going to be focused on cloud
services with
HTTP because there's also other ways that
you could communicate,
but HTTP is by far and away, the most
common
method of communicating between mobile,
mobile devices and cloud services.
So, we've built this entire framework
around the various constructs in HTTP
that we can use to place our application
in the cloud and then
send it commands which we can read and
process on the application side
using these constructs that we understand,
and then do something with the
information.
Now, one of the questions that arises is,
there are lots of ways that we
could express our command structure, our
expectations
about the formatting of those commands in
HTTP.
We can express the query parameters for
requests that we're sending
for information about the, the metadata
that was stored with videos
as query parameters or we could go and
express that information
as a multi-part set of parameters or URL
encoded form parameters.
We could store video with PUT request or
we could decide that we want to store
video
with a POST request because we can also
send a multi-part body along with a post
request.
We could use a delete HTTP method to tell
the
server to go and remove a video or we
could
just simply use a GET request to a
specific URL
to indicate to the application that we
want to remove a video.
So there's lots of things that we have to
consider when we're
trying to figure out how do we map our
application onto HTTP.
It, it give us a really, it gives us
a really good structure for building these
applications, but there's
still lots of design decisions that we
have regarding
what are the structures that we use for
our URLs?
How do we express where video is on the
server?
because we could have arbitrary naming
schemes.
Which of the HTP request methods do we
want to use for which actions?
Do we allow doubling up of request
methods?
For example, we could have a GET and a
POST, that
both access the same query URL allowing us
to send a query.
So we can have one version that allows
us to send a GET request with query
parameters
or we can have another version with a
post request that sends URL encoded foam,
form parameters.
And both of them would get the job done.
So we have to understand all of these
areas where we can make design decisions
and build on top of the HTTP protocol in
order to build a very complex application