[MUSIC]
One of the most common approaches that
ends
up getting used to solve this problem of
getting information or updates from the
server to
the client is what's known as Push
notifications.
Or depending on which particular platform
you're on.
If you're on Android, it's the Google
Cloud Messaging.
And the idea behind this is that every
Android client,
automatically sets up a persistent
connection to
Google servers, it's GCM servers, which
are the Google Cloud Messaging servers.
And this connection is done over XMPP,
which is an
XML based messaging protocol, that was
originally used for chat messages.
And the idea is, is that at any time
because this GCM server has
access to the Android client over XMPP, it
can push information to it.
So typically what happens is, is if you
want to have a
server that you're building that needs to
push information to a client.
What happens is, is when the Android
client goes and establishes the
connection, the initial, XMPP connection,
what it gets back is a registration ID.
And this is a unique handle or identifier,
an address
of this Android client on this GCM server
and then what
the Android client does is it sends its
registration
ID to the server, your sever doing
something like a
traditional HTP Push, I mean Post, or Put,
or whatever
it needs to do, depending on your API to
your server.
So now your server knows the unique ID of
this
Android client on, on this particular
Google cloud messaging system.
So what the server can do is when it wants
to send a message to the client, even
though it
doesn't directly have a connection to the
client, it can send a POST
message over HTTP that has a specific
format.
The POST message tells the GCM server, the
registration ID
of the client or clients that the server
wants the message delivered to.
And then the actual body or the content of
the message that should be delivered.
And so this gets sent to the GCM server,
and then because it has
a persistent connection to the one or
multiple clients that the server wants you
to
push to, it can then over one of these
XMPP connections, send the message that
the server provided to each of the clients
that it specified with a registration ID.
So, the idea behind this is the Android
client is setting up a persistent
connection to
Google's infrastructure and each time and
a client
connects to this infrastructure, it's
getting a registration ID.
And libraries that are on the Android
cloud automatically
handle the issues of reconnecting when the
connection has been
lost because you were in an airplane or
you went
through a dead zone and you didn't have
cellular coverage.
The Android libraries automatically
continually reconnect to the GCM server.
And if you have a rooted device, this only
happens and works if
you have all of the Google Play services
and apps installed on the device.
But it goes and connects, it gets this
unique registration ID.
And then anybody that wants to send a
message to this client can basically
obtain that
client's registration ID, so in this case
your
app gets that registration ID, sends it to
server, and then when your server wants to
send a message to the client, rather than
sending
it directly to the client, it sends an
HTTP message to the GCM infrastructure,
the Google infrastructure.
And the Google infrastructure based on the
registration ID or IDs that you
provide, figures out how to use its
XMPP connections to automatically deliver
the message.
Even if you're using a Push type service,
there's still
some architectural considerations to think
through when you're building your app.
The first one is the style of
notifications
that you're going to use to update your
app.
So there's a couple different approaches,
one is that you can have the client and
the server and GCM and
whenever the server wants to send
an update to the client, let's say you
have a server that's going
to notify the client of people that are
subscribing to that client's videos.
So whenever the server wants to tell the
client that a new subscriber has shown up,
it would send the post message with the
registration ID of the client to GCM with
the identifier, let's say, the message is
who subscribed,
so it, it, it directly encodes in the
message, the particular subscriber.
And from that point, when the client
receives the message,
it can instantly update its internal state
and be done.
Now, this is certainly a viable approach
as to
just directly send all of the state
information that you
want to communicate to the client in the
actual
message bodies that you're pushing out
over Google Cloud Messaging.
And the nice property about this is that
you
get the message to the client as quickly
as possible.
You get it that state update as quickly as
possible.
Now, one of the downsides of this approach
is that the messages
that you send through Google servers are
limited to four
kilobytes, so this only works if you can
send a state
notification that is less than four
kilobytes in size.
For example if you wanted to sync actual
video data, on the client,
you're not going to be able to do this
over Google Cloud Messaging.
Google is not going to push out a
multi gigabyte video, over cloud messaging
to client.
So this only works and is really designed
for
sort of small bits of information that
you're sending.
But, there's still a way to get large data
pushed to the client.
And the way that you do that is, you use
essentially a push to sync model.
So before when we were talking about
polling, the problem
was polling was that the client never knew
what was
going on in the server, it didn't know
when it
should go and poll the server to pick up
information.
But, with a push to sync model the
idea is, is that if something interesting
happens on
the server that the client needs to know
about it can push it to Google cloud
messaging.
The client can receive the message and
then it can go and pull
the server to get the state that it needs
to know about.
And so with something like this you could
actually
go and send messages that are greater than
four kilobytes.
What's happening is the server's sending
an event that's pushed
to the client, that then triggers a pull
from the server.
So, it's performing essentially the same
function as if you
were pushing out a large amount of data to
the client.
The client is being told to go and pick
up new state information, and you can send
it as
much state as you want, it's just that it
revolves, re, requires an extra round trip
to your sever.
Rather than directly receiving the message
from Google's cloud servers.
There's another reason that you might
want to consider using a
push to sync model, and that is if the
data or
the state that you're pushing out to the
client is
sensitive, and you are concerned about
Google having access to it.
So in our video example, it probably
doesn't make sense.
We've, we probably don't care about the
messages that are being sent.
But if, for example, you're building a
health
care based app, you might not want to send
a patient data through a push
notification, so if
you post patient data to Google clouds
cloud messaging.
That may not be acceptable in your country
and with
your particular laws, and then have it
delivered to the client.
In that case what you really want to do is
send a notification
that tells the client to go and pull your
server to get the data.
And with this model you can control the
security, so you get to control the
data and the security that you use to
deliver that data to the client.
Now Google I'm sure has a very, very high
security on their servers, but it's still
important that you
be able to control in many cases, the
actual
dissemination of your data and the
security over that data.
So the push to sync model is good when you
neither need to push out large amounts of
data or
you need to be in strict control of that
data's
dissemination and the security over the
dissemination of that data.
If you just want a quick message to the
client to update its state that doesn't
require high security, then the push to,
with
a message body is the right way to go.