[MUSIC]
It can be helpful to understand how
Spring actually converts our objects that
we return
from controller methods or that we pass
into controller methods, back and forth
from JSON.
So let's say that we have a controller
method like,
let's call this Video createvideo
and we will pass in a video.
And I'm going to leave off the annotations
and other things.
And we assume that there's a method body
here that does something.
So, the idea is we want the client to be
able to, through some request path.
And you would assume there was some
request mapping here.
There's at response body in this video.
There is at request parameters or at
request
body or whatever it is, on this, video
parameter.
So we're basically, we've already created
all of the infrastructure.
To make this method accessible, [UNKNOWN].
Now, one of the questions is how do we
take in a video from
JSON, and then how do we return a video
and convert it back to JSON.
So this is going to JSON and Spring
probably, and this is going from JSON.
So, what is the default mechanism or
approach
that Spring uses to convert to and from
JSON?
By default, to do this, Spring uses a open
source project called Jackson
and these, conversions are part of an, a
thing that Jackson supports called the
object mapper.
And the naming is a sort of a give away of
what this thing does.
It maps objects to JSON and it maps JSON
back to objects.
So, with an object mapper, we can go and
say, convert this object
into a JSON string or take this JSON
string and convert back into
an object and we just tell Jackson what
type of class we're expecting
that JSON string to be and then
it automatically goes and constructs an
object.
So, let's look at an example of converting
from JSON to an object with Jackson.
First, we need to define our video object
or
our video class that we're going to be
operating on.
So we'll just have a video and let's give
our class a couple of member variables.
Let's have a,
string title
and maybe private
string.
And you could have whatever you wanted
URL.
Now, just to be more interesting, let's
also add a
length to our duration
to our video.
Now, you can imagine that we would go and
create some getters and setters for these
properties so we would have public, String
getTitle.
And similarly, we would have getDuration,
we
would have getURL, and we would also have
setters.
So, we would have
public void setTitle.
It would take the title in as a parameter.
So, if we had this object, we would like
to
be able to map JSON into instances of this
object.
So, let's say that we have JSON that looks
something like this.
So, we have a JSON string that looks like,
we're just going to create
this object and we're
going to have title
Coursera and then we might have duration,
some duration 12345 or
something like that.
And we would have maybe URL,
and
we have some URL for this thing.
Now, what Jackson does, is by default, you
can tell it to go
and convert JSON into instances of a
particular class.
So in this case, we can go and convert
this JSON into an instance of video.
And the way that Jackson does this is
first by default, it expects video to
have a constructor that takes no arguments
so that it can construct a new incident.
So, what Jackson's going to do is it has a
method called read value that will
basically take this.
It will call the constructor for video.
It will create a new video object and then
it will call, as it walks through
the JSON, it will call setTitle and it
will find setTitle method.
It will call setDuration and setURL.
And each time it finds a new property on
the object in the JSON,
it will look at the appropriate type for
that, parameter or member variable of the
objects based on either the return type
from the getter or the value that's
being passed into the setter and the type
of parameter being passed into the setter.
And it will automatically look at that and
figure out how it needs
to convert from the string or number here
into a call on the setter.
So, it's a lot like what our Spring
controller is doing where
it's automatically, you know, constructing
our
controller objects and calling methods on
them.
In this case, the underlying Jackson
framework is going and looking
at the different pieces of JSON and then
automatically constructing objects that
we tell it to construct and then mapping
the different properties in
those JSON objects to the getters and
setters inside of our class.
So, this will end up calling setTitle.
It will call setDuration.
It will call setURL.
And it will automatically convert the
values.
The other interesting thing about Jackson
is let's say
that video had embedded reference to some
other object.
So, lets say that there was a video type
object.
Jackson, if it saw a property that was
video type and then specified a new JSON
object embedded within it, it would
automatically extract that object, look at
the type that was specified in video where
it would say video type and
then it would construct an instance of
video type before passing it to video.
So Jackson can go and take an entire
hierarchy of
objects or tree of objects specified in
JSON and convert them
into Java objects that we specify through
a series of
classes with getters and setters and, by
default, no argument constructors.
So if you ever go and see some strange
errors from Spring, for example, it may
say, oh, well,
your, your format is incorrect, or if it
sees that
there's a property here that's not in the
class, Jackson
will throw an exception saying some
property that it
was expecting wasn't on the class, or vice
versa you
can have properties that are required in
the class that
if they're not present in JSON it will
throw exceptions.
But, Jackson takes this process of going
from this to instances of
that, and automates it, so that you don't
have to write all of the code to do that.
And Jackson is what's sitting underneath
the covers in Spring, providing this
ability to automatically take your
response body from a controller method and
return it back into JSON or take JSON as
being sent as
a parameter to a controller method and
convert it into an object.
One of the other things is, you can go and
control how Jackson converts your objects
to JSON and can goes from JSON back
to your objects through a series of
annotations.
So, you can do things like @JSONIgnore
to tell Jackson properties of your objects
that you don't want converted
into JSON and brought from JSON back into
your object
to help it know things that you don't,
care about.
There's also the ability to go and specify
certain properties that you would like to
name differently.
So the default naming scheme is, it's
going to take a
property, it's going to title case the
first letter of the property.
So, it will go get plus it's going to take
the first lev, letter and upper case it.
So, that gets converted into getTitle.
If you had Foo here, that would get
converted into getFoo.
And similarly, if you have a setTitle or a
get, if you
have a getDuration method that's
automatically
going to become the JSON properly
duration.
So, you can also use annotations within
Jackson to control the naming of the
JSON that gets produced or the JSON that
gets consumed and mapped to your objects.