[MUSIC]
With Spring we create a series of
controller objects
that have various methods that we want to
have invoked.
By the web container.
Which is going to be routing them and to
do that, we make sure we set up a
web container with a dispatcher servlet
that Spring provides.
And then it decides.
Which requests go where and the web
container routes request to the dispatcher
servlet.
Now, as you can imagine.
If we want to set all of this
infrastructure up from
scratch we've got to do a whole bunch of
different things.
One is we've got to provide.
The web container with routing
information, which
can be done with something like web.xml
or by calling various method calls to tell
the web container how to route requests.
We've got to provide routing information
to the dispatcher servlet.
In order for it to know about our
different controllers.
And we do that with the annotations.
So these are usually annotations.
But we still have to have the web.xml or
some
configuration file that tells the web
container to get set up.
We also have to do the work of setting up
the web container.
So we might have to set up Tomcat which
is a web container or Jetty which is
another one.
And so we'll have to set up the web
container somewhere
and then we'll have to install our
application with a web.xml and
then all of this other stuff comes into
play and it
takes a lot of work to set all of these
things up.
So, Spring, one of the subprojects of
Spring is
a project called Spring Boot that is
designed to make
it really easy to set all of this stuff
up for an web application like this that
we're building.
Spring Boot will automatically configure
all
of these various parts of our application.
So that we can focus on writing our
controllers and putting the logic in them.
So this is where Spring Boot allows us to
focus, is where the actual value is.
All of this stuff, related to, like, our
video service, which is the logic in these
controllers.
And Spring Boot helps to automate a lot of
this set up.
So this is the stuff that Spring Boot
automates is the set up
of this tier in front of all of our
controllers.
Because really all we want to do is focus
on writing controllers.
We don't want to focus on all of this set
up stuff.
In addition to writing our controllers,
and so Spring Boot makes
this happen automatically and it does it
in a really smart way.
We can go and specify as many of the
different parts of this configuration
as we want or as few of them as we want
and Spring Boot will automatically.
Fill in the details.
So, if we specify certain parts of this
configuration Spring Boot
will use that information and then build
everything else around it.
If we don't specify anything, we just do
the simplest bits of configuration that
Spring Boot
needs it'll automate everything in here
and make
appropriate decisions about the way to
configure it.
A Spring Boot application has a fairly
simple structure, at least initially.
We do two things in Spring Boot
applications,
if we're writing a web application at
least.
One we create our set of controllers that
are just Java
objects.
And.
This is where most of the logic resides
for our application.
And then the second piece is we create a
class called Application typically.
This is a naming convention that is often
used
but you can call it something else if you
want.
You just have to annotate it properly.
And this is where we define
the configuration of, of our particular
application.
So this is where we define,
our
controllers potentially or we tell Spring
to automatically go and discover them.
And configuration.
So we can go and override defaults that
Spring Boot will create.
Now, what we do in order to launch Spring
Boot is this application has a traditional
main method, a.
Public static void main method that is
going to be invoked from the command line.
And in this main method what we do is
essentially invoke
Spring Boot and we do that typically by
doing something like Spring
application.run
and passing then our application
configuration here.
So this is the, the simplest sort of
sort of organization of a Spring boot web
application.
We have the appropriate libraries in our
class path.
To launch Spring Boot.
And then we have an application class that
defines the minimal configuration that
we're interested in defining.
And then we just tell spring
application.run.
And we provide it our, our application
class.
And Spring, from that point, takes over.
And it does a whole variety of things.
But some of the most important things are.
It's going to set up the container, the
web container.
And it's going to be an embedded web
container.
It's going to discover our controllers.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
It's going to set up the dispatcher
servlet.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
I'm just going to invit, abbreviate this
dispatcher.
And then it's going to.
We're going to set the web container,
we're going to discover our controllers,
we're going to
set up that dispatcher servlet, and we're
going to tell it about our controllers.
And then it's going to go and do any other
configuration that we've specified like
connecting to databases or other stuff.
So.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, as you can see, Spring Boot is
automating a huge amount of our work for
us.
It's setting up the web container, it's
find
our controller, it's setting up the
dispatcher servlet.
Telling the web container about the
dispatcher servlet,
telling it to, when to request to route
to the dispatcher servlet, and by default
it's
going to route all requests to the
dispatcher servlet.
And then it's telling the dispatcher
servlet about
our controllers, and then doing any other
configuration stuff.
And all we had to do was write our
controllers which contain the logic that
we care about.
And write this application dot Java class
to tell Spring
Boot which pieces of the configuration we
want it to, override from its defaults.
So we'll give it some initial information
and hints that it needs to go and get
it's job done, and then it will take care
of all of the rest of this complexity.
So for the rest of the course, most of
what you're
going to see in the projects, and the
example code is that
there will be an application.java clas
that you should always go
and look for and that's going to define
the core of the application.
And it'll define that configuration
information.
And then from there, we'll probably have a
bunch
of controller objects which are just plain
Java objects.
That will provide various pieces of the
logic for our application.
And the application is the, the part
that's tying all of this together.
It's the part that's telling Spring Boot,
where our controllers
live or where to go and look for our
controllers.
How to construct them and, as we'll see,
Spring can automatically
instantiate out objects for us and provide
them the correct parameters.
And references to other objects they need
to get their job done.
So Spring is going to go and automate all
of this construction effort, and [UNKNOWN]
this configuration of
our web container, and the dispatcher
servlet, and
the connections from our dispatcher
servlet to our controllers.
So at the end, what we do is we just focus
on this part.
We focus.
And Spring Boot does this.
So this is the automated part.
And this is our manual part.
That we have to do as developers.
So, whenever you see one of the
applications go and look for the
application.Java file.
Figure out what it's telling Spring Boot
to
do, what is it configuring Spring Boot
for.
And it'll also give you a hit as to
where the key controllers are or other
objects are.
That are going to participate in this
application and provide some logic.