[MUSIC]
Spring controllers, are just standard Java
objects.
There's nothing special about them.
So, let me give you an example, let's
write a simple spring
controller and show, how we would connect
it to the dispatcher servlet.
So that dispatcher servlet could route
requests to
that controller, into the appropriate
methods within the controller.
So in order to create a spring controller,
all
we need to do is create a simple class.
So in this case, let's create a class
called, Contacts control
and, what you will notice, is that well
first of
you will notice that we have to add class
here.
Since we want this to be a java class.
This is just a basic java class.
There is no special interfaces, or class
that we are inheriting from.
Now, let's say that we want to have a
method that is going
to handle requests from clients, in order
to view a list of contacts.
We could simply say, public, contacts,
get contacts.
And this is just like any other java
method.
We just need to do something, to retrieve
the contacts.
And then, let's say that contacts are
stored in some variable C.
And
then we're going to return the contacts,
so we'll return C.
So, this is just a basic Java class, we've
got a basic Java method.
Or, we're going and doing some work.
What's really nice is this is, this class
is clean.
It's, it's standard Java, it's not
polluted by any frameworks.
But we need a way to connect it, to
the dispatcher servlet, so that the
dispatcher servlet knows
about it, knows which request to route to
it,
and knows which methods to route those
requests to.
The way that we do this in spring, is we
add an @ RequestMapping annotation.
And what this tells the spring framework,
is that this is
going to be a method, that we want to
route request to.
And we'll talk about what goes into this
in a second.
The other thing we have to do is at the
top of this class, we have to add an
@ controller annotation, so that Spring
knows that this
class, that we want it to serve as a
controller.
Now, what we do in this request mapping,
is we then
specify a path for when we want this thing
in vogue.
For example, we could say /contacts, that
we want you to route any
request to /contacts into this particular
method.
And then, what the dispatcher circuit will
do, is whenever it sees a request
with a /contacts path, it will
automatically
route that request into, this particular
method.
So if we then went and let's say we
extended our class, and we have another
method, we have public, let's say
contacts, and then we just call this
friends, for example.
Maybe, we would want a list of contacts
that we consider to be just our friends.
The way that we would tell the dispatcher
servlet about this thing is, again, we
would just
add another RequestMapping annotation,
and we would map it to a separate path
from the first one.
So maybe this one goes to /friends.
So these annotations, the request mapping
annotations tell the dispatcher sort of
what.
When you route a request to the contacts
control object, and
which we are saying is a controller with
this act controller annotation.
If it goes to, if the request is for slash
contacts, it should go in this method.
If the request is for slash friends, it
should be routed to this method.
And these methods on these a, on this
object will then handle
the logic for processing those requests,
and determining what happens with them