[MUSIC]
So we've seen how we can take requests
that are coming from a mobile client, like
a mobile device, and create controllers
that then have methods that are
annotated with that request mapping and at
request pa, parameter or at a path
there in order to map those requests into
invocations of methods on our objects.
And to take parameters from the que,
requests, either in the query
string or in the body, if it's a URL
enphoto, encoded form body
or multi-part body or even out of the
actual request path itself and
map those into the method parameters that
we need to invoke the method.
The one thing we haven't talked about is,
we've only talked
about how we get data into our methods to
invoke them.
But we haven't talked about how the data
that we're returning from our method
actually ends
up being converted into a response that's
an
HTV response that goes back to the client.
And how that gets encoded and how that
data
that we're returning, in this case a Java
object
called contact, actually turns into
something that can be
sent in an HTV response back to the
client.
So let's look at actually how we can do
that in Spring.
So, in Spring, when we declare our
response,
we declare it by specifying what the
return type is for the method.
And what we want to do is we want to tell
Spring that you should look at the return
type, and you should automatically use it
as the body
of the response that you're sending back
to the client.
And we do that by annotating the return
type of the method with @ResponseBody.
And
so now, when Spring sees our return type
of our method, it
knows, when I invoke this method, I'm
going to take the return type,
which is a contact, and I'm going to
encode that contact into
the body of the response that I am sending
back to the client.
The way that Spring does this is, it has a
series of what it calls message converters
that can convert data being sent in the
body of a request from
a client into Java Objects and then also
convert Java Objects back into a body that
can be sent out to a, a client that's,
that requested something from the server.
And, in this case, the default way that
it, Spring tries to convert our data, is
it
will convert this contact object that
we're returning into
JSON, so that the client can receive JSON
back.
And it will be a JSON object that
represents the contact.
So whenever we go and send a request to
/search, the dispatcher controller's going
to go, it's going to see that slash search
should be mapped into this search method.
Any parameters inside of here that we
have, request param annotations
on or path var annotations, it will get
the data for them.
It will extract them and pass them into
the correct location in the method.
Our method logic's going to get executed.
And then our method is going to return a
contact object,
which Spring will then convert because
we've added the @ResponseBody annotation.
It will then see this and know that I need
to convert
this object into the body of the HT
response that I'm sending back.
And it will convert that contact object
into
JSON and place it into the response body.
So now we have a complete path from the
client sending a request.
Spring, seeing that request in the
dispatcher servlet, figuring out which
request
mapping of all these annotations and all
the various methods actually maps
to the path in the request, figures out
the correct method to
invoke, handles all of the extraction of
parameters, invokes the method logic.
And now finally, takes the return of that
method,
converts it into response body, and turns
it into JSON.
Now, this is a huge amount of work that's
going on.
And what we're going to see is that it's
actually not a lot of work for us.
Spring is doing the heavy lifting for us.
All that we're doing is telling Spring a
little bit extra
about our classes and our methods in our
classes so that
Spring can go and invoke the methods that
we want on
our objects and translate between HTV
requests and invocations of our methods.
And translate between the return types of
our methods and responses
that we're sending back that are HTV
responses back to the clients.
And what's really nice is suddenly, if
you'll remember, we had this original
setup where we were sending commands to
our application.
And then we wanted to be able to send
responses back.
And in this case, we've got a simple class
that we can think of as an
application there, Contacts Controller, is
a component of
an application that we can send a command
to.
We can specify how the commands that are
being sent, in these cases, HTV requests
with data
in them, get routed to individual methods
that we
need to invoke in order to implement those
commands.
And then we can specify how the return
types
from our methods should be converted back
into responses.
So we've come full circle on that original
vision.
And the other thing is, is rather than
living on
a single host, all of this is happening
over the internet.
So this is running in the cloud on this
side,
and this is running on our mobile client
over here.
So not only are we going and actually
creating a way of mapping
the commands that are being sent to the
individual objects that were created
to build an application, but we're also
doing it in a distributed manner
so that the client can be remote, can send
the commands over HTDP.
And we can handle those HTV commands, map
them into our objects, and
send responses back, and do all of it on
top of the HTDP protocol.