[MUSIC].
An important Java feature that we're
going to use
over and over in this course is Java
annotations.
So it's really critical that if you don't
understand Java a, annotations.
That you watch this video very carefully
and pay attention to how they work.
Throughout the infrastructure in Java that
we're going to be
using, we're going to see Java annotations
spread across that infrastructure.
And if you don't understand what
annotations are
or how they work, it's going to be very
difficult to understand the code examples
that we're
going to be using later on in the course.
If you understand Java annotations you're
free to skip this video.
I'm sure that you'll be just fine.
If you don't feel completely comfortable
with them.
I think it'd be helpful if you stopped and
took some time to watch the entirety of
this video.
So, let's dive into Java annotations.
Let's imagine that we're building an
application and
it has a method to store a video.
So, we have public, void, store.
And we're going to take some information
about that video.
Now, we might do something in here.
And let's imagine that, storing a video is
a protected operation.
We don't want anybody to be able to store
a video.
We only want people who are authorized, to
store video, to be able to do it.
So, you would imagine, we'd like to be
able to express.
To other developers, or the framework
that's running and encapsulating the store
method in it's encapsulated object, that
this is some type of secured method.
We'd like a way of expressing that, but
Java
itself doesn't really give us a way to do
that.
We could try to name this something like
store secured.
So that others that came and looked at the
method
would know that this is some type of
secured method.
But then that sort of relies on the naming
scheme.
And if there's some other entity that this
is incorporated into, it has to
do really some complex work with Java
reflection to get access to that name and.
Try to decide if it fits the naming
scheme and if we can have different naming
schemes.
And how do we tell at compile time for
example
if they make a mistake or typo in their
naming scheme.
So, we need some way of annotating this
code with
some meaningful expression that we know
about that means that it's.
Secure.
So what annotations are are these, these
little @, annotations that you see
throughout code.
And basically it's an @ sign with a
identifier.
So this is a simple annotation here.
That's been created.
That's saying @secured.
It's an, it's an additional piece of
meta-information about this method.
And it's simply declare with the @ sign
followed by some identifier.
There's two interesting things that we can
talk about with this security annotation.
One of them, is that secured, actually,
when it gets created.
Somebody has to define secure.
And the way that that happens is, they
define
an interface called secured, that has a
special format.
And that format, signals to Java that that
is a annotation that can be applied.
To some Java element, be it a class or
a method or other parts like actual member
variables.
So, we have @secured here, and somewhere
else someone has defined
a Java file that's called @secure and has
an interface in it.
And what @secured does, because it's
defined in
a Java file, it means that if we
make a typo here, Java won't recognize the
@secured and it will give us a compile
error.
So we can create naming schemes for our
meta information.
And attach them to various Java elements
with these @ annotations @secured and java
will check that it can actually find
a declared annotation that matches the
naming.
And again we can import the interfaces
that define these
annotations, just like we can import any
other Java interface.
So, somewhere earlier in this class, we
could have an import statement that
defines where exactly you can find that
particular interface defining and secure.
Then, once we've imported it, and we have
it in our naming space,
if we make a typo in it, Java will catch
it at compile time.
So suddenly we have a naming scheme that
can actually be enforced and analyzed by
our compiler.
The other interesting thing is we may not
want our meta information, our
names that we are applying to methods like
secured to be applied in the wrong place.
For example, @secured may not make sense.
This to apply to a member variable.
It only makes sense to methods.
And so what Java allows us to do is
in the definition of the interface for
@secured, we
can specify the type of Java member or
element
of the source code we want to apply it to.
So we can say @secured only applies to
methods.
And so, if somebody tries to add @secured
above a
member variable, Java will flag it as a
compile error.
So it can both check the naming as well
as the location that somebody puts one of
these annotations.
So it's giving us a type checking over
this meta information we're defining.
We can say, here is a name that's special
to us.
Here's where we expect it to show up only
on methods.
Now compiler, go and enforce that naming.
So we end up with the ability to annotate
our code and have the compiler enforce it.
The other thing that we can do, is we can
add
parameters that are essentially passed
into the annotation you can think of.
But really what that means is that they're
like attributes of the annotation.
So for example we could have an annotation
that looked like role=user.
And
in this case role in our interface would
be some method, that we define, called get
roles.
So, if we define a get role method in our
sorry.
If we define a roll method, in our
annotations interface.
So, the method, the annotation would look
something like this, for this.
It would look like.
We have an @ sign interface, secured.
We've defined our secured interface, and
this is indicating that it's an
annotation.
And then we would have just a public
string
role method that's defined in that.
And so now, certainly we can go and the
attribute role to our annotation.
And Java will check that the value that we
provide for role is of the right type.
So certainly, we can add attributes and
actual type checking, of
the values that we're providing for the
attributes, on our annotations.
And so, this structure, of annotations,
allows us to mark up our code.
By adding these naming schemes to
particular Java elements
that the compiler will enforce are in the
correct place.
As well adding different attributes to the
specific annotations to parametrize them
in different ways.
And the compiler will, will not only check
that the appropriate attributes are on.
A annotation but also that the values for
them are correct.
So if we define role here it means that
every time somebody goes
and defines this annotation they are going
to have to have the role attribute.
So, we can go and build these, these
constructs where we have an annotation
that we can now apply specific parts of
our code and attach meta information.
That the compiler checks for us and
strongly types.
And this is going to be the basis
throughout the course.
Some of the things that we're going to see
are
the frameworks that we are building on top
of, expect you
to go and place those annotations in your
code, so
that the framework can understand what to
do with your code