[MUSIC]
Typically, we don't just have data, on the
server side.
We're more building a cloud service for
mobile devices.
We typically, are building applications
where we have some data that's living
on the devices, and some data that's
living in the server's side.
And there's a constant flow of information
between the two.
So, important question is, how do we take
data, from the mobile device, send it to
the
server and using a spring controller,
extract that data
from the request, just like we could with
servlet.
With servlets we could.
We read, request parameters out of the
HTTP request object.
So how do we do the same the same thing,
with the spring control?
Well, the way that we do this, is first,
let's say we're going to have a contacts
control object and it's as we discussed
before
it's where all the contacts for a user.
But let's say, we want to allow users, to
send a search string.
They want to find a specific contact or
contacts that start with a or c.
How do they do that?
Well, let's create a method.
Let's say, we have a method called,
search
and.
Search is going to take some parameters,
which I'm going to, fill out on the next
line here, but I'm going to just leave
some space here where I'll fill these
parameters out.
And then within our method, we actually do
some work.
So, let's say for example, we wanted to
have a string.
Which is the, search string.
And then maybe we want to have, an
integer, which is a search flag,
which is a search flag, which tells us,
how we want it to match.
Do we want to match against.
The first name or the last name.
Or, maybe we want it to indicate, how
strict it should be in the match.
So, how would we go about, telling the
dispatcher servlet, how to map, the
http request parameters, to these
individual, method
parameters, for this method within our
controller.
Or the way that we do that, is first of
course, we going to have to add
an at request mapping annotation, to this
method
so that the dispatcher servlet, knows the
column.
So we will just put at under slash search.
So whenever we see slash search, in our
requests, the
dispatcher servlet is going to route it to
the search method.
No we need a way of telling the dispatcher
servlet, about
these method parameters and how we want it
to fill them in.
And then we, way, we do that, is with
at-request param.
And these are params or annotations, that
can be attached, to, individual.
Method parameters.
So for example, at request params search,
but then say go and extract the
HTB request parameter, with the key search
and map it to this, individual method
parameter.
Similarly we could say, at request param.
Flag
and the dispatcher server will
automatically go and look for an
HTTP request parameter, with the key flag
and map to search flag.
Now one of the really important things to
notice here.
Is what the dispatcher server is going to
do for us in this case.
The request for param flag, in the HT
request, is going to be stored as a
string.
So what that means is, is when the
dispatcher server
extracts that string, it has to convert it
to an integer.
In order to pass it into this method
force.
So the dispatcher server, when you map
request parameters to method parameters it
automatically figures out what the correct
target type of that parameter is in Java.
And it will do the conversion for you.
So the dispatcher server will
automatically go.
And look and say, all right.
Flag is being mapped to an integer so I
need to convert flag to
an int before I invoke the search method
with this data from this request.
And what's important to note, is all of
the validation of the type, from
that request parameter string is being
done
by the dispatcher servlet for you,
automatically.
And then it's automatically marshalling
all of that
data after extracting it, into your method
parameters.
So then your method, you can write
standard Java
code and logic code that's just OO code
without having
to muck around with the request and the
extracting data
from the requesting and converting it to
the right types.
In handling any errors that occur.
The dispatcher server does that
automatically for you, and
that allows you to separate that logic out
from
your code, which really isn't what your
business logic
in this method is supposed to be doing
anyway.
So your cloud service wants to calculate
something, it wants to do something.
It doesn't want to be worried with how
that request got to the server,
what format it got there in, how all the
data got extracted from it.
It just wants to, do some calculations on
it.
So this allows you to simplify your
methods and write cleaner, simpler
methods, by using
request parameters in the request mapping
to extract
that data and pass it into your method.