So far all the data that we've been
sending to the
server about our videos has just been
simple string metadata, but
what do we do when we actually want to
send the
video data itself which might be hundreds
of megabytes or gigabytes even.
And we want to send this data to the
server and have it stored or do something
with it.
How do we go about doing that?
Well all of the request that we've been
sending
and, and operating on so far have just
been simple
request where either the parameters were
provided in a query
string or they were URL encoded into the
request body.
But for really large sets of binary data,
things like video data
that we're uploading, we don't want to use
a URL encoded form body.
What we want to use is a multi-part
request.
We want to have the body of our
HTTP request that we're sending be
multipart encoded.
Now, what this means is, is that our
server side has to understand how to
accept multipart data, and this is easy to
do with the controllers that we've been
writing.
So let's take a look at how we do this.
So let's say we go back to our video
service controller.
So we have our video service
and it's got all of the nice spring
annotations
on it and we want to accept a video.
So let's say we have a new method which is
public you know, maybe we'll return a
[UNKNOWN] or something else.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Upload video.
So we got our request mapping up here just
like we normally
would, we've got a request, or response
body mapping for what we're returning.
And we want to an accept a parameter that
is
going to be the actual binary data for the
video.
What we can do, is we can add a parameter,
a request param,
[BLANK_AUDIO]
for, the video, let's call it Data,
and we can set its type to Multipart File.
And we'll call this Video Data.
And what this parameter is is when you
send a multipart request, it doesn't make
sense,
always, to process that request in the
same
way that you did for simple string data.
It doesn't make sense to necessarily load
it all
in the memory, and then process it in
memory.
You probably want to, you know, stream
that data in from the client and stream
it to disk as you're receiving it from the
client, or do something similar to it.
You don't want to load a multi gigabyte
video into memory necessarily
and then wait til it's all done and then
save it to disk.
It is using up a lot of memory.
You probably want to read it as you're
getting it and save it,
or read it as you're getting it and
process it in some way.
So that's what the multipart file type
gives us is
the ability to, begin streaming and doing
something with the data.
So that we're not just loading huge things
in the memory necessarily and doing
something with them.
So, what we do is we get this just
as a request param, just like we normally
would.
We just declare it's typed to the
Multipart File.
And if you want to do accept Multiple
Parameters,
you can just make this an array of
Multipart Files.
And then in our method what we're going to
do is we can get an input stream.
And you should be familiar with input
streams if you have worked with java.
From the file, so we can say video data
get
input stream,
and we can obtain an input stream from
this video data.
And then we can go off and do something
with it, like
save it to disk, or to a database or
whatever we're doing.
Sending it or streaming it to another
client, whatever we want to do.
And so the multi part file is our
connection
to grab an input string from that video
data.
We can also get the actual file name that
was provided by the client,
for that data from the multipart file
element that we're provided as a
parameter.
But this is what gives us the hook into
that data that's coming in from the
client, and allows us to grab a stream and
process it and do something with it.
And also to provide, get access to the
metadata that
the client may have provided about the
video, like it's name.
The second thing that you need to do to
enable multipart uploads to your
controllers is to configure a
multipart configuration in your
application so that Spring knows that
you're expecting multipart data and you
want to handle it.
And also to tell us some information it
needs to now
about how big you expect these request to
be at maximum.
And other things like that that help us
decide is the client trying
to upload too much data and attack me, or
is what they're doing legitimate?
So, in order to enable this, in
your application class, where you have
your configuration,
you need to add a new bean.
And, later, we're going to talk about what
these beans are doing.
But for now, just understand that when you
want to
accept multipart data, this is what you
have to do.
You need to add a method
that returns a multipart
config element, and
we'll just call this method
get multipartconfig.
And it is going to take no arguments, and
it's going to be annotated with at bean.
Now what this app beam does, and you'll
learn
about it later when we talk about
dependency injection,
is it tells spring that this is some piece
of configuration information that it needs
to know about.
And to go and call this method, get this
thing back, and then go and use that
configuration information.
In this case use the thing that's being
returned for
a multi part config element to configure
part of the application.
What this multi part config element's
going to have is
information about what you expect from the
multi part request.
So, what we do is we say multipart config
factory.
F equals, and we construct a new one of
theses.
And then we can do things like say
f.setmaxfilesize,
and we can provide some size like 2000
bytes
or whatever it is that you want to limit
the upload size to be.
This will set the maximum file size that
we want to accept,
but, a request could potentially have more
than one file in it.
So, we may also want to set a limit on
the total size of any HTTP requests that
we receive.
So we could say f.set max
request size, and provide a value for it
as well.
Finally, we just return f.create
multipartconfig,
and Spring will go and take the
information you told
it about, max file size, and request size,
and
other parameters, create multipart
configuration
that can then be used to decide what
multipart data is
accepted, how much, how big the request
can
be, and all of those other types of
things.
Now, if this code seems a little bit
boilerplate and you're worried about
remembering all of it.
Don't worry.
We've got code samples, so, how you
can set up multipart config in your
application.
And the, the truth is, is that this is
pretty much the same.
All you end up doing is needing to know
about configuring these
two things, but the rest of this is pretty
much the same.
Any time you want to accept multipart data
like video data that
you're uploading, you need to add this
block to your application.
You'll want to add an add bin annotated
method that returns of multipart config
element.
And, probably even a better name for this
would be
multipartconfig with a lower case m rather
than get multipart config.
And we'll talk about how we do dependency
injection and how this is actually used
later on.
But for now just know that if you want to
accept multipart
data, add this to your config, and this
block is
pretty much the same across all the
applications.
You just go and add it to your
configuration for your application and
Spring will pick it up and begin accepting
multi part requests from clients.