[MUSIC]
So servlets are really helpful in building
cloud base
services to talk to mobile devices, but as
we've
seen there's still a lot of work that has
to been done when a servlet receives a
request.
In particular, we have to do a lot of
data marshalling to extract parameters
from an HTP request.
So we'll typically have doGet.
We'll have some request object.
And then in our request object we
will extract information or params from
the request.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then we'll do validation on those
parameters.
And then, we'll probably construct some
java objects that use those params.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then finally we actually get to do
some work.
So there's a lot of overhead that goes
into just processing a simple request with
servlets.
All of this overhead here of looking at
the request,
figuring out what's inside of it, figuring
out if it's the
same set of data that the client isn't
sending anything, malicious
isn't sending anything that's malformed,
and there's not any other problems.
We validate that data.
And then finally we construct some
objects.
So, do some data marshalling to turn that
data into some
format, some object oriented format that
we know how to process.
And then finally we get to do work.
So this is a lot of effort.
So one way to handle this is a framework
called the
spring framework, and it provides a
specialized servlet within that framewor
called
the dispatcher servlet that can help us to
simplify a lot
of this work here that we have to do over
and over.
Now, they're other frameworks other than
the
Spring Framework that do this type of work
for us, but the Spring Framework is one of
the most popular and widely used.
So we're going to talk about it in this
course.
Now what the spring framework gives you is
it
gives us a specialized servlet called the
dispatcher servlet.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And what this servlet does is it allows us
to register one or more controllers with
this thing.
So, we have one or more controllers.
And again, these are just plain java
objects that can handle HTP requests.
But the wonderful thing about the
dispatcher servlet in
the spring framework, is that it allows us
to
stop writing all of this boilerplate code
to extract
parameters and do things in just right
standard methods.
So our controller can have simple methods
like, you know, update balance.
And what is called an update balance, it
takes an integer for example.
And whenever we send a request, the
dispatcher servlet can route that
request to the appropriate controller,
just like we do with a web.xml file.
There's a separate way of specifying
routing
from the dispatcher servlet to the
controller.
And we can do that a couple of ways, one
is through
an xml file, another is with some Java
annotations that we'll talk about.
And all of those form routing information
that the
dispatcher servlet can use just like the
web container.
So the dispatcher servlet can do a second
layer of routing after the web container
and what it does, is it does
routing to individual methods inside of
the controller.
So rather than just having a single
doGet method within this controller, let's
say that
handles get requests, we can have specific
methods that have arbitrary names like
update balance
and then we can specify that whenever a
request to a particular path or that meets
some series of conditions comes in, it
should be routed to this specific method.
Now we have a lot more routing flexibility
in the
dispatcher servlet than we do in
traditional you know, servlets.
We can do things like look at the
parameter values and do wild
card matching as parameter values or path
values just like we would in web.xml.
And then use those to determine which
individual method is invoked.
So we can do an extra layer of routing
in the dispatcher servlet based on not
only the path
of the request, but the parameters, and
not just to
a single servlet, but two specific methods
within the servlet.
So, different paths can invoke arbitrary
methods within our controllers.
So the dispatcher servlet gives us this
extra bit of routing.
But what it also does is when it, before
it invokes a
method, so if we map a particular request
path, to this particular method.
Before it invokes this method, it will
automatically look
at the parameters that that method
requires and then
look at the HTTP request and figure out if
it can extract the appropriate parameters
for this method call.
So if for example, we have an int here,
there's a way to specify that we want this
integer of this method let's say,
account-num parameter in the HTTP request.
We can say, we want you to always map the
account-num
parameter in the HTTP request to this
parameter to the method.
And then the dispatcher servlet will
automatically do all of the work to
extract the parameter from the HTP
request, look at it, make sure that it
actually is an integer, and then pass it
in and invoke this particular method.
So the dispatcher servlet can do a lot of
this extra work that we've previously
done, from extracting parameters.
The dispatcher servlet will extract them
based on how we tell
it to extract them and map them to the
individual method parameters.
It will automatically do some level of
validation.
And you can give it more validation to do,
depending on how you configure it.
But at the very least it will check that
what was passed as data in the
request for that particular parameter
actually matches the
type that you are expecting in your
method.
And then you can also view actual object
marshalling and I'll talk more about
this later but it can actually extract a
series of parameters from the request.
And automatically marshal them into an
object that get's passed into this method.
So the dispatcher servlet gives us a whole
bunch of extra routing power, as
well as data extraction, marshalling and
validation, before we actually do work.
So it's simplifies our life as developers
by eliminating all
of this boilerplate code that we would
normally have to write.