[MUSIC]
When HTTP requests come into a server they
typically
have some data that the client wants to
send along.
So we'll have, key value pairs that are
sent along with the request.
So these will be things like, the
username for a login, and the password
particularly.
Or maybe we're not sending a password
along, we're sending something else.
But, we have a series of key value pairs
or
pieces of data that are encoded in an HTTP
request.
And when we receive those pieces of
data on the server side, so when those
enter into the server and were received
at a servlet, we have to convert those
key value pairs, to the objects
that we use in the application.
So, for example, when you have a servlet
and it looks
at the request, and it's extracting the
user name and password.
And converting those into some
representation of the user.
Maybe, you have a user object.
This process of looking at the data that's
coming in, and extracting information
from it and turning it into objects, is
going to be called data marshalling.
So, this is how do we look at the data in
the incoming request and convert
it into objects or data structures, that
the
servlet is actually going to use operate
on.
This is what data marshalling is.
And this is a really important concept,
when you're building cloud-based services.
Is figuring out how do you efficiently,
extract data from requests?
How do you specify the format that, that
data should be placed into the request?
And then also if we're sending information
back tot he
clients, how dow we do data marshalling in
the opposite direction.
So, how do we convert our object back to
key value pairs?
That can go into some HTTP response, or
maybe we convert that
into some other format like JSON, or XML.
There's a whole bunch of different
formats,
that we could use that we may want
to convert this data to, before sending it
back to the client that requested it.
So, this process of taking data in, in one
format, converting
it to objects or data structure that we
can operate on.
Doing computations in order to service
your requests, and then
converting them back to some format that
we're going to send
back to the client be it, JSON or XML or
whatever it is, this whole process is
called data marshaling.
And it's a very, very important concept in
cloud services.
Another very important concept.
And this, is a process that's called
object mapping.
And you'll see this quite a bit in Java in
particular, is
that you have frameworks that can automate
this process of converting.
So, object mapping in frameworks.
Automate the conversion
of data to objects
and vice-versa.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So this is what object mapping is, is,
we've taken some data,
and then we automatically convert it
to objects, using some object mapping
library.
And there's a variety of object mapping
libraries that are available.
Things like X Stream, if you're working
with XML and Java, or things like Jackson
if you're working with JSON and Java.
And so these libraries help you, so that
you don't have to write
the tedious and error-prone code of
extracting all of these QV value pairs.
From the request figuring out which
objects they represent in that
request, and then constructing those
objects and calling getters and setters
to create the various values in that
object that you want
for the member variables, and then doing
something with those objects.
And then when you're done, taking each
getter and setter and extracting the value
you
need, and converting it back to the format
that you want to send To the client.
So, object mapping is a really important
process, and a really important tool if
you
have an object mapping library, to help
you do data marshalling, and cloud based
services.