[MUSIC]
One of the things that we have to consider
when we're building a cloud service that's
going to talk
to a mobile device, particularly Android,
is on the Android
side, we're going to have an application
or an app.
That's going to be sending response
sending request to our servers.
So this thing is going to send HTTP
requests.
And each of those requests, is going to
have an, a body within an HTTP request
body, and that request is going to go to
our cloud service, on the server side.
And it's going, to
our service.
And our service is going to have to read
this body, and extract objects out, of
that body.
Because we want to be able to communicate
from the objects.
On the device, which are going to be Java
objects in our Android app.
We're going to have to extract data, turn
them
into a request body, and then we're going
to
have to, on the service side, preferably
extract those
objects that we sent to the service back
out.
And then when the service is done, what
we're
going to want to do, is take the object or
objects.
It's the return from our service's
invocation, and
we're going to want to turn that into a
response,
that has a body attached to it, that's
going to go back to the device, and then
we're going to have to read from that
body,
and try to extract some Java objects from
it.
So one of the important considerations is
we have to think about, how do we
express whenever we go and encode objects
into a body.
How do we represent those objects and
express them?
What is the format that we use to express
objects
in an HTTP request body or in an HTTP
response body?
So, one of the most common formats for
expressing objects, when you're using the
HTTP protocol, is using a a data format
called the JavaScript Object Notation.
And it's simply a way of simply expressing
objects in
textual format, so that they can be sent
in HTTP bodies of messages,
and then on either side, converted back
into object representations.
The JavaScript object notation or JSON, is
a simple
data format, and we express an object as
follows.
We start by having a brace, and then, a
closing brace, and
within the braces, we can express the
properties, or we can think
of them as member variables and values of
an object, or another
way of thinking of it is a set of keys and
values.
So let's say we have in this object, a
value called,
or a key called Name or remember a
variable called Name.
We would then express the mapping of that
name, to
the actual value, as follows.
And then, let's say that we wanted to have
another property in this object.
We could go and we could add another one.
And we could say, class of MOOC,
and then we could say, Coursera.
And then if we wanted to have another one,
we could say, University.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then we could say Vanderbilt or Vandy.
And so, we can create a representation of
an
object, by creating the braces, and then
we simply have
a key or a member variable name, followed
by
the value for it, when we're separating by
a colon.
Now, the other interesting thing, is we
can nest the objects within each other.
So for example, maybe we would like to
express some information
about this course as an object, till it
gets embedded within My Objects.
So we might want to say Mobile
Cloud, and then we could say, that's also
going to be an object, embedded within.
We see the embedded braces.
And then we say, date.
And we could have some information on the
date, and we could say
URL, and then have some information on the
URL for this thing.
And so, we can build up and nest objects
within
each other using the j, the JavaScript or
JSON notation.
And it's a very simple format.
All we've got are a set of keys or
member variable name, colons, and then a
set of values.
Which if they're strings, they're quoted.
We can also do numeric values.
So if we had another object, that was
something like
Course.
And then we said Mobile Cloud.
And then we might want to say Enrolled.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we could say 40,000, and that could be
a valid property.
So, we can quickly build up
representations of objects,
in a sort of platform independent way
using a simple textual
format, with JSON, and have those objects
parsed as strings.
In either request bodies or response
bodies of our HTTP messages.
Another thing that we can do, is we can
have arrays.
So, for example, we could have an array
for dates.
Maybe we don't want a one date, but we
want
dates where this is going to be offered,
in the future.
And we could say, we're going to start an
array, and we could say, you know, date
one.
We could have whatever value we wanted.
Another comma, date two, and then we could
close this up.
And this is very similar to what we have
above.
It's just another value, except in this
case, rather than
our curly braces, we're just using array
notation, like we would
in Java, we're defining sort of an array
with a,
a indexing we're, we're going to define
the values within that array.
And, just, we have values in here, but we
could
just as easily have objects separated by
commas within this array.
And so, we can build up complex
structures, that we are
sending across in HP requests
and responses, using JavaScript Object
Notation.
And we'll see this is a very handy format
to express data
in, and to exchange data between the
mobile device, and the server.
Now, some of you may be familiar with XML,
and say why don't we do this with XML?
You could do this with XML, but it's very
interesting because, JavaScript
Object Notation, is much more condensed
and compact than H, than XML.
And so, there's actually been studies that
have shown
that you can measure the difference in
power consumption
on a mobile device, between communicating
with JSON and
your HTTP request and response bodies,
versus communicating with XML.
So, this is a much for efficient, both
from a power standpoint,
parsing standpoint, and sort of ease of
writing standpoint, than XML is.