[MUSIC]
Data that's sent from the clients to the
server, doesn't
have to just be embedded in the HTTP
request frames.
For example, often we see links where the
link itself has some semantic meaning to
it.
So, for example, the path that's specified
in that link, or the path that's specified
in the HP request, actually has data
embedded into it that we'd like to
extract.
And this is, for example, a typical thing
you'll see in
a rest architecture, which we'll talk
about later in this course.
So lemme give you an example, let's say.
Rather than just sending a request where
we're embedding all
of the search strings into the HP request
parameters to
search in our contacts, let's say, for
example, we wanted
to be able to have links that looked like
slash search
a.
And that would return the list of all
contacts that started with a or
slash search ab, and it would give us all
the contacts that started with ab.
And why we, we want to do this?
Well, it's usually easier to share a link
that looks
very nice and clean, which is just
embedded in the
path, rather than having a question mark
in all of
these request parameters falling in off
the end of it.
Or in sharing a post, obviously isn't
something you can do.
You can't just share a link for an HTTP
post.
So, often we want to have nice clean
looking links that are easy
to access in the browser and make sense
for sharing or other purposes.
So there's a easy way to do this in
spring,
to extract data that might be specified in
the request path.
Rather than in the request parameters.
And the way we do that is first we have
to create a request mapping that is to
something variable.
So we're going to say at search.
And then we're going to do something
interesting here.
We're going to add a bracket.
And we're going to say the string that
we're searching for.
And then we'll close this off.
And what this is going to the Spring
Dispatcher Server
to do is to look at the request path.
And, anything that is search slash any
string, or any
integer, or anything, is going to be
routed to this request.
So what we're doing here, is we're
specifying a path variable.
And that's what the
open braces and closed braces around this
string.
Is just defining a variable and the string
doesn't represent the type here, I want to
know.
This is just an arbitrary identifier that
I'm given for this variable.
So I'm saying look for a request, where
the path has this format, slash
search slash some path variable that I'm
looking for that has a arbitrary value.
Now what we then need to do is tell the
Spring Dispatcher Server, how to
extract those path variables that we care
about, and get them into the method
parameters.
So what we do, is we say @PathVariable,
and then we can say, string.
And what that will tell spring to do is
automatically extract, this, string from
the path, and, convert it, into, this
parameter, for the method call.
So what this allows us to do.
Is to have some of the data embedded in
a request parameter, and some data
embedded in a PathVariable.
And we can combine and mix and match
these approaches for extracting data from
the request.
We can have some data that lives in the
PathVariable.
Now we can have all of the data living
in the request past and extracted via the
PathVariables,
or we can have all of the data living
in the request parameters or any mixture
of them.
And all of them serve the same purpose, to
tell the Dispatch
Servlet, how to extract information the
client has embedded in the request.
And convert it into the arguments that are
needed to the, be passed to the method.
So if we want to go and change our
architecture and change how
the data's passed from the client to the
server, all we have to
do is go and update these variables I mean
these annotations specifying
how the method vari, the method parameters
are mapped by the Dispatcher Server.
So we can change this PathVariable to a
request parameter or this
request parameter of PathVariable and we
can do that over and over.
And it separates our logic from the logic
of extracting
the information from the request or from
the request path