[MUSIC]
We've re-factored the video service that
we
built with Servlet to use the Spring
framework.
And what we're going to see it that Spring
vastly simplifies our lives, particularly
with respect to getting
data from the client and insuring that
it's at
least minimally validated and in a format
we expect.
And also for getting that data into
objects
that we can actually use and do something
with.
So what we're going to see is in
this version, before we had the Servlet
container
that was directly talking to our Servlet,
which was the video Servlet.
This time, the Spring Dispatcher Servlet,
which we're not even going to see
in our code, is what the client is going
to be talking to.
And then that Dispatcher Servlet is going
to
be actually routing requests to our video
service controller.
So we have a video service controller
object.
And this is just a controller, is just a
Java object
with the Spring app controller annotation,
which is what you'll see.
But the key thing to focus on here is how
much simpler this version of the service
is going to be.
All we're going to focus on writing is
really this video service down here.
There's not going to be a web.xml anymore.
There's not going to be any Servlet that
we have to write.
Spring's going to provide all of that for
us.
And what we're going to focus on is our
actual logic
to do something with the data we're
getting from the clients.
So let's take a look at this, video
service controller.
So, if you go to the project, it's in the
video controller and retrofit project.
The first thing we want to go and look at
is
in the source main Java folder, this video
service class.
And if you open this class up, what you'll
see
is, is just a standard Java class that
implements an interface.
And this interface is one that we define.
It's nothing special from Spring.
So this is just a Plain Old Java Object,
or POJO,
so nothing is, is, we're not being
required to inherit from anything.
The only thing that's different is we're
going to mark this
class with an annotation that tells Spring
that it's a controller.
In this case it's an @Controller
annotation.
So this little annotation right there is
giving us a huge amount of power.
It's telling Spring, here is a class that
doesn't inherit from anything that you
know about.
But you need to look at it and use it like
it's a controller.
So this ability to mark up standard java
objects with annotations
and provide metadata on them that
otherwise we would have to
express somehow through inheritance or the
implementation of interfaces, sort of
gives us greater flexibility in how we
implement and create our classes.
So this simple Java object that's
annotated with @controller is going to
be discovered and loaded by Spring just
because of the simple annotation.
If we look at the video service, we'll
actually see this isn't a remarkably
simple class.
Just like in the Servlet, we're going to
create a list that we're store the videos
in.
And this is just a standard array list,
nothing special.
And then lay, lower down in the file we
have two methods that are the
equivalents of the methods that we had in
the Servlet for do git and do post.
In this case we have an add video method.
So, one of the things to immediately note
is
that spring isn't enforcing any naming
conventions on our methods.
We've got methods that make sense for that
object, add video.
So, the fact that we're not being forced
to inherit
from anything in particular and that we're
not being enforced
on any particular naming conventions in
this example, it allows
us to write an object that makes much more
sense.
You look at this object and you understand
what the add video
method is going to do, even if you don't
have the source code.
It's much more explanatory.
Now, what we'll see is that this method,
because it doesn't have to follow any
naming
conditions, it does have to provide some
metadata
to Spring to tell it how to use it.
So the first thing we see is the
annotation @requestmapping.
And what this does is, the @requestmapping
tells Spring that this
is a method that we want you to route some
HTTP request into.
So, whenever you see a request where the
path is
video service path, and if we see this
constant just expands to /video,
whenever you see a request sent to /video
that is of
type post which we see here, you should
invoke this method.
So, we're, rather than expressing do git,
do post and
changing our method to take a Servlet
request and a Servlet response, so that
we can read from the request parameters as
strings, and get a
writer, and write a response back out,
it's just a primitive string.
We're certainly, actually writing a method
that looks like a standard
method that you would write in Java to do
something useful.
Now, where it also gets interesting is the
next parameter, or
the next annotation, @RequestBody, which
is attached to the video parameter.
So we're expecting this method to take a
video as input.
And what we need to do is we need
to tell Spring where it should get that
video from.
In this case, what we're doing is we're
telling Spring, that we
want you to go and look at the body of the
HTTP request.
And we want you to automatically try to
convert that body into a video object.
And there's a lot of different ways, that
you can
tell Spring how to convert a body into an
object.
By default, however, Spring knows how to
convert
JSON, or the Java Script Object Notation,
into objects.
So, if we have a request body that has a
JSON object
encoded into it, not URL encoded, but just
JSON directly in the request body.
The, controller can automatically have
that data extracted as an object
by Spring and then passed into the method
that we've mapped with @RequestMapping.
So we don't have to worry about going and
figuring out how we take
some you know, request Servlet request,
and
extract parameters from it, and extract
the object.
We can just tell Spring, we want whatever
is in the body of
that request to be interpreted as a video
object, and extracted for us.
And Spring is doing this all behind the
scenes for us.
So, if we see now, this method is simple.
Even if we didn't have HTTP requests, we
could still interact with
this method and create video objects and
use the, the logic in it.
So it's also decoupling us to some degree
from the idea of HTTP requests.
And then we're just adding the video to
the list of videos that we've created.
So our logic is incredibly simple.
We're focusing only on the things that we
care about.
The taking a video and adding it to the
list.
And so if you compare this to our original
code, which is in the video
Servlet, look at all the work that we had
to do in the video Servlet to handle
the post request, to get all the
parameters
out, to validate some minimal information
about them,
and then to actually construct a video and
then finally, down here actually add the
video.
All of this was overhead for this tiny
little method call down here.
But if we look in our current version with
the controller,
everything is about this one thing that
we're actually trying to accomplish.
So suddenly we can focus on the logic the
we actually care
about this taking a video and adding it to
the list of videos.
We don't have to focus on the logic to
construct
that video that were going to add to the
list.
So Spring has taken over that work of
unmarshalling all of that data
from the request body into an object that
we can actually operate on.
The other interesting thing to note is
this @responsebody annotation.
You'll notice that we're not taking an
HTTP response
that we can write to any more as a
parameter.
We're not getting a writer and writing out
what we want
to go back to the client or setting the
content type even.
All we're doing is saying @responsebody,
which tells Spring that I'm going to
return an object, or a value of some kind
and, whatever the return type of this
method is, I want you to take it and
covert it back into a response body
automatically, using the same conversion
that you used to take the parameter in.
So in this case, what this means is, is
that whatever Boolean we return, Spring
is automatically going to convert it into
a
JSON representation and return it to the
client.
So we don't even have to worry anymore
about taking
our return value and writing it back to
the client.
We just returned something and tell Spring
you have to go figure out how you
make whatever we return into a H2D
response that can go back to the client.
And as you can imagine, if you threw an
exception, spring is
automatically going to be smart and figure
out, oh, this method threw an exception.
I need to return an error 500.
Similarly, you notice we're not returning
the error
400 anymore if the client provides invalid
data.
What's nice is if the client doesn't send
valid data,
that can be converted into a video, Spring
is automatically
going to tell the client and generate that
error 400
for it, to tell it that it sent an invalid
request.
Then if we go down and look at the get
request, again we see
a request mapping, again to the video
service path, which is /video, and this
is the equivalent of the do get method
that we saw before except that we are
scoping this request mapping specifically
to the get method of HTTP requests.
But, the method itself is not polluted
with any change in our logic.
We're just adding metadata that Spring can
find.
And in this case we have a simple method
that takes no argument, so
we're not even going to look at the data
that's in the request that we're getting.
And instead, all we're going to do is
return a list of videos.
And here again, we're using the
@responsebody to tell
Spring go and take whatever list of videos
I returned to you
and automatically convert it back into a
JSON list of
objects, that can be returned to the
client, in the HTTP response body.
So Spring is doing the heavy lifting here
of setting
the appropriate content type for the
response, converting your list
of objects into JSON, encoding those,
those, that JSON into
the HTTP response, and then sending it
back to the client.
But, in your code right here, you're not
seeing any of that.
You don't have to go and pollute your
code.
You're just working with standard Java
objects that look much more natural than
they did when you were trying to write all
of this special logic for HTTP.
So, we've decoupled how we access these
methods, and how we
encode, and, and decode requests and
responses into just simple logic.
We're just adding some metadata to our
class,
and suddenly spring does all the work for
us.
If we go and look at our video object and
see
that we still get the member variables, we
still have a constructor.
The only thing that we've done new is
we've added a default constructor that
takes no parameters.
And this is just to help the underlying
Spring framework infrastructure, be
able to instantiate our objects and then
set all of these values programmatically.
Now it's possible to also have a, not have
the default constructor but it
just takes a little bit more annotation
that I decided to skip for this example.
Now the final thing that we need to note
is we don't have a web.xml file anymore.
We've removed that extra piece of
infrastructure that
we had to have and understand how to
build to tell the Servlet container about
our
Servlets and how to map requests into
them.
So how does Spring figure out where our
controllers are and how they should be put
together?
Well that's what this application class is
that we're going to look at.
So, the application class is now our entry
point into our application.
We simply have a public static void main
method just like we would
with other applications that we wanted to
be able to have, the executable.
And then we ask Spring to go and run our
application.
Now, what this is going to do is Spring is
going to
look at our application in the
configuration that we're expressing in it
at.
And then automatically, in this case,
create
a web container, put a Dispatcher Servlet
in that web container, and then
auto-discover
all of our controllers in our application.
So what this, this application class
primarily serves to do at this point is
to provide these annotations to Spring,
telling
it information about how to construct our
application.
So the first annotation that we see up
here is @configuration.
And all of this is, is an annotation
that's provided to Spring, to
tell it when you are expressing
configuration information in a class.
So Spring will look at this class and
know that it should interpret it as a
configuration.
The next thing we're doing is we're saying
@EnableWebMvc.
And what this does is it tells Spring to
set
up a web container with a Dispatcher
Servlet inside of it.
And that, that Dispatcher Servlet should
be configured
to be able to route requests to
controllers.
So this one annotation is doing a huge
amount of work.
It's going and setting up a Dispatcher
Servlet, making sure that the web
container
knows about it, and that the web container
will route requests to that Servlet.
So, this is almost taking the place, this
one line, of our entire web.xml file.
The next line is telling Spring that we
want you
to go and look in this Java package for
all
of the objects in there that are important
to Spring
or annotated with Spring information that
it needs to know.
So in this case, the @component scan is
telling spring
to go and automatically look at this
package down here.
And I'm going to close this up to make
this a little
easier to see this controller package
which is specified right here.
And discover any controllers that are in
here.
So this one line tells Spring, no matter
how many controllers you have in this
package, go
and look through all the classes and
discover
any class that has controller and set it
up.
And then the final one is
@enableautoconfiguration.
And that tells Spring that if I have asked
for any type of,
of objects that I need for dependencies,
to automatically go and configure them.
And we'll talk more about dependency
injection later.
But these four annotations on this
configuration class
go and set up an entire web container.
They create the Dispatcher Servlet that we
need to route requests to our controllers.
They automatically scan the appropriate
packages
that we want to discover our controllers.
And then they automatically configure our
controller
with any dependencies we want them to
have.
So, if you look at this application and
the source code for this, it's actually
remarkably simple.
It looks like a bigger application than it
is just because
there's so many comments in here
describing what the different lines do.
But the actual logic is remarkably simple.
This configuration is a simple class
called
application that has four annotations with
it.
And a main method that delegates to a run
method in Spring application.
It's incredibly simple.
The video service class now is really just
a list with two
methods that either add an object to the
list or return the list.
That's it.
And then our video class is just simple
Java object
that can be constructed and given some
information about a video.
So, what you can see, is that we've,
in, vastly simplified the logic for this
video service
by building on top of Spring and then it's
starting to do a lot of the hard work
and boilerplate code with respect to how
we
take HTTP requests, turn them into objects
and invoke
methods that we care about, return objects
from those
methods and then convert them back into
HTTP responses.
So if we think back to that original
vision, where we want to allow our clients
to essentially send commands to our
objects that
are sitting on the server through the
network.
So this is sent via HTTP.
Suddenly we've got all of this covered for
except that so
we can solely focus on writing logic that
can receive commands.
And we can, as we'll see in a minute, do
the same thing on the client side, so that
all of this work to take HTTP, transport
the commands
and get the responses back, we can hide a
lot of the complexities of the
underlying HTTP, protocol by using a
framework like Spring.