[MUSIC]
The dispatcher servlet can pass much more
sophisticated information than just simply
extracting parameters from the HTTP
request
and dumping them into method parameters.
You can actually extract entire objects
from an
HTTP request and pass them as method
parameters.
And by objects I mean something more
sophisticated than just a string or an
integer.
Actual custom Java objects that you
specify for your own classes.
So let me give you an example.
How would we use this?
Well, let's say our search method, we
wanted to have a
more sophisticated search capability, and
to do that we want to create
a search object that would specify the
parameters of the search
and hold all the data needed to do our
more sophisticated search.
And let's just assume, we have a sample
object which has a first name of
the person that we're searching for and a
last name, so we can have two queries.
We can have some string that will match
against the first names
and some string or expression that will
match against the last names.
And maybe we had mode so we can
do regular expression matching versus non
regular expression matching.
And we wanted to have a sophisticated
search mechanism.
Well we would want to be able to take an
HTTP request and we want to extract all of
this information and then convert it into
a
search object, which the search method
would operate on.
Now of course, we could spell out all of
these individual things that
we contain within the search object as
individual method parameters of the search
method.
That kind of limits our flexibility,
because every time we wanted to
add a new parameter, we'd have to go and
change the search
method, and add the appropriate request
mapping to it, and the actual
request parameter or path variable, or
however we're going to extract this
information.
So, what we'd really like to do is have a
single object that is passed
into search and then search can do what
ever it needs from that single object.
So how do we do that?
Well in Spring what we can do is we can
create
and say well we're going to have a search
object as a parameter.
So we'll call it S.
And so when the dispatcher servlet calls
search, search is going to
expect that one of its params is just a
search object instance.
So how does it go about, how do
we go about telling the DispatcherServlet
to convert and
assume that all of the parameters within
the
HTTP request are actually an instance of
this object?
And the way we do that is with an
annotation called at @RequestBody.
And what this annotation does is it tells
it for this particular parameter, search,
S, we want you to take all of the HTTP
request parameters and
automatically convert them to an object of
this type.
So because this is a search object the
dispatcher
servlet knows that when it sees
@RequestBody, then it's
going to take all the HTTP request
parameters and automatically
convert them to a object of the type
search.
So we got our search class here and there
are various automatically
preconfigured HTTP objects
inside of spring that take care of math
and these HTTP request params into search.
And these are HTTP message converters, so
whenever an @RequestBody
is seen, an HTTP message converter,
and I'm just going to abbreviate this to
make it easier to fit on the board
here, is used to look at all of the
request parameters and then
automatically construct an object and map
all of those
request parameters to the various method
parameters of the getters
and setters, as well as the member
variables within this object.
And then once it's constructed and it's
completely well
formed and ready, it then passes it into
the method.
So this is another very important and
powerful
aspect of Spring is this automatic data
marshaling
from HTTP request parameters into objects
that you
want to be passed to your individual
methods.