Hello, and welcome to Part 4 in the module
on Patterns and Frameworks for Synchronous
Event Handling, Connection establishment
and Service initialization.
In the previous parts of this module, we
first described the reactor and
Acceptor-Connector patterns, which are
patterns that abstract away from event
handling details in order to allow
application processing to be decoupled
from service, initialization, and
connection establishment.
We then talk about the ACE Reactor
framework and how it implements the ACE
mechanisms for the Reactor pattern.
And then we talked about how we could
apply the ACE Reactor Framework to our
JAWS Web Server to provide a very simple
event-driven solution.
In this particular part of the module,
we're going to go ahead and describe the
ACE Acceptor-Connector framework.
And then, illustrate how we can apply that
to a different version of the JAWS Web
Server.
This different version is going to be a
slightly different path through our
pattern language we've been describing.
In this particular path, we're going to
still use the wrapper facade pattern in
order to abstract a way from the tedious
and error-prone and non--portable system
programming methods by using nice,
cohesive, more modular object-oriented
wrapper facades.
We're going to apply the Reactor framework
to be able to decouple the even
dispatching and detection into
multiplexing logic from the processing
behavior of those events.
And we're going to join this up with the
Acceptor-Connector pattern and the ACE
Connector framework in order to be able to
get even further accessibility and reuse
from our infrastructure.
So as you'll see, even though the
processing logically do is almost
identical to what we did in the previous
solution, it's even less code we have to
worry about to write the bug maintain and
evolve.
To motivate the ACE Acceptor-Connector
framework, let's first kind of step back
and talk about different types of
connection-oriented network application
roles.
There's two roles that are most important.
The connection role, which determines how
apps establish connections.
And then there's also the communication
role, which determines whether an app
place the role of a client or a server or
both.
The connection roles are typified by being
either active or passive.
The active side is the Connector part.
The passive side is the Acceptor part and
then the communication role is the part
that interacts irrespective of whether it
was started as active or passive role.
It's also important to realize the
fundamental asymmetry that exists in these
connection-oriented environments.
So servers often, but not always, play the
passive accept role where they listen on a
particular port for someone to connect to
them.
Conversely, clients often, though not
always play a more active role, they are
going to initiate a connection to a
particular port that a server is listening
on.
By factoring out these different roles and
responsibilities, we can greatly reduce
the amount of tedious and error-prone code
that has to be written by application
developers and has to be ported to
different platforms has to be evolved and
maintained and so on over the life cycle.
And in general, if you don't have to write
it, don't write it, leverage it from some
place else much less problematic and
expensive down the road.
So let's talk now about the
Acceptor-Connector Framework in ACE.
The classes in this framework decouple the
connection establishment and
initialization of cooperating peer
services or, or service handlers in a
networked application from the processing
performed by these service handlers once
they're actually connected and
initialized.
So you can imagine there's a variety of
reasons for doing this kind of decoupling.
It reduces the amount of code.
And it also gives you more flexibility
from a design point of view.
For example, sometimes it's the case that
the servers are the active initiators of
connections, sometimes the client's are
the active initiators of connections.
In a web server environment, the clients
are the active initiators; in other
environments, say network management, it
might be the servers that do that.
By decoupling these roles, we can make the
service handler behavior be independent
from whether they're established actively
or passively, which means more reuse,
better architecture, easier to explain,
easier to evolve.
In the Acceptor-Connector Framework, the
applications will typically subclass from
the ACE Service Handler base class.
The ACE Service Handler class itself is
actually a subclass of other classes as
we'll talk about.
It, itself, inherits from things like ACE
Task, which inherit from other parts of
ACE we'll get to later.
When you inherit from a service handler,
there's certain methods you typically
override, in order to be able to kind of
clean things up clean up the, the service
handlers when they go away.
And you also typically override some
methods having to do with how you activate
the service handler.
[inaudible] and activation here
corresponds to the different ways you want
it once it's been created.
Some of those different activation modes
include reactive processing as well as
various types of concurrent processing,
such as multithreading, using thread per
connection, thread pools, multiprocessing
a processor pool, or a process per
connection, and so on and so forth.
These kinds of decisions can be left as
late binding decisions in the way which
about your system.
Naturally, the, the particular roles and
classes in ACE and its Acceptor-Connector
Framework follow along with the roles and
responsibilities that are designated in
the Acceptor-Connector patterns.
So it's really easy to follow on with the
framework if you know the pattern.
Here is a quick synopsis, of the key
classes, in the ACE Acceptor-Connector
framework.
Ace Service Handler, is the core piece
that, that embodies the application or
service specific processing logic.
That's where the interesting business work
gets done.
Then we have the ACE Acceptor, which is
the part that's a factory that creates.
The service handlers and gets them
connected when a client goes ahead and
connects to the acceptor.
And then, on the inverse side, we have the
ACE Connector, which is the part that
initializes a service handler when it
connects it to a corresponding acceptor
that's running somewhere else.
And we'll talk through these different
examples and you'll see lots of ways in
which they could be customized and applied
for various use cases.
Take a look at this URL if you'd like to
learn more about this particular
framework, and of course, there's even
more discussion in the various books, the
POSA2 book and the various books on ACE.
Let's now do a little bit of, of a deep
dive into the capabilities and structure
on the ACE Service Handler class.
This class provides synchronous and
reactive data transfer capabilities, and
as you can see, it has a bunch of
interesting things going on in terms of
how it's associated with other classes in
ACE or other classes you might find.
One of the things that the ACE Service
Handler provides is an inter-process
communication or IPC endpoint that's used
to communicate with its peer connected
service handler.
And as it turns out, this particular peer
is going to be connected by the acceptor.
The service handler also codifies certain
best practices related to reactive network
services.
So, out of the box, if you do nothing else
and you create a service handler subclass,
it's going to be able to register itself
automatically with a reactor and be driven
by a reactive callbacks that we talked
about before.
So, it registers itself with its
corresponding reactor when it's created.
And then it can also be used to, to shut
things down and clean up its resources,
including its IPC mechanism when its going
to be destroyed later in its life cycle.
The service handlers can also participate
with other concurrency models that are
provided through various frameworks and
patterns that are used with ACE, things
like Active Object, Half-Sync/Half-Async.
So we'll often end up spawning pools of
threads or we'll connect together service
handlers with active objects that
themselves contain pools of threads, in
order to be able to get more concurrent
behavior if a reactive approach alone
doesn't work scalable or correctly in the
environment that you're trying to use it.
And it gets this capability because it
inherits of something called ACE Task.
And we will talk about the ACE Task
Framework in the next module in next
modules in the course.
Not right away, but we'll call, come to
those later.
The ACE Service Handler basically gets
these capabilities from ACE and it gets a
number of capabilities.
In fact, it gets concurrency In queuing,
synchronization, dynamic configuration,
and event handling, from other parts of
ACE.
This is a good example of how frameworks
can give you quite a bang for your buck,
or from your non-buck if it open source by
being able to associate canonical control
flow, and canonical domain specific
structures and funcitonality into the
infrastructure, so you don't have to write
that yourself.
From a commonality and variability
perspective, the ACE Service Handler is
going to handle the variability of the
inter-process communication mechanism and
the synchronization mechanism by a common
API.
You can come along and customize this by
instantiating templates or subclassing and
overriding certain hook methods in a very
convenient and consistent way.
Here's a simple illustration that shows
how you can use the ACE Service Handler
with the ACE Reactor.
This is what you get out of the box if you
don't do anything to the contrary.
Typically, an ACE Service Handler will
register itself with an ACE Reactor when
it's been created by an acceptor or a
connector.
And, then, the ACE Reactor framework will
automatically call back to the handle
input method in the service handler when
some kind of data arrives on an endpoint
with the service handler indicated it was
interested in knowing about.
The Reactor framework can also be
responsible for initiating graceful
shutdown and destruction of service
handlers when they are no longer needed,
for example, when the underlying
connection is shut down.
Once again, offloading a lot of the grubby
work from application developers.
The ACE Acceptor class is a factory that
plays the acceptor role in the
Acceptor-Connector pattern.
But keep in mind, we're not really talking
much about connector in this particular
set of slides, because web servers don't
really do connector roles, but there's
lots of other literature and example you
can learn about the connector portions in
the ACE Acceptor-Connector framework if
you're so inclined.
So the ACE Acceptor class decouples
passive connection establishment and
service initialization logic from the
subsequent processing performed by a
service handler once the acceptor has
created and initialized it.
Once again, there's a bunch of interesting
things going on with this class in terms
of its dependencies on other parts of ACE
and other things you provided via
templates and subclassing.
One thing it provides for example is a
parameterized passive mode, IPC endpoint
that can be used to listen and accept
connections from peers.
And you can provide that as a template
parameter as we'll see when we look at the
code a little bit more.
There's also a number of hook methods it
defines using the Gang of Four template
method pattern in order to be able to
automate certain steps that are used to
create service handlers, accept
connections into them and then activate
them to run with the appropriate type of
concurrency or reactive processing model
which we'll look at.
By inheriting from various parts of ACE
for, by inheriting for example from the
ACE service object class which itself
inherits from ace reactor and it's the ACE
event handler class.
You can use these acceptors with the
reactors, you can link them in
dynamically.
There's lots of things you get as part of
the framework that you don't have to worry
about writing yourself.
From a commonality and variability point
of view, the ACE Acceptor is going to
handle the variability of inter-process
communication mechanism and service
handlers in a common way.
So we'll say by using template
instantiation and subclassing you can deal
with this variability with a common
interface, which makes it really easy to
do plug and play types of extensibility to
your software components.
Here is an example that illustrates the
common flow of control between and ACE
Reactor, an ACE Acceptor, and sometimes a
service handler that was parameterized
into the acceptor.
What typically happens is that an acceptor
will be registered with the Reactor for
accept events, which is one of the types
of events that it knows about.
And when an accept event occurs, the
Reactor will dispatch the acceptors handle
input hook method.
This hook method on acceptor actually
plays the role of the template method in
the Gang of Four pattern as it plays the
role of the template method in the
pattern.
And then it calls out to a number of hook
methods itself to do the various steps in
the acceptance algorithm.
These three steps are making a service
handler, creating one as a, as a factory
method, accepting the service handler,
that is accepting the connection from the
client and then activating the service
handler.
And that activation step can be used to
decide what type of reactive or concurrent
processing will be done by the service
center.
Once again, by default, it uses reactive
processing, it registers back with the
Reactor.
Let's now take a look at how this
Acceptor-Connector implication could be
applied to JAWS.
This will give you a high level view, then
we'll look at some of the code.
From a high level view, this looks almost
identical to the example we'd seen before,
when we talked about the purely reactive
based approach.
The only real difference here is that
rather than defining an HTTP Acceptor or
an HTTP Event Acceptor, and an HTTP Event
Handler.
These are now done for us by the various
classes in the Acceptor-Connector
Framework.
So we'll have an HTTP service acceptor
shown here, which inherits from ACE
Acceptor, register itself with the
Reactor.
When a client connects, the Reactor calls
back to the handle input method of the
acceptor, which does that template method
process that we talked about before to
create the appropriate service handler,
which then registers itself back with the
reactor.
Everything is purely reactive at this
point.
When the client sends a get request, the
Reactor calls back to the handle input
method on the registered HTP Service
Handler.
And that goes ahead and cracks open then
message, finds the appropriate content,
memory maps it, and then sends it back to
the client.
And we'll look at the code in just a
second.
But the good news here is that this set of
canonical interactions is very, very
stylized.
Once you understand it for one type of
application for a web server, you can use
it for many, many other things.
It have nothing whatsoever to do with Web
services or HTTP protocol processing.
So let's take a look at the code and the
more detailed design.
This example's going to show how to use
the acceptor and it's service handler
parts of ACE in order to implement a
reactive Web server.
As you'll see, there's even less code than
we looked at before, because the ACE
Framework is doing almost all the heavy
lifting .And you just have to fill in a
couple of blanks that deals with the
processing of the actual protocol that
corresponds to what we're building, which
is a web server.
So let's start by looking at an HTTP
Service Handler which inherits from ACE
service handler and it's got a couple of
methods there.
As you can see, when it inherits from a
service handler, it fills in that template
to use the SOCK stream, wrapper facade,
and something called the null synch, which
means there's no, no concurrency taking
place in this example.
We'll see later how to override that.
And then what it does is it defines the
handle input method.
This is really the only piece of
application specific processing logic in
the whole implementation.
This is what of course is going to get
called back by the Reactor when the get
request arrives from the client.
And as you can see, it does the canonical
processing we've looked at several times
before.
It gets the path out of the get request
that comes in.
It memory maps that path into the
appropriate part of the file system and
stores it in memory.
And then, it goes ahead and transmits the
content back to the client in one
operation using the mechanisms in ACE to
transmit exactly n bytes.
This business logic is really the only
thing we have to write.
Now, naturally in real life, you would add
a lot more capabilities to do prep servlet
processing.
You might do more sophisticated caching
operations.
You might do various things where you're
going to add additional capabilities,
concurrency and so on.
But for now, let's keep it simple, just to
focus on the patterns and how they get
applied.
This then is the basic service processing
logic for the main program.
We're leveraging a lot of things we've
done before.
We're using our ACE Acceptor and we're
parameterizing it with the service handler
we just wrote, and the ACE SOCK Acceptor
to accept the connection that comes from
the client.
We abstantiate this new HTTP Service
Acceptor into that helper class called
Reactor HTTP Server that we looked at
before.
And then the rest of our logic is very
straightforward.
We instantiate the appropriate templates.
We derive things and use this as we talked
about.
We go ahead and create the ACE Reactor in
order to be able to drive the event loop.
We create an instance of the HTTP Server
Daemon passing in the reactor pointer, so
it registers properly.
It can be used to clean things up
appropriately when everything shuts down
later and then we just run the server
event loop and away we go.
So the nice part about this is there just
isn't a lot of application-specific logic
here.
We're customizing the framework.
We're combining the realizations of those
patterns we talked about before.
As we'll also see, this is going to be
used for much more powerful concurrent
mechanisms and much more flexible,
dynamically configureable mechanisms later
and we'll get to that as we explore
alternative paths through our pattern
language.
So, to summarize this particular module,
this particular part of the module the ACE
Acceptor-Connector Framework decouples
JAWS, connection establishment, and
service handler initialization, from the,
the protocol processing for HTTP.
This separation of concerns allows us to
reuse large parts of our solution be able
to push that in to the infrastructure, so
we don't have to worry about it.
Somebody else can maintain it.
Someone else can optimize it.
Someone else can debug it.
Someone else can document it, and so on.
So we have the generic reusable framework
portion that you see here.
And if we can come along and just
specialize a few pieces The business logic
for processing the get request, as well as
the part that's going to be doing the
acceptance of the connections and that was
really no real code.
We were just customizing templates and a
few helper classes.
One of the things you'll also see by our
solution approach here is we're combining
both white box and black box reuse.
Some parts of the white box reuse come
from the use of these hook methods in the
template method that drives the acceptor's
key algorithm steps to create a service
handler accept something into the service
handler and then activate the service
handler.
Those are done in the white box like way.
You can inherit from ACE Acceptor if you
want to customize any of those steps to do
different things.
We'll see some examples of that later.
But at the same time we also get black box
reuse by being able to plug in various
template parameters, so that you don't
really have to know a lot of the details
of how things work.
You just have to know what type of
signatures that are expected by the
templates that use these template
parameters.
So the end result is a very powerful
solution without a whole lot of code to be
written and it gives us yet one more piece
in our ever expanding pattern language for
high performance web servers.
First, at the heart of these framework
designs are commonality and variability
analysis.
I've talked about a lot of stuff that took
years to evolve to figure out what was
fixed and what varied.
We used to go back repeatedly and vary out
designs as we came up with new insights
about commonality and variability.
So what you're seeing here is the product
of a lot of thinking and a lot of
re-engineering and a lot of refractoring.
The key is not just to focus on the
specific examples of what ACE is doing,
but tho think more broadly about a
methodology for building software that's
extensible, and contractible, and
subsettable for your own application
environments.