Hello and welcome to Part 2 in the Module
on Patterns and Frameworks for Synchronous
Event Handling, Connection Establishment
and Service Initialization.
In the previous part of this module.
We described the acceptor connector
patterns, and explained how these patterns
can be used effectively, in the context of
our web server.
We're now going to talk about a way to
implement these patterns, starting with
the reactor pattern.
And to do this, we'll describe the way in
which the Adaptive Communication
Environment or ACE, implements a framework
that embodies the patterns we just talked
about.
There of course are many other ways to
implement the pattern for a reactor, we're
just going to focus on one, to give you a
more detailed understanding of how this
could work in practice.
So let's motivate why we need this in the
first place.
This is a little bit of a recap, but it
provides the foundation for what we're
about to talk about.
Historically when people have developed
event driven applications They program
them directly to the native operating
system mechanisms.
This is particularly true if you're doing
systems programming.
If you're doing applications programming,
these days you're probably using higher
level frameworks and tool kits.
But if you're building systems code, then
you're usually using sockets or select or
other kinds of event demultiplexing and
mechanisms.
Unfortunately, when you program like this,
it tends to tightly couple a lot of parts
together, which means whenever any changes
are made you have to spend a lot of time
going through to code, performing surgery,
rerunning regression tests, having to open
up your source control system.
Usually finding all kinds of mistakes over
time, shaking out those error legs
throughout a long, protracted quality
assurance cycle.
As another consequence is that developers
spend way too much time rewriting this
lull of infrastructure code.
And believe me, it's very tedious and
error prone.
I've written way too much of this code in
my own life, and once I learned the magic
of patterns and frameworks I resolve to
help other people not having to rewrite it
again from scratch.
The good news is a lot of these codes is
very generic.
If you spend some time to refactor it, if
you spend some time thinking through the
various implication of design construct,
structure, conanical bahavior, flow
control and so on.
You can abstract a lot of this out.
And turn into a framework.
And that's exactly what we're going to
talk about ehre.
So the ACE_Reactor framework provides a
set of classes, that allow event driven
applications to react to events from a
range of different sources of events.
Different kinds of I/O events.
Sockets, files, terminals, local
inter-process communication and so on.
Time-based events.
Signals.
Anything that is event oriented you can
typically connect together in a common
interface through a framework that we use
for the reactor.
Applications typically inherit from
something called ACE_Event_Handler which
is a base class, and they override the
hook methods of this base class.
And then they fill in various service or
application specific processing behavior.
That can leverage the reasonable
infrastructure for an event.
These classes of course are designed in
accordance with the reactor pattern.
Here are some of the key classes that the
ACE_Reactor framework provides.
We'll talk about them one at a time.
It provides something called ACE time
value, which is a class that normalizes
time.
And let you do various kinds of relational
and arithmetic operations on time values
so you can compare them and add them and
subtract them in a clean and portable way.
It also provides something called the ACE
timer queue, which is a base class for
whole families of different timer cube
management mechanisms.
Various things using timer wheels and
timer heaps and timer lists and so on, in
order to be able to dispatch time-out
handlers very convienently and
efficiently.
There's also, of course, the ACE event
handler which is the core for being able
to be called back when various kinds of
things happen.
Either time-based events, signal-based
events or I/O based events.
And finally we have the ACE_Reactor.
Which is essentially the facade.
It's the interface.
It usually uses the bridge pattern to
provide an abstraction.
In order to make it possible to register
event handlers, remove event handlers.
Run the event loop.
Start timers, stop timers.
All kinds of other different types of
things that you might want to do here.
You take a look at this paper, it gives
you some more information about the, the
ACE reactor framework and how it
implements the particular pattern we've
been describing.
One of the things you'll see is that the
heart of the reactor framework is this
concept of object-oriented event handling.
So let's talk a little bit about why you
would want to do this.
If you take a look back in the early part
of event driven frameworks and event
driven communication, things like the X
Windows Toolkit.
Those were typically implemented in C not
in C++, or Java or some object oriented
language.
And as a result, when callbacks occurred,
they typically called back on functions,
and those functions were typically
associated somehow with some type of data.
And this data would either be global data
or it would be passed in as pointer to a,
to a structure or some kind of other
relational database information that is
associated with the function callback.
And by doing this it's just a little
crufty.
It's a little error prone.
The connection between the functions and
the data is a little bit diffuse and it's
somewhat hard to understand.
In contrast, with the reactive based
approach we're talking about here, we can
more cohesively associate the data and the
functions that operate on that data
through the use of an object oriented
event demultiplexing interface.
So, what we'll have is an event handler
base class that you can sub-class, and
then you can have your state.
Associated in the subclass.
And in the various methods that you
override, can access that state.
And it's all much more cohesive and
localized and easier to understand, easier
to maintain.
Let's take a look at the ACE_Event_Handler
class just to give you a feel for how this
works.
Keep in mind that other implementations of
the reactor pattern will do.
Slightly different things, there is the
java implementations, their implementation
in other environments as well.
The core idea here is to provide hook
methods for each of the different types of
events that may occur.
As you can see in this diagram we've got
input events, things like incoming
connections or incoming data, we have
output events which you typically used.
For learning when a connection has no
longer been flow controlled.
And now you can go ahead and send without
blocking.
We have exception events which typically
deal with things like out of band data
delivery.
We have timeouts.
We have signals.
We have other kinds of things as well.
So those are the main hook methods that
you would subclass and override, depending
on the kind of thing you're dealing with.
This particular approach also centralizes
how event handlers are cleaned up when
they're no longer going to be needed.
We handle close method that you will fill
in to delete the object or shut down any
resources it allocated dynamically when it
closes down.
The event handler also contains a pointer
to the reactor it's associated with, and
that makes it easier for an event handler
to figure out how to Remove itself, how to
update its event registration masks, that
we'll talk about shortly.
And basically, keep charge of its life
cycle by knowing the reactor it's
associated with.
It's kind of a parents point if you will.
Another nice thing you can do is, because
we use classes, with virtual methods.
Is it's easy, as I mentioned before, to
associate state.
With the, the hook methods.
So here we have an example we'll talk
about later, which is our HTTP event
handler which inherits from
Ace_Event_Handler.
And it has some state, it has the
connected sockets that it's using to
receive data from a client, and it
overrides methods like handle input.
To figure out how to process the incoming
data associated with that stream.
And it's all nice and compact and
encapsulated, and part of the same
abstraction.
So, if you look at this from a commonality
and variability point of view.
The ACE_Event_Handler allows us to have a
common interface that is open to
extensibility for the different kinds of
events you might want to handle.
I should mention very briefly, by the way,
that these events that the Event Handler
deals with are fairly coarse-grain
systemsy kinds of events.
Input events, output events, signals,
timeouts.
In a real application, you typically have
more domain specific events.
Thinking about Android, for example, you
have a whole slew of life cycle events for
on create, on destroy, on start, on stop.
And usually you would take the reactor as
a core piece And then build, in a layered
manner, more fine grain type of event
management on top of the core reactor
framework.
Let's talk a little bit about some of the
types of events an event handler hook
methods.
When an application registers an event
handler with a reactor, it has to indicate
the type or types of events it wants to be
notified about.
Here's a simple example we'll talk about
later.
When an HTTP event handler is created and
initialized, it turns around and says
reactor, please register me, this, to be
notified when read events occur using a
read mask.
A read event would correspond to the
arrival of a get request from a client.
There's a whole slew of different kinds of
event types that can be handled by the
reactor.
There's Read Events, there's Accept
Events, there's Connect Events, there's
Output Events, called Write Events,
Exception Events and so on.
Where going to be focusing primarily on
Read Events and Exception, and Accept
Events, not Exception Events, Accept
Events in our examples here.
And I'll show you as we go through this
how these are applied.
They're basically provided by a bit mask.
And you can or the bit mask fields
together.
In order to be able to register for
multiple different types of events.
And that allows one event handler to
handle many different kinds of things.
If you choose to use that particular
approach.
There's also return values that the hook
methods will give back to the reactor
framework, after they finish processing
whatever it is they're doing when an event
shows up.
For example, here's the handler input
method that gets called back on the
HTTP_Event_Handler.
We'll look at this in more detail later,
but what it's essentially doing is it's
extracting the URI from the incoming
stream and then it goes ahead and memory
maps a file that corresponds to the
content.
Designated by that URI and then it
transmits file back to the, to the client.
When it's done, it returns various values
and it indicates whether it succeded or
failed.
So we get back certain values to say if
this worked or it didn't work.
Here are the different values that get
passed back.
So we have the zero value, which means
everything worked fine.
Keep me registered.
I'd like some more callbacks in the future
when my handles become ready again,
please.
If you get back a minus one, it says,
something went wrong or I'm done.
Please call my handle closer method and
shut me down.
And if you give back a greater than one,
that indicates that please re-dispatch me
again after you've handled all of the
other various sources of input in this
particular pass.
The key point here is that when things get
shut down, the reactor knows how to call
the handle close hook method on an event
handler and that can be used to clean
itself up, often by deleting this as we'll
see later on.
Let's now talk a little bit about the
ACE_Reactor Class itself.
This is the, the public interface, the
abstraction that you will interact with as
a user of this framework.
It does a couple of things.
It centralizes event loop processing.
It hands, has a method called
run_event_loop().
It also has another method called
run_reactor_event_loop(), used for a
slightly different purpose.
And so, when you want to run the event
loops, those are the methods you call.
It also has some kind of way of waiting
for activity to occur, by using low level
I/O multiplexors like select(), or poll(),
or other mechanisms.
And these are used then as part of the
demultiplexing process to figure out
what's happened, and which event handlers
to call back.
The event handler callback process is done
by the reactor, when the underlying
multiplexor returns.
And it basically takes a look and sees
what happens.
Correlates that to the handlers registered
for those types of events.
And then it goes ahead and dispatches
their hook methods.
The appropriate ones, based on what events
occurred.
And these hook methods, of course, are
then the things that do application- or
service-specific processing logic in order
to carry out the work designated and
associated with those types of events.
From a variability and commonality point
of view the reactor provides a common.
Interface for being able to do several
different types of variability.
Of course, it can handle different kinds
of event handlers by subclassing from
event handlers we talked about before.
And it can also shield the rest of the
application from the details of the
low-level, synchronous, I/O multiplexers
and event demultiplexing logic so you can
plug in different mechanisms.
And we'll talk more about that in a
moment.
There's a number of different
implementations of the ACE reactor
framework that come bundled with ACE.
Ace uses the bridge pattern in order to be
able to separate interface from
implementation.
And there's over a dozen different
reactors for all different flavors of
event loops, user interface tool kits and
so on.
Some of the core types of reactor
implementations that are most commonly
used are the following.
The ACE_Select_Reactor which uses select()
and it allows one thread to take its time
to dispatch event handlers that come back
from events that select will dictate and
indicate have arrived.
It's got something called the ACE_Thread
Pool_Reactor or TP_Reactor.
And that implements something called the
Leader/Followers pattern, which we'll talk
about later.
And that actually allows a pool of threads
to take turns accessing the underlying
select mechanism.
We'll talk more about that pattern in a
little bit later part of the course.
It's also got an implementation called the
ACE_WFMO_Reactor or the Wait For Multiple
Objects Reactor.
And that uses a very interesting system
call that's provided by, by windows that
allows you to wait for things to happen on
an array of handles.
And it, it allows you to wait for many
different types of events on Windows, not
just sockets.
You can wait for various types of
synchronization events, you can wait for
various kinds of threading, user
interfaces files, overlapped I/O and so on
and so forth.
And in the last one we'll talk about just
briefly here is the ace dev poll reactor
which uses a couple of specialized .
Various mechanisms that Solaris and Linux
implement, using Dev_Poll and Dev_Epoll
respectively, which are designed to be
more scalable than select(), when you have
large numbers of clients connected.
So to summarize this particular section,
the ACE_Reactor Framework is designed to
simplify the development of event-driven
apps.
And the way, one way it does this is by
encapsulating the low level I/O
multiplexing and synchronous event
demultiplexing logic within the framework.
So it's shielded from you.
You don't have to worry about how to write
that code, maintain that code, optimize
that code.
There's all kinds of clever optimizations
that are baked in to the implementation of
the ACE_Reactor.
And then it also facilitates greater
reuse.
Of course there's more reuse of the
infrastructure for event management, but
there's also going to be more reuse of the
components you develop that live on top of
this.
And we'll see more examples of this as we
look at more sophisticated examples of the
patterns and frameworks that we're going
to be talking about shortly.
One of the other key things we do is we
separate out the mechanisms.
Of the infrastructure for event handling,
from the various policies and protocols
and algorithms that are implemented on top
by the subclasses that derive from the
ACE_Event_Handler.