Welcome to Part 3 in the Module on
Patterns and Frameworks for Service
Configuration and Activation.
In previous part of this module, we've
described the Component Configurator
pattern.
And also talked about the ACE Service
Configurator Framework that implements
this pattern in a portable fashion across
a wide range of operating system
platforms.
Now, we're going to talk about how we can
apply the ACE Service Configurator
Framework In the context of another path
though our JAWS pattern language for web
server implementations.
This particular path will build on what
we've done before.
We will again use the Wrapper Facade to
provide us portability for different types
of interprocess communication mechanisms
that we might encounter on different
platforms.
Will also provide a way to use the Reactor
Framework to handle event detection, event
demultiplexing and event handler
dispatching when events occur.
And we'll also provide the Acceptor
Connector pattern and its framework
realization, in order to handle connection
establishment and service initialization.
This time however, we're going to go one
step further and we're going to add in
support for the Component Configurator to
allow us to be able to dynamically
configure certain aspects of our solution.
We're going to do this by modifying, to
just a small extent, the previous example
we used for the acceptor connector
framework solution.
If you recall that solution, it had a
single thread of control that' used the
ace reactor, and used the Acceptor
Connector capability.
And when connections came in, those were
handled by the Acceptor, the HTTP Service
Acceptor.
And passed off, to create an HTTP service
handler.
And then wen get requests showed up, those
things were handled by the service
handlers.
And all of this was driven by callbacks
from the reactor itself.
In this particular variation where we
extend our existing solution, we're going
to be able to add in the capability to
link or unlink the service implementation,
the web server implementation, dynamically
from a script.
Let's first start by talking about how we
might arrange the overall architecture of
our revised solution.
We're going to begin by defining a new
class.
This class is going to be called reactor
HTTP service adapter.
And that name should give you an
indication of where we're headed with
this, to some extent.
This particular adapter class is going to
inherit from ACE servers object.
Which means it can be linked in
dynamically under control of the service
configurative framework.
There are a number of hook methods we can
then fill in to dictate the way in which
objects of reactor HTTP server adapter can
be initialized.
Finalized, suspended, resumed and queried
to give you information about what kind of
capability it provides, what port number
it lists it on and so on.
Also notice that what we do is we're able
to reuse our previous reactor HTTP server
template.
And the nice thing about this is we were
able to apply the Gang of Four Adapter
pattern.
In order to be able to leverage what we
had already written.
In terms of reactive and acceptor
connector based server capabilities for
our web server.
While adding in the capability
transparently for dynamic configuration.
And you'll see how this unfolds as we go
through the discussion.
Here's a sequence diagram that kind of
illustrates the step involved here.
Rather than configuring our solution
statically, which it what we'd done
before.
We've linked everything together with the
main program.
Now, we're going to configure this
dynamically under control of the Service
Configurator framework.
And what this framework's going to do is
it's going to read a configuration script
that we'll look at shortly.
And have this script inform it how to link
in a DLL that contains a factory that
creates a reactor HTTP server adapter
object.
And then this thing will be registered
with the reactor.
And the processing can take place over
some period of time.
And when we're done with it, we can go
ahead and shut down this particular
object.
And have it unlinked and removed from
memory altogether, if we happened to
choose to do that.
Let's take a look at how we might
implement the constructor for this
particular obstruction.
It turns out the constructor in this case
is really the init function.
This is a good example of a, of a factory
method or a virtual constructor as
described in the Gang of Four book.
So the init hook method for a
Reactor_HTTP_Server adapter is going to be
called back by the server configurator
framework when it decides that we're going
to initialize this object dynamically.
By this point, by the time this method
gets called back, the object will have
already been created.
And its implementation will have been
dynamically linked in from a dll.
When the init method is called, it turns
around and it creates the appropriate
Reactor_HTTP_Server, with the appropriate
acceptor.
We'll look that in just a second, that's
really not that much different from what
we did before.
And this particular object then will go
ahead and, and be handled by the reactor.
And the, we're going to be using the
singleton reactor in this case just to
keep everything simple.
In practice, you could make your own
reactors if that was important for what
you're doing.
If everything goes well, we return to 0,
which says we are correctly initialized
and that object will then be registered
with the service repository so it can be
Used later and managed it's life cycle can
be managed dynamically.
If something goes wrong, however, we
return to minus 1, which says oop, things
failed.
Please shut everything down and clean it
all up, and unlink this particular file.
Let's take a look at a couple other, other
life cycle methods for the
Reactor_HTTP_Server adapter.
The fini method is what's called when
we're going to shut things down and what
that does is it goes ahead and closes the
server and that will go ahead and
terminate and free up any memory that was
allocated when this was actually created
initially.
And then things will be unlinked, after
fini finishes The service configuration
framework will unlength the DLL if it was
linked in dynamically.
There's a couple of other life-cycle
method shown here.
We have suspend and resume and as you can
see what they do is they use the reactor
in order to be able to unallocate or
temporary suspend the handle That we're
listening on for incoming requests.
So from that period of time after you're
suspended to when you're resumed, no more
requests will be handled.
Here's an interaction diagram that
illustrates some of the steps that are
taking place as these interactions are
going on.
As always, it's a little hard just by
looking at source code To get a good
feeling for how the dynamic interactions
are taking place.
So a sequence diagram is a good way to get
a feeling for that.
We're going to do a couple things here.
We're going to statically configure a
component, or a service called a service
reporter.
And this is a general purpose useful tool
that can report out to the outside world
or some administrator.
What services are actually configured at
any given point in time into an ACE
Service Configurator framework managed
server.
And so this is just a helper class, we're
not going to talk much about it, just
imagine it's something that we could use
to keep track of what's actually going on,
to monitor what is the state of the
running server.
We're also going to be able to dynamically
link in the particular implementation of
our Reactor_HTTP_Server adapter.
And we'll see how we can change this over
time in a subsequent discussion.
Here's the main program that we'll use to
drive everything we're talking about here.
This is a generic main program.
It is intended to be useful as the
baseline for many different kinds of
services and applications.
In fact when you look at it, you'll see
that there is really nothing here that has
anything, whatsoever to do with web
servers.
What it does is it goes ahead and defines
an instance of this service reporter which
is statically linked, just to illustrate
how static configuration works.
And then it goes ahead and opens up the
service configurator, which will then read
its script file and carry out all the
directives in the script file.
We'll look at the script file in a second.
And after that script file is done, all
the services will be linked in and
initialized.
And then we'll go ahead and run the event
loop of the reactor.
And from that point onwards, everything
will be driven as callbacks using the
reactor pattern.
Here's the particular file that we might
define to implement some of these pieces.
As you can see here we're going to
instantiate an instance of the
Reactor_HTTP_Server adapter using our HTTP
server or service acceptor that we defined
in the acceptor connector example.
And this particular type def will then be
used to tell the framework that it's
possible to dynamically link items of this
particular type.
And that is important so that the symbols
are exported properly with whatever
platform specific details are needed for
symbol export from a dll or shared object.
Here is now an illustration of the service
config file we might start out with here.
Noticed that it does a couple of different
things.
It illustrates how to statically configure
the service reporter.
So that basically says this has been
linked with the main program, now just go
ahead and initialize it to bring it into
existence, what its virtual constructor
its init method.
And then we also say dynamically configure
the web server implementation.
This is the one that's the Http server
game that we talked about before.
And what this definition does here is, it
says, go and link in the HSD dll using
whatever platform specific suffix is
important for your platform.
Find a factory function inside that dll
called make_HTTP_Server_Daemon() call that
factory function, get back something
that's a server instance, a service
object, call its init method passing in
some information.
And the information that''ll be passed in
this case actually can be read using
various environment variables that you set
up when you go ahead and run your
programs.
So you can dictate how these things are,
are going to be executed and configured
based on the environment variables in
which you run these applications.
These particular variables which might
include the port number, for example, will
be passed to the init method when it runs.
That will be used to indicate, say where
the web servers should listen for incoming
client connections.
And after everything works, and assuming
the init method doesn't fail, then the
service object is registered in the
service repository, under the name,
HTTP_Server_Daemon.
Here then is some discussion of how we can
go one step further.
So what I showed you here was how we might
bring an object, a web server object, into
its existence when a program starts to
run, at, in installation time or launch
time.
We're now going to talk about how to
reconfigure things as the system is
actually running without having to stop
what's already going and restart all of it
in a statically compound and statically
linked sets.
So to do this, let's first talk about a
limitation about previous solution, our
previous solution had
run_reactor_event_loop() that could not
easily be terminated gracefully.
It would just keep running and the only
way to shut it down would be to kill the
process which might end up leaving things
in some indeterminate state.
Log files might not be flushed properly to
cache, the file system might not be
flushed to disc properly and so on and so
forth.
So let's take a look and see how we can
improve upon this.
What we're going to do is we're going to
make a new svc.conf file that has a
different set of directives.
And then we're going to instruct the
service configurator framework to go
re-read the service configurator, service
config file, and carry out the directives
that are part of that.
[unknown].
One of the first things we'll do is we'll
shut down temporarily this particular
server but other things that might have
been running could continue to run and the
process is not shut down just the service
is taken out.
We will then go ahead and restart the
service and we're also going to start some
special object called a shutdown a
Sever_Shutdown service.
And this service shutdown service, this
Server_Shutdown service, will be used in
order to gracefully shutdown our web
server based on various commands we can
give it from an administrative interface
or even from the svc.conf file itself.
So let's take a look at how we might
implement some of these various pieces.
Keep in mind that all of what Iu'm talking
about now could be devised and added after
the original server had been launched and
was running and handling requests.
Here's the server shutdown service, which
is an ACE service object, an inheritance
ACE service object, and it has a couple of
interesting things.
It has an init virtual constructor that
goes ahead and spawns a new thread of
control and runs a controller object and
we'll talk about what this controller
function does in just a moment.
It then also has a fini method which, when
called, will create an instance of
something called a Quit_Handler and then
pass that to the reactor via it's notify
pipe.
The notify pipe is used to indicate to a
reactor to, to do something sort of in a
out of band path through the code.
Even if it's already blocking, waiting for
IO to occur on other sources of input.
And then we define a macro that says, hey
this particular service, the
Server_Shutdown service, can be linked in
dynamically.
Here's the controller function.
I've mentioned before this runs in a
separate thread of control spawned by the
ACE thread manager, which provides
portable thread spawning on different
operating system platforms.
And what this does is it goes ahead and
Creates a quit handler object, which we'll
look about, look at in just a minute, and
then it runs a loop waiting for someone to
type quit in on the console and when
someone types in quit, it goes ahead and
passes that quit handler object to the
reactor via it's notify pipe.
Let's now take a look at how this is going
to work.
The quit handler is an ace event handler,
so It has all the various ACE hook
methods.
In this particular case, the two that we
care about are the handle exception method
and the handle close method.
When you pass a an event handler object to
the reactor by it's notify pipe, by
default it's handled exception method is
called.
As you can see, in this particular
example, the handle exception hook method
shuts down the reactor event loop
gracefully.
Returns minus 1, which causes the
handle_close method to be called.
And that goes ahead and deletes itself.
So it cleans up all the memory.
And this allows us to shut things down in
a graceful way.
Its okay to delete this in this particular
context because we don't have anything
that depends on that state after this
particular point.
Notice by the way we also make the
destructor private to ensure we can only
allocate instances of the quit handler
dynamically.
This is just a good C++ idiom to know
about if you want to enforce dynamic
allocation of classes.
Here is that particular sequence diagram
illustrating how some of these various
steps will work.
We start out by getting rid of the old
implementation out with the old and then
we bringing in the new we bring back in
the server the HTTP Daemon server object.
And then we bring in the Server_Shutdown
service object, both are configured in
dynamically.
So, to summarize, a picture that
illustrates how everything looks by the
time we're done reconfiguring our web
server.
It now looks roughly the same as before,
with respect to the HTTP processing, using
the acceptor connector and reactor and
wrapper facade capabilities we discussed
before.
But now, it's got one additional piece.
It's got another thread of control, that
runs this controller function.
And this controller function can be used
to pass a quit handler.
To the reactor to tell it to shut itself
down and clean everything up.
So to summarize this particular section,
the ACE service Configurator framework
makes it possible to configure and
reconfigure our services for web
processing for service reporting, for
shutting things down gracefully, and so on
and so forth, in a way where you can make
changes very late in the design cycle.
If you take a look at the diagram here you
can see how we went from our initial
configuration that was driven by the
directives in the original service config
file, to our new configuration which was
dictated by the directives in the new
service config file.
And you can do this, of course, in other
ways with other services.
I'm just illustrating one small piece.
Moreover, you could also even get further
fine grain.
You could go ahead and have different
pieces of the web server modified
dynamically as well.
For example, under different
circumstances, you might want to change
the way in which the caching mechanisms
would work.
Least recently used, least frequently
used, those policies might differ over
time.
Based on run time load information you
would only know after the server had begun
to run.
So to, to sort of summarize the lessons
learned from what we've discussed so far,
we can use the Service Configurator
capabilities in order to be able to build
our web server out of smaller pieces or to
have multiple different implementations of
web servers developed independently and we
can link these things together
dynamically.
The result is that we can make our
decisions at the right time and we have
enough information to make an informed
design and implementation choice and it
also allows us to be able to pick things
that make the most sense depending on the
context in which we run it.
So this is a very powerful framework.
Obviously not everything should be done
according to Service Configurator,
protocols and Service Configurator
policies.
Some things have to be statically
allocated mission critical or safety
critical code, may not be able to afford
the luxury of changing dynamically because
of security policies or safety policies.
But there are many systems where the
ability to upgrade the behavior of the
system on the fly can make the solutions
much more flexible and tuneable for the
environment in which they run.