Welcome to part 2, of the module
discussing patterns and frameworks for
concurrency and syncronization.
In the previous part of this module.
We talked about the active object pattern.
Now, we're going to describe the ACE task
framework, which can be used to implement
the active object pattern.
As well as other patterns for concurrency.
The classes in the ACE task framework
provide a producer-consumer concurrency
model that can be used to associate one or
more threads of control with a message
queue and other state associated with a
service or an application object such as
methods, fields, other kinds of data.
Typically application classes will inherit
from the ACE task base class, override its
methods and these methods are then called
back by the ACE task framework in order to
be able to decouple the thread in which
invocations are made from the thread in
which these invocations are actually
executed in one or more methods of
control.
Naturally the, the classes in this
particular framework are guided in part by
the active object pattern and related
patterns.
Let's talk about some of the various
classes that are part of the ACE task
framework.
One of the first classes we'll discuss is
something called the ACE message block,
which is essentially a composite that
allows you to put together.
Messages made out of building block parts
that can be chained together for various
types of efficient encapsulation and
de-encapsulation of messages that may end
up flowing across networks, for example.
Another capability in this framework is
the ACE Message Queue class which is
essentially a doubly linked list of ACE
message blocks That can be used to
in-queue and de-queue messages, either, in
a, synchronized way, between multiple
threads, or simply used as a regular
message queue within one thread of
control.
The next part of this, is something called
the ACE thread manager, which is a helper
class that can be used to portably spawn
one or more threads of control.
On different operating system
environments.
And then the last piece in this framework
is something called the ACE task class
itself.
And this is the primary unit that's used
to be able to queue messages, run various
service processing operations concurrently
and[UNKNOWN] for subclasses to inherit And
customize its hook method, fill an
additional state and in general run things
in a concurrent, various concurrent
models.
Take a look at this URL for more
information about ACE task.
And of course this also appears in the
book on C++ network programming.
With ACE in frameworks.
So let's talk now about the ACE task class
itself, we'll talk about the ACE message
queue class later.
The ACE task class brings together a
number of different things.
It has a message queue that can be used to
decouple data and requests that come in
from one thread From the time when they're
processed, and the thread in which they're
processed, by some other threads or
threads later.
You can take an ACE-task object and you
can activate it.
Which means 1 or more threads will then
start to run.
And these threads, threads can then run in
the background and process the requests
that come to them via the message cue.
The hook methods that ace tasks provides
can be selectively overridden in order to
be able to handle various application or
service specific concurrency and queuing
disciplines and models.
By inheriting from a service object which
in turn inherits an ACE event handler, you
can use instances of ACE task both to be
linked dynamically, as well as to be run
by callbacks reactively from the, the
reactor and we'll see how we use this a
little bit later when we generalize the
application of this framework to other
more complex and currency patterns.
From a commonality and a variability point
of view, an ACE_Task hides the variability
of concurrent processing and queuing by a
common API.
With a certain set of templates and a
certain set of hook methods you override
and customize in various ways Let's talk a
bit about each of these hook methods.
There are 4 of them that are important to
understand.
The first method is, is very simple.
It's the open method.
And it's essentially a form of a virtual
constructor.
And it's used to be called to initialize
an ACE task when it starts to run.
And the most common thing it does.
Is it turns around and calls activate in
order to convert the object into an active
object, and I'll show you how that works
in just a moment.
Another very important method for ACE task
is the put method.
And this method is used to pass a message
from someplace else.
Perhaps another ACE task, perhaps some
other part of the software, like the
reactive layer for example, and pass that.
Message to the task and then the task can
figure out what to do with it.
It might chose to perform the work
immediately or it might choose to enqueue
the work and then run it later in its
service method.
The service method.
Typically runs in one or more threads of
control that execute in the background as
part of the active object pattern.
And these service method calls will wait
for work to show up on the message que,
which is synchronized, and when work shows
up, perhaps being put there by someone
else, then it, the service hook method
removes the message.
Figures out what the work request is,
performs the work, and then perhaps goes
back to waiting for the next message to
show up on the message queue.
The final hook method we'll talk about
here is the close method.
It's purpose is simply to be called back
when the thread executing the service hook
finishes and it gives a chance to clean up
anything that might need to be cleaned up.
You will have as many calls to close as
there are threads that are running the
service methods as part of the active
object.
And there are some mechanisms you can use
to figure out whether you're the, the last
hook method to be called the last close
method to be called when the last thread
exits from the active object.
Let's talk now about how you actually go
about activating an ACE task.
So when you call the activate method to
make it become an active object, several
things happen.
First let's talk briefly about when this
might occur.
We'll talk shortly about the thread per
connection, or TPC HTTP handler.
And that's going to use activate to create
a single thread of control for every
connection and every get request that
comes to the server.
Later, we will also talk about another
variant in our pattern language, that's
the thread pool HTTP task, which be part
of the Half-Sync/Half-Async solution.
In this case we actually spawn a pool
threads, perhaps 8 threads.
Which we could also use through activate.
So activate gives us tremendous
flexibility to spawn different numbers of
threads that'll run in the background in
an active object.
When you call activate, what actually
happens under the hood, is that it uses
some mechanisms available in ACE.
It goes ahead and calls the ACE thread
manager spawn method and that in turn will
reach down into the low level operating
system portability layer and call whatever
OS specific thread creation routine in
needed.
Which in turn will create a stack to run
the thread on and passed into that, that
thread function will be the address of the
task itself.
The thread start function is something
called service run.
And as you can see here on this particular
diagram, what service run does is it plays
the role of an adapter.
To take the task object that past in and
then call it service hook method back in a
new separate throttle control.
So that's how you make things run
actively.
Naturally it's quite easy to port this to
other platforms, which already done for
you, of course by ACE.
So you can easily port this to run on
POSx, you can port it to run on VXworks.
Other environments that have different
models for threading.
It's also worth just noting briefly that
this way of doing things is not unlike the
way that Java threads work.
In Java threads, you call start on a
thread in order to be able to create a new
thread under the hood, and then it's run
method is called.
Likewise with ACE task, you call activate
on ACE task object.
And that creates a new thread or threads,
and then you could have their service,
hope that its called on that object.
The main difference between a job of
thread and ACE task is that its task can
spawn a pool of threads.
As opposed to one thread.
And secondly an ACE Task can also have a
message queue associated with it.
So it can process and store those requests
and do various kinds of patterns like
active object or Half-Sync/Half-Async.
So to summarize this particular discussion
about the ACE Task framework It provides a
nice, extensible object oriented
concurrency capability that can spawn
threads in the context of an object, so
it's an object oriented concurrency model.
And then it allows you to be able to
transfer and queue messages between the
different threads.
You can use this particular framework for
various things, we're going to focus first
on using it for active objects, where
we're trying to decouple the thread that
invokes an operation from the thread that
runs the operation.
And we'll be using a subset of the full
blown active object pattern to do this,
because that's going to give us just the
features we need without incurring
additional complexity or overhead.
And then later, in a different part of
this module, we'll come along and show how
we can use the ACE task object oriented
concurrency model for a more sophisticated
concurrency pattern called
Half-Sync/Half-Async.
And this will allow some parts to remain
synchronous or reactive, and then we'll be
able to connect those things up.
With the various threads and a pool of
threads managed by an active object, So
you'll get a chance to see this framework
in a couple of different contexts.