Welcome to Part 4 in the Module on
Patterns and Frameworks for Concurrency
and Synchronization.
In earlier parts of this module, we
started by describing the active object
pattern, then we discussed the ACE task
framework, which can be used to implement
Active object and some other patterns.
We then illustrated how you could apply
the ACE task framework with the ACE
acceptor connector and reactor frameworks
in order to implement a thread per
connection version of our JAWS web server.
And now, we're going to describe the
Half-Sync/Half-Async pattern, which builds
upon some of the things we've talked about
earlier.
Let's first start by talking about the
motivation for why we want to improve opon
thread per-connection.
Thread-per-connection is certainly an
improvement from a performance point of
view, on a purely reactive solution that
we had before.
And it's also going to have lighter
weight, less overhead characteristics
relative to the, the activator based.
Process per request or process per
connection model that we'd also talked
about earlier.
But there are some downsides.
If you have an environment where you've
got large numbers of clients, and you may
have very bursty data traffic, you can end
up in situations where you've got hundreds
or thousands of threads being spawned to
handle the various connections.
And if you only have a limited number of
cores at your disposal, four, eight,
twelve, having thousands of threads
running around really doesn't give you
much of a boost.
In fact, it's probably going to take a lot
of extra memory.
It's going to end up requiring a lot of
extra work by the operating system to
manage.
All those internal thread queues and keep
track of all the resources and so on and
so forth.
The thread stacks, etc.
So what we'd like to do is find a way to
be able to get concurrency but perhaps
without paying quite so much overhead,
especially in ways that really doesn't
help advance the performance of our
system.
So to do this, we're going to apply
something called the Half-Sync/Half-Async
pattern.
And we're going to use this pattern in
order to be able run our HTTP get request
processing in separate threads of the
control.
But we're going to bound the number of
threads that we allocate to keep them
closer to the number of CP user cores that
we may have at our disposal.
In general, the Half-Sync/Half-Async
pattern helps to decouple asynchronous and
synchronous service processing in current
systems.
And the goal is to both simplify the
programming model without unduly reducing
performance.
So let's first start by talking a little
bit about the structure of this pattern
and, and how it's been applied.
This pattern is often applied historically
in operating systems.
People often implement operating system
kernels using this pattern.
The kernel processing is typically driven
by asynchronous callbacks, at which don't
block.
There's often not more than one or a
handful of threads of control in the OS
kernel to keep things efficient.
And then when you get up to the
application process level, then those are
able to block.
You can block on read calls, you can block
on right calls, and so on.
And in between those things, there's some
kind of queuing layer that's used to
mediate interactions between the a,
interrupt driven asynchronous kernel, and
the more synchronous process, more
civilized programming model, that you get
up the user space.
The sockets layer is a good example of
such a queuing layer.
You also see this pattern used in many
modern user interface toolkits.
For example, in Android, you typically do
your user interface processing in the main
thread, in one thread of control, and you
can't afford to block that thread for more
than a very short period of time.
Or you'll get some kind of application not
responding dialogue popping up.
So if you want to do longer running
operations you spawn threads and you run
those as background processing and then
you have the main thread coordinate with
those other threads.
Well both of these examples are very nice
because they illustrate the core
structural elements of this pattern.
So let's talk about those structural
elements briefly.
At the bottom of this is the so-called
Async or Asynchronist service layer.
This is driven by incoming events.
It could be driven by call backs, it could
be driven by signal responses, it could be
driven by interrupts, etcetera.
And the characteristic of this layer is
that there's only one thread of control,
one stack and so you can't afford to block
for any length of time or you'll starve
out all the other sources of events that
happen to reside at this layer.
As we'll see, this is often used in a
reactive way because it's got many of the
same properties that we have with an
asynchronous approach.
On top of the, the Async approach but
beneath the next layer up is something
called the queuing layer.
And when the Async layer is done
processing the incoming events to the
point where it might have to block to do
anything further.
It sticks the request onto a queue in the
queuing layer.
That queueing layer is then used to
service the various threads or proceeses
that run in the synchronous service layer.
And this is the layer where you can have
multiple blocking threads or processes
that sit there waiting for work to come in
on the queue.
And when the work comes in, then they can
go ahead and do their own thing without
worrying about perturbing or interfering
with other things taking place in other
threads or other processes.
So that's the base, basic structure
relationships between the various layers
in this pattern.
You can take a look here for more
information about this pattern.
This also appears as a very detailed
description in the POSA2 book.
Lets take a look at the dynamics of this
pattern which may help to explain some of
the interactions between the different
layers.
So in this approach, the Synchronous
services can run concurrently in multiple
threads of control or processes that can
block and make it run concurrently both
relative to each other.
As well as to the processing that's taking
place in the Async layer.
So, typically you might do the event
handling logic down in the Async layer
perhaps using some kind of reactive-like
approach.
And that won't block for any length of
time.
When that is done processing an incoming
request.
That comes from a source of events.
Then it will typical enque that onto the
message que in the queing layer.
And then one or more threads or processess
will wait on that que, pull the request
off and then run those things to
completion at their leisure without
concern for wheather they're stealing or
starving.
Anybody else out because they have their
own threads, they have their own
independent instruction streams and their
own resources and stacks and so on.
So, let's see how we can apply the
Half-Sync/Half-Async pattern to our JAWS
web server.
And first, we'll talk about how we can
apply the pattern, then we'll talk about
how this pattern could actually be
understood by combining other patterns.
So, let's first assume we have some
bounded number of cores at our disposal.
And so, we would allocate some bounded
number of threads that would be maybe a
factor of two larger than the number of
cores.
Doesn't hurt to have some extra threads
because if one thread is blocked on I/O,
other threads can continue to run.
What we're trying to avoid here is an
unbounded number of threads.
I'd say a thread per request or a thread
connection, which could get unwieldy in a
very dynamic and bursty environment.
Each thread in the Synchronous layer is
now able to block, either because of flow
control or it's doing some kind of long
running right operation, where it has to
read from some data or it's grabbed a lock
or whatever it is that causes it to block.
Without having to worry about interfering
with the quality of service and
performance of the other threads at the
Synchronous layer.
That they themselves can also be blocking
and running on the multiple CPUs as their
logic dictates as a general rule of thumb
it's easy to program.
A multi-threaded approach that simply
reads data in, grabs something, and then
sends it back in blocks.
That's pretty straight forward.
We can then use the Half-Sync/Half-Async
pattern to implement our JAWS web server
by combining the reactor pieces that we've
talked about before with the active object
pieces that we've just got done talking
about.
Here's the way we could do this.
We could have a reactor at the bottom in
the Async or reactive service layer that's
waiting for work to show up on multiple
sources of input, multiple sources of
socket events.
And when that work comes in, the work will
be processed by, say, one of our HTTP
service handlers, which will read the
requests out of the buffer, and when we
finally got all the pieces in a get
request.
We can then turn around and stick them
onto a queue, and that queue will then be
used to service the various threads that
are running in the active object layer.
So you can think of the cue and the
threads as being part of an active object,
and the reactor as being used to feed that
particular cue.
And then the threads that are running the
object layer can DQ the get-request, do
the processing, and afford to block.
The synchronized request queue, of course,
is what mediates the interaction between
the reactive portion and the active
portion.
So we have one thread in the reactor part,
multiple threads in the active object
part, and the queue is part of the active
object that's used to feed those threads
in that pool.
If for some reason, flow control occurs in
one of the threads, not a problem.
We're able to keep making progress and
other threads will not be blocked unduly.
So this gives us a nice way to scale up
our performance without using an
unrealistic and unreasonable amount of
resources to do so, most of which would be
wasted.
So here are some of the benefits and
limitations of this particular pattern.
You can simplify some parts of your design
quite nicely, it's easy to block in these
threads that are spawned.
But at the same time, we don't have to
have a completely multi-threaded solution
that would have too many threads running
around without actually improving
anything.
We could also do a good job of separating
concerns.
So we can end up having things done in
such a way where the right concurrency
model is used at the right layer.
We use the reactive approach down below
because there is not much going on at that
layer.
We have the active approach on top,
there's more blocking that may be going
on.
And this allows us to be able to work
effectively between those different
realms.
Another nice thing is we're able to
centralize the communication between the
various layers.
So there's one queue, there's one single
point to go.
We can do all kinds of clever things to
that queue.
We can reorder the events, get requests so
that they may be able to be run In
priority order rather than running in
arrival order, which could give preference
to certain clients that are perhaps
higher-paying customers or gold card
customers as, as opposed to bronze card
customers and so on.
So we have a lot of flexibility by the
fact that there's this extra queue that's
used to mediate between the async part and
the sync part that's on top.
Naturally, there's some limitations you
have to be aware of.
There can be boundary crossing penalties
that in, are incurred when you go from the
reactive, or async portion, up to the
synchronous portion.
They'll be additional context switching to
do between threads, additional
synchronization.
Data movement costs, if you go between
different threads that are running in the
same on different cores.
In some kind of multi core environment.
There will also typically be dynamic
memory allocation.
And dynamic memory release.
So these are things that start to add up
if you're not careful.
And once again, if you do long running
operations, it's not a big deal.
But if you do short running operations,
this could be prohibitively expensive from
an overhead point of view.
Another downside with this pattern is that
the higher level services may not be able
to benefit from some efficient
asynchronous I/O support that's built into
certain operating systems.
We will talk about a pattern later called
the proactor pattern.
That allows us to alleviate this
particular downside.
And then the final problem which we always
have whenever we deal with concurrency
there's lots of stuff going on.
There's multiple threads of control
running, there's reactive stuff.
If the async layer is driven by callbacks.
That itself can be complicated, or
interrupts, even more complicated because
you have timing properties that are
difficult to emulate and to debug and to
test, that only run in certain ways in the
production environments.
So when you use any kind of concurrency
pattern, it really pays to think carefully
about the different pieces, what the
various constraints are, what the various
responsibilities are.
And use that to help shape the way in
which you set up your debugging
environment and the way which you think
about the various states and interactions
in your program.