Welcome to Part 1, of the module on
Patterns and Frameworks for Service
Configuration and Activation.
In this part of the module, we'll begin by
describing the Component Configurator
pattern.
To motivate this pattern let's talk about
enabling and enhancing server
configurability and reconfiguarbility.
The context for this is that some
implementations of web server components
depend on either static or dynamic
factors.
Some of the static factors include things
like the number of CPUs or cores available
when you start to run.
Other factors include the version of the
operating system that you may be using
which may have certain enhancements or
certain optimizations enabled.
More dynamic factors include things like
what the network load is and the workload
that's being sent by clients, so what are
the problems?
Well if you prematurely commit yourself to
particular implementations of the
components in the web server this can be
either inflexible or inefficient because
there certain optimizations and design
decisions you really can't make without
having knowledge of takes as you begin to
launch, or run your application.
Moreover, if you fall into the tendency of
trying to group everything together into
one big module, to have all the different
alternatives covered, you can end up with
bloatware which is very large and very
slow because it won't fit into caches and
you're including a lot of capability that
really isn't needed.
So what can we do to address these issues?
Well, as we'll describe here, we're going
to apply the component configurator
pattern in order to assemble the desired
web server components more dynamically
late in the design cycle either at
installation time, or even at run time.
The component configurator pattern
decouples component interfaces from their
implementations and makes it possible to
dynamically configure or reconfigure these
implementations at various points of time
in the life cycle.
And you can even do this in a way that
doesn't require having to shut down and
restart running applications.
And the diagram on this slide illustrates
the overall structure of this pattern,
some portions are infrastructural.
There's typically some kind of class
interface or message interface that you
inherit or implement that provides you
with life cycle operations.
Things for initializing, finalizing,
suspending, resuming and so on the
components that are being controlled under
this pattern.
There's also a way of being able to
restore a group of dynamically and/or
statically configured components into some
kind of repository so we actually know
what constitutes the space of different
implementations available at any given
point in time.
Yet another piece of the structure of the
solution, is some kind of component
configurator that orchestrates the way in
which various components are dynamically
brought in dynamically removed, suspended
and resumed and so on.
What you typically do then is you go ahead
and you inherit or implement these various
hook methods to fill in concrete
components that will be used and managed
in terms of their life cycle by these more
abstract elements.
If you take a look at this URL, you'll
find a paper that talks in more detail
about the component configurator pattern.
So let's also talk a bit more about the
dynamics of this pattern.
This set of slides illustrates the various
ways in which either an application or an
administrator can interact with the
capabilities defined, by the pattern in
order to configure the system and assemble
it more dynamically and more flexibly.
So typically, under some directive from
some place, be it an administrator or
application.
The component configurator is instructed
to configure a service or a component into
the address space of the application
process.
That will then go ahead and look into some
kind of dynamic link library, or shared
object, pull out the various information.
Typically, in the form of a factory
function that will create the appropriate
instance of the component with its
appropriate implementation.
That will then get stored in the component
repository and the service can then begin
to run, to do whatever it is it needs to
do.
Some examples of capabilities that work
like this, historically, have been things
like loadable device drivers for
protocols.
Things like transfer protocols or device
drivers on various kinds of operating
systems.
Java applets have historically worked this
way, as well as the ability to load
components into application servers
dynamically based on some type of script
that's read when they start up.
We can apply the component configurator
pattern to JAWS in a number of ways.
First, what we can do is we can implement
a bunch of different threading models for
our particular web server, some that would
use thread for connection, thread pool.
Various kinds of asynchronous processing
with threads, even more conventional
reactive processes.
And we can have these different
implementations available and stored in
various DLLs or shared libraries.
And then these shared libraries and DLLs
can be used to link in the appropriate
implementation that's desired under the
appropriate circumstance, in which we find
ourselves when we begin to run our
program.
Key to note that by doing this, the
implementation only has to pay the cost in
terms of memory footprint utilization for
the services that it actually uses at any
given point in time.
And moreover, we can change these services
over time as well.
So this leads us into a discussion of some
of the benefits of using.
The component configurate, configurator
pattern.
Chief among these benefits is this paths
of parsimony you're only paying the costs
in terms of memory footprint and
utilization of the actual components that
you need, the ones that you don't need
don't have to be linked in.
You could also centralize the
administration so all the components can
be configured in a uniform common way.
With a uniform API that's used to
initialize them and finalize them and so
on.
Because you're building your components
out of smaller pieces, and your
applications are scripted out of building
blocks, it enables a much more modular
approach to building your software.
And by doing things like this you also
encourage the use of various kinds of unit
testing, test-driven development,
continuous integration where you can
assemble the different parts and test them
in isolation.
And then integrate them together
dynamically to see how they work.
The last main benefit of component
configurator is indeed this concept of
dynamic configuration.
You can wait until late in the design
cycle to bring in just the elements you
need, just when you need them and tune
them to the particular details of the
context or environment, in which they run.
There are of course some limitations
associated with all this flexibility.
One of that chief limitations is the fact
that by bringing together an application
who components are dictated dynamically,
you end up limiting or reducing the amount
of determinism.
It's not always clear.
What is actually being linked together and
whether those things are correctly
ordered, whether they'll be brought in at
the right time, whether they have access
to each other in an appropriate way.
So that makes it a little bit harder to
know just exactly what your system does.
Another consequence of this as well is
there are certainly robustness and
reliability issues.
Some things might work fine in isolation
but when brought together might have
conflicts.
This is particularly true with respect to
properties like, timing properties, where
things may run fine in isolation but when
you combine them together dynamically, all
the sudden their timing properties begin
to vary.
Naturally, there are also some security
implications.
You have to be careful you aren't loading
Trojan horses into your address space
without really knowing what they're going
to be doing.
Another issue is when you start using
shared libraries or DDLs, some
implementations, especially ones that use
so-called position independent code, to
allow the modules to be linked in various
parts of memory.
Those can incur some extra levels of
overhead for indirection, especially for
global variables which may be one reason
why you should avoid using global
variables.
Yet another reason to avoid using global
variables because you could have some run
time over head by having to go indirect
through various types of indirect through
various kinds of global offset tables.
And another issue that you have to deal
with when you're using this pattern is the
potential for overly narrow common
interfaces.
Some things work well with a common
interface.
Other things might require more
configuration information than you might
be able to pass through a common interface
for all the different types of components.
And you may end up trying to fit
everything into a Procrustean bed where
some things don't quite fit and you have
to stretch them or reinterpret them in a
more dynamic way.
It turns out that these issues can be
addressed by proper design of the generic
interfaces.
And we'll talk about this as we go further
along in this particular module.