Welcome to Part 5, in the module on
Patterns & Frameworks for Concurrency and
Synchronization.
In previous parts of this module, we
started by describing the active object
pattern.
And exploring the ACE task framework that
can be used to implement active objects
and other concurrency patterns.
We then talked about how to apply the ACE
Task and ACE Acceptor-Connector frameworks
in order to be able to implement a thread
per connection version of our web server.
Next, we talked about the
Half-Sync/Half-Async pattern, which
combines the reactor with active object.
And now, we're going to implement
Half-Sync/Half-Async using a number of
frameworks in ACE.
This particular example will provide yet
another path through our pattern language
for web servers.
This particular path will be, as you'll
see, more scalable, realistically scalable
than some of the implementations and
patterns and frameworks we've looked at
before.
This particular example will start by
applying to use of the ACE service handler
in order to be able to provide the
reactive portion of this half-sync, half
passive pattern.
If you recall, we have a reactor portion
on the bottom and an active object portion
on top.
And we'll start by talking about the
reactive portion.
There are a lot of pieces to discuss in
this particular example, and so it's
important to have an understanding of the
pattern, in order to figure out how the
pieces interact with each other and how
they're structured.
Let's first start by talking about
defining the TP_HTTP_Handler class.
Tp stands for thread pool.
In this particular case the
TP_HTTP_Handler class is going to inherit
from ACE service handler, and that means
that we can dispatch it from the reactive
part of our system.
It them goes ahead and defines a reference
to an active object called, TP HTTP task
that we'll be talking about shortly and
that reference is tucked away as a data
member in the implementation of this
class.
We then override the open hook method
which will be used by the ACE Acceptor
Framework In order to activate this
particular object after a connection is
established.
Now when this occurs, what we're going to
do, is we're going to do two things, first
we're going to register ourselves with the
reactor to be dispatched when an incoming
event shows up, containing a, get message.
And we're also going to go ahead and
schedule a timer and this timer is used to
guard against situations where clients
provide some kind of intentional or
accidental denial of service attack.
Where they connect to our server, but
never send any get requests.
And therefore, we'd end up wasting
resources.
Let's first take a look at how we might
implement the handle time out mechanism.
If the time out period elapses.
Which could be whatever you want it to be
30 seconds, a minute, 10 minutes, 2
seconds.
Whatever you think is appropriate for your
workload environment.
Your reactor will go ahead and call-back
the handle timeout hook method after that
timeout elapses.
And what we do in this case is we use this
as an opportunity to shut down that
particular connection and reclaim any
resources that have been allocated
dynamically, to prevent those types of
denial service attacks.
More likely however, we're actually going
to get a get request, and when that
occurs, the reactor will call back to the
handle input method on our TP_HTTP_Handler
class, and this handle input method will
do several things.
The first thing it'll do, is it'll try to
receive the complete message from the
socket end point, and this may actually
take a number of tries, because we can't
afford to block here.
Because we're in the Half-Async layer, or
the reactive layer, of our solution.
Assuming we get the complete message then
what we do is we cancel the timer, remove
the handler, and we take the message that
we got and we pass it up to the half sync
layer using the put method that is invoked
on the.
Thread pool HTTP task object we've got a
reference to this put method represents
the boundary between the Half-Async part
or the reactive part which is single
threaded and runs with callbacks from the
reactor and the active object part, which
as we'll see in a moment is actually
multi-threaded and runs as an active
object.
So let's now take a look at how we can
implement this half-sync layer using the
ACE_Task class.
So once again we have our Half-Async part,
which we're using the reactor, and now
we're going to go ahead and focus on
illustrating how to implement the
half-sync portion of our
Half-Sync/Half-Async solution, using
ACE_Task, which will spawn a pool of
threads.
So let's first define the TP_HTTP_Task
class, where once again, TP is thread
pool.
As you can see, this particular class
inherits from ACE_Task, and it provides a
special set of traits and these traits are
used to indicate that it wants to use the
multi-threaded synchronization
capabilities, which essentially means
we're going to have a synchronized request
queue.
And we'll talk a bit more about that as we
go further along.
We then go ahead in the constructor of
this object and we activate it to become
an active object.
And as you can see here we're going to
spawn, eight threads, and these threads
will run in a pool in the background, and
we'll look more at that.
In just a moment, when the put method is
invoked on this particular active object,
as part of the handle input phase in the
Half-Async portion of our design, that put
method is going to turn around, take the
message that is passed in, and then put
it, or enqueue it, onto the thread-safe
message queue.
And that will then be used to feed in to
the method that we'll look at on the next
slide.
We'll explain how this synchronized
request works in the next part of this
module.
We talk about the monitor object pattern.
Here is the key driver for this Half-Sync
layer.
This is the service hook method.
This method will be called back once in
every thread that's part of the thread
pool.
And that, of course, will be managed by
the ACE task framework we've been talking
about.
This particular service method will block
in every thread, waiting for a new message
to show up from the half a sync part, from
the part that's driven by the reactor.
And the schedule of the operating and the
thread scheduling package will decide.
Which of the threads waiting, in so-called
hungry puppy fashion, to get the next get
request.
Which of those threads will receive the
work.
The thread will then unblock when getq
returns, when it's, it's turn to run and
that get request will then be extracted
out of the message along with the socket
handle that comes back and that will be
used to memory map the particular content
requested by the user and then send that
content back to the Client Application
running on another machine.
Notice how as always the core web server
logic is essentially identical in all the
examples we've looked at, the thing that
keeps changing is the way in which we
arrange this logic to be called, using
different concurrency and event handling
patterns, an arrangement of those
patterns.
Let's take a look now at our thread-pool
HTTP acceptor class, or TP HTTP acceptor
class.
Which of course is an ACE acceptor, so it
registers uses all the capabilities that
ACE acceptor provides.
It's parametrized using the TP.
Http handler class, which we looked at
earlier, which is a service handler.
And its constructor simply forwards down
to the constructor of ACE acceptor which
will go and listen on the appropriate port
number.
In our case most likely port 80, unless we
decide to override that somewhere else.
And then if you recall the handle input.
Put template method that the acceptor uses
when it gets a new connection coming in
from a client somewhere in the network.
One of the hook methods that the template
method handle input calls back is called
make service handler.
And you can see here, we will simply
override make service handler.
In order to be able to spawn a new
instance, or create a new instance of the,
the TP_HTTP_Handler object.
And that will also include a reference to
the TP HTTP task object, which is the
active object.
So, what that means is that every end
point object, which is the one that's a
service handler, has a reference to this
active object.
So, it knows how to do a put invocation on
that active object to pass the incoming
GET messages from async layer up to the
sync layer, where things can be running
and blocking a different thread control.
Let's take a look at the driver program
for our solution.
As you can see here the driver program is
very, very similar to the one we saw
before, just a little tiny tweet to use a
different kind of acceptor.
In this case the TP, HTTP acceptor that we
just define.
We go ahead and create ourselves an ace
reactor to drive the event loop.
We create an instance of the HTTP server
demon, which will use that reactor to go
ahead and, and do various things to
register for, for deallocations when
things get shut down.
And then, finally, as always, with the
reactor.
We run the event loop and the event loop
will be used to wait for connection
requests to come in and when those
connection requests come in they're
accepted.
The HTTP handlers are created by the
acceptor and then those handlers are used
to take the messages.
Put them in the thread safe message queue.
Where they're then processed by threads in
the pool of threads.
Running in the TP, HTTP task, which is the
active object seems complicated.
But actually, it all flows quite nicely
from the various parts of the pattern.
So, to summarize this particular section,
this particular part in the module.
It turns out that, even though there are
lots of moving parts, we can keep track of
the roles and responsibilities, the way in
which those moving parts relate to each
other, by a firm understanding of patterns
and frameworks.
The particular patterns that we are going
to use here or that we've used here are
they Half-Sync/Half-Async pattern?
And of course that's going to be able to
combine the reactor pattern with the
active object pattern.
So now we are able to reuse these patterns
we've talked about in previous examples.
And more importantly we're also able to
reuse not just the design artifacts but
we're also able to reuse the
implementations of these design artifacts
that are provided by the various
framework.
The ACE reactor framework, the acceptor
connecter framework, and the ACE task
framework.
So this gives us both the reuse of the
design knowledge that went into
understanding how the patterns relate to
each other as well as the implementation
knowledge and detail design knowledge
embodied in the source code that we get
with the ACE framework works.
Another nice thing about this particular
approach is that by trying to more
carefully bound the number of threads that
we allocate to the number of cores at our
disposal in the hardware, we're probably
in a better shape to be able to scale up
the processing more effectively.
We're not allocating hundreds or thousands
of threads, most of which are doing
nothing most of the time.
Instead, we're having about as many
threads as there are cores.
And then those threads are used to get
data out the endpoints from the sockets.
And then queue up that data in the
synchronized request queue where it's
eventually processed by the various
threads in the active object pool.