Hello and welcome to Part 1 of the module
on Patterns and Frameworks for Synchronous
Event Handling, Connection Establishment
and Service Initialization.
In this part of the module, we're going to
be presenting the reactor and acceptor
connector patterns, which are key patterns
for event handling, service initialization
and connection establishment.
To motivate these patterns, let's talk a
bit about our expectations of a webserver.
When we talked about the wrapper facade
solution in the previous module we focused
on keeping things simple, we gave you an
iterative solution that doesn't really
scale, its only handling one connection
request, one GET request of the time from
clients which is absolutely not going to
work in practice.
One alternative approach, people have
historically used when they built web
servers, was to be able to support
multiple clients simultaneously.
And a very classic way of doing this is to
use some kind of underlying operating
system IO multiplexer, like select or
poll, or wait for multiple objects.
And to run this in a single thread of
control.
And then to wait for something to happen
on multiple sources of input.
And then to handle all or part of the
incoming request before going on to the
next request from a different client.
Typically when people implement solutions
in this way, they tend to tightly couple a
number of things.
They tend to couple certain concerns.
They couple concerns for event
multiplexing and demultiplexing, service
establishment, connection establishment
and service initialization.
And those things all get glommed together
with the actual protocol processing done
in our case using HTTP.
Lets take a look at little bit of a code
fragment which illustrates these problems.
Here is piece of code you might find in a
traditional, reactive style web server and
what you see it doing as it uses the
select call to wait for.
Either connection events or data events to
occur on multiple sources of handles.
That obviously hard codes us to using
select which may not be the right choice
in all environments and all platforms.
We're also still hard coding ourselves to
some Posix and Unixisms as far as how
socket handles are defined.
That will be a problem if we try to port
to other platforms like Windows.
We're also using sequential linear search
to look through all the handles to find
handles where activity have gotten sources
of events to come in, that will take a
certain amount of long time if there's a
lot of connected clients.
And then finally, we also tightly couple
the protocol processing, the HTTP protocol
processing with the connection
establishment, service initialization, and
event multiplexing.
So how can we get around these problems?
Well what we're going to talk about here
as a way to do it is to apply a pair of
patterns that are often used together.
These patterns are the reactor pattern and
the acceptor connector pattern and we're
going to use these patterns in order to be
able to separate out the generic.
Event infrastructure service
initialization a connection establishment
code from the protocol processing we do in
the web server once things are connected.
Let's talk first about the reactor
pattern.
If you take a look at this diagram, it
illustrates the structure of the reactor
pattern, which is broken up into a couple
of parts.
First we have a role, or a class, called a
reactor.
And it's essentially a container and
applications, or higher level services
register so called event handlers with a
reactor via its register handler methods.
And these handlers are typically pointers
to base class objects that can be
subclassed and customized to provide
specific event handling logic.
The reactor then squirrels away this
information in some internal tables, and
at some point the application turns the
flow of control over to the reactor by
calling it's handle events method or run
event loop method.
At which point the reactor then
coordinates with the underlying IO
multiplexer and synchronous event, the
multiplexing mechanisms that the operating
system provides, which wait for activities
to occur, which wait for events to occur
from different sources of events, on these
handles associated with the event
handlers.
And when stuff happens, it returns and
then the reactor will dispatch the
particular events to the corresponding
event handler by invoking their hook
methods.
Now, the application or the higher level
service will have customized the core
event handler base class.
Overridden its virtual functions.
And then carried out whatever service
specific or application specific
processing functionality is needed to
handle the events.
If you take a look at this paper at this
URL, you'll find more descriptions about
the reactor pattern, and ways to implement
this pattern and practice.
Here's a view that illustrates some of the
dynamics of the reactor pattern.
The dynamics are broken up into a couple
of different phases.
One of the first things we do is we
typically register a bunch of concrete
event handlers with a reactor.
And the reactor often does a little
double-dispatching dance with those event
handlers to get handles and other
information explaining what those Handlers
are trying to do, what types of events
they're concerned with, and those things
get stashed in an internal table.
Then at some point the application turns
the focus of control over to the reactor.
It goes ahead and uses the demultiplexing
and multiplexing mechanisms of the
operating system, to wait for events to
happen, and when those events occur, it
then calls back on the corresponding event
handle.
Note the inversion of control that's
taking place here.
The reactor runs the event loop, it has
the main focus of control and it does
callbacks to hook methods back to the
concrete event handlers to get the work
done.
Let's now turn our attention to the second
pattern in this group of patterns, the
Acceptor-Connector pattern.
The purpose of this pattern is to decouple
the connection establishment and service
initialization lodge, which is fairly
generic as it turns out.
From the more specific customized
application or higher level service
protocol processing that occurs once
things are actually connected.
As with the reactor there's a couple of
layers involved here from a pattern
structure point of view.
The core part of this is some type of
dispatcher.
We're going to be using our reactor,
because they work together nicely.
Which is waiting for say different kinds
of events.
In our particular case, the acceptors and
connectors are concerned with connection
establishment events.
Things that occur when a connection
arrives or when you initiate a connection.
There are several layers on top of the
dispatcher reactor portion, and let's talk
about the most important part.
This is the part that deals with
connection establishment and service
initialization.
In this particular layer, we have three
primary roles, we have connectors,
acceptors and service handlers.
Service handlers are the pieces of logic
that actually carry out the application
protocol.
They have a conversation with their peer.
In our particular case for HTTP, they
would be passing GET requests and POST
requests and so on and getting the
appropriate responses back from the
server.
The connector is the role that actively
initiates a connection.
And when the connection is established
with it's peer, then it goes ahead and
initializes a service handler to do the
actual application processing.
The acceptor is the inverse side of this,
it waits passively for something to
happen.
It waits passively for the connector to
connect to it and when a connection
occurs, it accepts the connection and then
it goes ahead and calls to initialize the
appropriate service handler and now once
the acceptor and connector have done their
job.
The service handlers on each side of these
different relationships go ahead and
interact with each other, and carry out
their conversation.
Here's a more dynamic view that
illustrates how these different parts talk
to each other.
And to explain this particular diagram,
I'll give you an example that's probably
something you may be familiar with from
everyday life.
If you are an important person or if you
know an important person in an
organization, that person often doesn't
take their own phone calls.
They have an assistant, a receptionist who
plays the acceptor role and will screen
the calls and only pass the calls along if
they deem those calls important for the
service handler, for the person to handle.
Likewise if you're an even more important
person in an organization you may not
place your own phone calls.
You may have your assistant or
receptionist place the calls.
So the concept of a connector is the
person who connects the communication, the
concept of an acceptor as someone who
accepts an incoming connection.
And then the service handlers are the
parties who are important who actually
carry out the conversation.
Once other roles have done their job to
get them connected.
This separation concerns is basically
there to make sure that we don't waste
time of people and to refactor the generic
processing so it can be handled at lower
level.
Take a look at this URL for a paper that
goes into more detail about acceptor and
connector.
Now that we understand the basic patterns
let's talk about how we can apply acceptor
and connector in the context of JAWS.
What we're going to do here is separate a
couple of different concerns.
We'll use the reactor to separate the
concerns of generic event detection,
demultiplexing and dispatching.
Some of the events we'll be dispatching
will be those having to do with passive
connection, establishment and service
initialization and the acceptor will do
that, other events that'll come after
things are connected or events that
actually correspond to the web protocol
that we implement, HTTP.1 for example.
In that case we're going to have some kind
of handler, some kind of service handler,
that will actually do the work once the
acceptor factory creates it.
Notice this particular example doesn't
really emphasize the connector because a
web server plays the passive role.
But there are plenty of real-life
applications where you need connectors as
well, in fact whoever the, the active side
of the web communication could be using a
connector in order to carry out the
connection establishment logic.
So lets talk about some of the benefits
and limitations of these various patterns.
From the reactor pattern point of view,
some of the benefits are these very strict
separation of concerns.
The infrastructure processing is done by
some of the core parts of the pattern.
You as an application developer don't have
to write this code, you just have to know
how to use it effectively.
You just have to focus on writing your
application logic.
Some other benefits are that it's much
more modular and reusable and
configurable.
It's easy to extend application or server
specific logic by inheriting from the base
logic.
You can reuse the infrastructure once you
have a framework that realizes this
pattern.
Another benefit is it's easy to implement
this pattern in a way where you can hide
the details of the underlying event
multiplexing into multiplexing provided by
the operating system to make your solution
more, more portable.
We'll talk later about ways we do this in
ACE.
But you can port this to many different
platforms and extract and hide those type
of details and encapsulate that
variability from higher level services and
applications.
Another benefit you get here is you
typically can have Coarse-grained
concurrency control.
With the reactor, with the reactive
solution, there's typically one thread of
control that's being driven to call back
into the application event handlers and
this particular thread of control can be
doing its thing and if you're writing an
event handler, you typically don't have to
be concerned about another thread of
control coming along and modifying any
data or state that you may be accessing.
So it simplifies concurrent access.
There are of course, some limitations.
If you don't have aplatform that supports
sychronist mulchplexing and demultiplexing
efficiently, then this pattern's not
really going to work very well.
It would be way too much overhead to
emulate this with threads, for example.
Another issue has to do with the
single-threaded nature of this solution.
If you have call back that's being run on
a event handler and that callback blocks
or goes into an infinite loop or runs for
an extended period of time, then you'll
end up blocking and starving other
connected clients from getting their work
to be accomplished, and that can be a
problem if they need to be more
responsive.
A similar issue with a single threaded
solution is we don't have an easy way to
scale up to multiprocessors, or
multi-core.
So, as a result, if you're using a purely
reactive solution and the arrival rate of
new work is faster than it takes to
process the existing work, there's no way
to offload that by running it on multiple
processing units.
Another challenge you always run into when
you start building frameworks and patterns
that exhibit inversion of control Is the
more complicated debugging you have to
concerned with.
Knowing how to set breaking points,
knowing when the various callback take
place, require you to have some knowledge
of the inner workings of the abstractions.
And while that's not the most hard thing
in the world, it does takes a little bit
of practice to become comfortable
programming and debugging and testing in
an inversion of control environment.
Let's talk about some of the benefits of
the acceptor-connector pattern.
As with the reactor, things are more
modular, you can tell at a glance what's
the acceptor role, what's the connector
role, what's the roles for service
handlers.
You can make things more reusable, it's
easier to extend by subclassing or various
types of parametrization from the base
portions of the abstractions that
implement these particular pattern roles
it's also more robust.
You can't accidentally try to accept or
connect to a service handler.
You can't likewise try to read and write
on something that's a connector or
acceptor, the type system doesn't allow
that.
So it removes certain types of errors and
from a efficiency point of view.
If you're using the connector portion of
this pattern, which we haven't talked a
lot about here but if you read the
literature you'll find out more about it.
You could actually invoke connections
asynchronously.
And the nice thing about asynchronous
exception connection establishment is
that, that scales up very nicely within a
limited number of threads of control to
take advantage of the inherent parallelism
in the operating system, the hardware, the
network, the remote operating systems and
so on, to allow many connections to be
running in parallel.
While only devoting a very small number of
threads, maybe even just one on the client
side.
There of course, are some limitations.
Typically, when you implement the acceptor
connector patter, yoiu have a framework
implementation.
And any type of frameworks has additional
levels of indirection, various kinds of
callbacks and so on.
And so you have to be sure you can afford
those levels of overhead.
They're typically not on the critical path
but you have to think about this
nonetheless and there's always a space
overhead incurred with frameworks for the
most part.
Another potential issue is that there's
just more moving parts in an
Acceptor-Connector solution.
And if you're building a large system
that's going to run for a long period of
time perfectly acceptable to walk up that
learning curve, and to master these other
elements.
If you're just trying to throw together a
simple prototype, you might not want to
spend the time learning all these
different pieces.
In my experience, sometimes, these simple
prototypes escape from the lab.
And we end up having to maintain them, and
extend them over long periods of time.
So sometimes, it actually makes sense to
invest up front.
And learning the abstractions to make you
a more effective developer down the road.