Hello, an welcome to part three in the
module on patterns and frameworks for
syncronous event handling, connection
establishment and service initilazation.
In previous parts of this module we first
described the reactor and acceptor
conector patterns and then we talked about
the way in which.
The adaptive communication environment, or
ACE implements the reactor pattern in the
form of the ACE reactor framework.
And now we're going to talk about how to
apply the reactor framework to our JAWS
web server.
This particular example will be a very
simple path through our pattern language.
We're going to be using the wrapper
facades we talked about before.
And we'll be combining it with parts of
the reactor framework in order to be able
to have a reactive solution.
Later, we'll go ahead and generalize this
and aplly some other patterns to implement
other variations in this particular
pattern language.
Here's a high level view that illustrates
how this particular design is going to
work using a reactive approach.
What'll happen here is that we'll create
something called an HTTP_Event_Acceptor
which registers itself with the
ACE_Reactor.
The flow of control will then be turned
over to the ACE_Reactor which will wait
for clients to send events.
When a client connects, that'll cause the
reactor to dispatch the handle input
method.
On the HTTP event acceptor, which will act
as a factory to create the appropriate
HTTP event handler.
Which will then register itself back with
the reactor.
That's the connection establishment and
service initialization faze.
Then when a client sends over a get
request or some other type of request, the
reactor will turn around and dispatch the
handle input method.
On the corresponding HTTP event handler.
Which will read the request, figure out
the corresponding URI that was part of the
request message.
Remember map that, and then transmit that
back to the client and then clean itself
up.
And these are the basic steps.
And you can imagine having multiple
different clients connected and these
kinds of things taking place concurrently,
all driven by callbacks using ACE reactor.
Here's a particular view that illustrates
how this works, it's kind of another
variant of this particular design.
You can see here how we have an ACE
reactor at the core of everything, it's
running in one thread of control and it
handles two types of events.
It handles Except Events And it also
handles data events.
So, not surprisingly, those are the kinds
of things that we'll be using to register
with the reactor for to tell it to
dispatch it when accepts and, and reads
occur.
We're going to define two different types
of event handlers to make all this work.
One of these types of event handlers we've
already mentioned, which is the http.
Event handler, and this is the one that's
going to process the get requests.
And under the hood, it's going to have an
instance of an ACE sock stream that it
will use to read the data in and then send
the results back to the connected client.
We will also have the http.
Event Acceptor and that's a factory that
knows how to create the
HTTP_Event_Handlers and internal to the
factory, it has an instance of
ACE_SOCK_Acceptor and it uses the sock
acceptor in order to be able to initialize
the corresponding ACE_SOCK_Stream When a
connection request comes in.
Lets take a little bit of time and look
through some of the code here, I'm sure
there's a couple of different pieces.
We first start by talking about the http
event acceptor which inherents from ACE
event handler in this particular case.
So that means it can be registers with a
reactor and dispatched by the reactor
event.
We define this, this factory object called
the ACE sock acceptor that knows how to
receive connection accept connections from
clients.
We use the default reactor singleton.
Which allows us to have a single place
where we drive everything by one reactor
in our process that we're using for this.
There, there are ways to override this if
you don't like to use singletons.
This is a very convenient way to do it.
We then have a, an open hook method, which
is going to be used to initialize SOCK
Acceptor to listen on the right port in
this case it would probably default to
port 80 but you could override that if you
wanted to.
And then it'll also go ahead and register
itself.
It registers this with the corresponding
reactor and says please call me back when
the accept event occurs.
When, when a client connects, when the
accept event bubbles up from deep in the
bowels of the operating system.
We've, I've omitted some of the error
checking here just to avoid making the
code really convoluted.
In, in real life, of course, there would
be more error checking.
Let's take a look at the handle_close
method.
This is the one that's called back when
this particular object goes away, say,
when the reactor's shutting down.
In this particular case, it goes ahead and
shuts down the acceptor and then it goes
and deletes itself.
It's perfectly to do delete this in this
case, though you have to be careful with
this in practice.
There's also a method that's called
get_handle, and the reactor uses this to
do a little bit of Doubled dispatching
with the acceptor to get the handle it's
going to use to listen on by its
synchronous I/O multiplexer.
The most interesting method here is the
handle_input method.
This is what gets called back by the
reactor automatically when a connection
shows up.
We'll talk about this method in a second
after we talk about the
HTTP_Event_Handler.
Here is the HTTP event handler.
This is also an Ace event handler so it
can be dispatched by the reactor
framework.
As you can see it has an instance of an
Ace sock stream, which will be connected
by the acceptor to correspond to the
connection with the client, that's in data
mode or the ability to send and receive
data on it, It also has an activation
method called open and we'll look and see
how that's used by the acceptor in a
moment.
It's got a little accessor method to give
back a reference to the underlying
ACE_SOCK_Stream and we'll use this in
order to access that whenever we need to
access the connection to the client once
it's connected.
There's a Handle input method, which'll be
used when the, get request, or other kinds
of HTTP messages show up from clients.
And then there's the Handle Close method
that's used when we're going to be shut
down, when we're all done processing, or
if a error occurs.
Now that we understand a little bit about
HTTP Event Handlers, let's talk about how
the Handle input method of the HTTP event
acceptor works.
Handle input is called back when a
connection arrives from the clients and as
you can see in this particular example, it
does several things.
It goes ahead and it creates an event
handler that knows how to handle HTTP
events, get request for example, and then
it goes ahead and accepts the connection
and stores it into its SOCK_STREAM.
And then it turns around and it says to
this newly created Event_Handler, please
activate yourself, by calling the OpenHook
method.
What the OpenHook method does as we show
here is this turns around and registers
itself, the Event_Handler back with the
same reactor that's being used to drive
the Acceptor logic.
So now both Connection accept events and
read events, which correspond to get
messages, are going to be handled
reactively by the same event loop, by the
same event loop object, the reactor.
Now when a get request shows up from a
client.
The reactor will call back to the handle
input hook method on the http event
handler, and that does a couple of things.
And notice this logic will start to look
very, very familiar because we use it over
and over again.
What it does is it goes ahead and extracts
out The path name, from the stream it was
passed from the client.
So it extracts to get, requires and
extracts the path-name from there.
It then goes ahead and memory maps that
file the content that was requested by
that path-name and then it turns around
and sends the result back to the client,
as a, as, a pointer to contiguous memory
object using memory mapped IO.
Now, of'course be aware that a real
Production web server would do a lot more
things than I'm showing you here.
I am just showing you parts that real,
that focus on, the networking and
concurrency portions.
So there's other patterns other
capabilities that we're not talking about.
That would be part of a broader pattern
language for a full featured web server.
When we're done, when we're finished
setting the file, we go ahead and close
things down.
And that will cause the stream to be shut
down, and we'll end up deleting the HTTP
event handler that was allocated
dynamically.
Note the similarity here between the
handle input logic for doing the get
method path name extraction The memory
mapping the file and the transmitting of
that content back to the client with the
logic we had in our earlier wrapper facade
base solution.
Its virtually identical and many of the
other solutions are almost identical too.
So you kind get the sent you could reuse a
lot of this logic over and over again in
different configurations.
So now let's go ahead and talk about how
we could use the ACE reactor portion.
We talked about how to subclass event
handler and be able to have an acceptor
and a handler for get requests for HTTP,
let's now talk about how we could combine
all the pieces together with the ACE
reactor class that we talked about before.
So keep in mind that the ACE reactor is
going to allow us to run our web server in
a single thread of control But we'll be
able to handle connection and get requests
that come in simultaneously, from multiple
clients, except they'll be handled in a
reactive way.
To do this we're going to define a little
helper class that we'll use quite a bit
throughout the rest of this section.
This class is called the reactor HTTP
server.
As you can see, it's got an interesting
use of templates and subclassing.
It's parameterized by a template and then
that template is then used as a base class
for this class.
And we're going to actually pass in
different kinds of acceptors in this
particular example.
There's a constructor that we use to pass
in rvrc command line parameters As well as
a pointer to the reactor that's going to
be used to run the event loop.
Let's take a look at how that constructor
would be implemented.
As you can see here, we turn around and
initialize the underlying exceptor base
class, passing in the reactor pointer, so
it, it knows who its associated with,
which reactor it belongs to.
We then do a little bit of parsing of the
Arc V parameter to get the appropriate
Port number to listen on.
We'll defort, default of course to port
80, that's the canonial port number but
you can change that if you want.
We then create an address using a trait so
we can write this in a generic way.
As long as our acceptor supports a trait
called pier adder, then we can pass in
many different kinds Of acceptors using
generic programming.
And then we'd turn around and we'd say
acceptor, please go ahead and start
listening for things to occur.
And if something were to go wrong, we'd
tell the reactor please shut yourself
down, we're going to bail out.
So that's the basic logic of this helper
class.
And we'll use this helper class in other
parts of the solution as well.
Here, then, is the main program.
This also will be very common.
You'll see things looking like this quite
a bit.
We go ahead and type DEF.
An instantiation of our reactor HTTP
server.
Parameterized with the HTTP event
acceptor, which we just created.
We'll then go ahead and make ourselves the
reactor of that loop object to control the
event loop.
We will make a new instance of this
typedef HTTP Server Daemon and we pass a
pointer to the reactor into that so it can
know how to clean itself up later.
And then we turn around and run the
reactor event loop, and, henceforth,
everything else is driven by callbacks
using the magic of inversion of control.
So you can see that the logic here is very
clean, very connonical, as you see later
we can generalize this particular approach
quite a bit to do other concurrency
models, handle other things beside web
server so on and so forth.
So we got a very clean starting point for
future exten, extension and evolution of
our design.
Sometimes it's hard when you look at
source code to really see how the various
callbacks are taking place and the
relationships between the various objects
involved in the design.
So the next couple slides I'm going to
kind of walk you through.
A sequence diagram illustrating how the
reactor and the HTTP event acceptor and
the HTTP event handler talk to each other,
in order to carry out the processing logic
I just showed you in code.
We start out by having the, the main
program register an acceptor who's
interested in accept events, we saw that
earlier When a connection arrives the
reactor then calls back through the handle
input method on that acceptor which turns
around and creates and event handler, that
http event handle then registers itself
with a reactor and says, please call me
back when read events occur.
Such as the get request that comes in from
a client, and then finally when that data
shows up the reactor calls back to that
event handler.
And it goes ahead and cracks open the
message, pulls out the various parts, the
path name, memory maps the file, and
transmits it back to the client, a very
simple example.
I, you'll see later that when we step back
and look at this logic we can actually
apply some Gang of Four patterns, such as
the Template Method Pattern.
And we can use this refactoring in order
to help drive the main logic and algorithm
of the acceptor connector pattern, which
we'll talk about shortly.
So to summarize this section, the ace
reactor version of the web server is much
more modular and extensible than the
raptor facade version that we saw before.
Or even though it does essentially the
same thing, its done in a way that's easy
to understand, the wrapper facades help to
resolve accidental complexities with
programming to low level IPC mechanisms
like sockets.
But it doesn't really address
architectural considerations.
It doesn't really provide you with the
framework for being able to extend it and
hence evolve your software in more
flexible way.
The reactor framework in contrast provides
a nice archetictural perspective.
That's why it's viewed as an archetictural
pattern.
Its core processing logic as we saw here
was very similar and very simple.
But the way in which we can extend this as
you'll see later is much more powerful.
We'll be able to add lots more capability.
And as, most importantly, as we go through
many more parts of the pattern language,
we'll be able to come up with ways to work
around some of the limitations with the
reactor pattern in particular it's non
preemptibility and non scalability by
coupling it wiht othe patterns to provide
much more effective thread-pool based
approaches.