Welcome to Part 2, in the module on
Patterns and Frameworks For Service
Configuration and Activation.
In the previous part of this module, we
had talked about the component
configurator pattern.
Now, we're going to describe how ACE
implements this pattern as part of the ACE
Service Configurator Framework.
Naturally, there are other ways to
implement this pattern, we'll be focusing
on the way in which we do it in ACE.
So, let's motivate the need and the way in
which this framework is going to act to
begin with.
Capturing and managing the life cycles of
services involve a number of different
aspects, it involved dealing with
initialization aspects.
It involved dealing with aspects having to
do with execution control, running event
loops, suspending, resuming, services
under various conditions and so on.
And of course it also deals with
termination or finalization, shutting
things down when they're no longer needed.
If you implement these things in a very Ad
Hoc way, you can end up with solutions
that are tightly coupled, difficult to
evolve, and difficult to maintain over
time.
Because each service will be done in a
slightly different way, and it'll be hard
to control them in a uniform and
centralized manner.
So to avoid this, we have developed a
framework called the ACE Service
Configurator Framework.
And that classes in this framework allow
applications to defer certain
configuration and implementation decisions
about the services that they provide until
late in their life cycle, late in their
design.
Namely at installation time or even during
run time, applications are services that
use this particular framework, inherit
from a base class called the ACE service
object, and then they override some of its
methods and the ACE Service Configurator
Framework then invokes these methods.
In order to configure and control the life
cycle of the absent services using the
framework.
We'll talk about a number of these
different classes in a moment.
Of course, these classes correspond
closely to the roles and responsibilities
defined in the component configurator
pattern.
Here's a brief summary of the key classes
that are part of the ACE Service
Configurator Framework.
One of the core classes is called ACE
service object, which is this base class
that provides a number of hook methods.
These hook methods are used to control
various life cycle activities of a service
or a component while it's being brought in
to existence.
While it's being executed, and when it's
being finalized and shut down is also
another class called the ACE service
repository.
And this is use to store instances of ACE
service objects.
Because we are going to be able to
configure the application services
dynamically, we need to have a common
place to go to learn what services are
actually provided at any given point in
time.
And so, the service repository is used to
keep track of that kind of information.
Then finally, we have another class called
the ACE service config and this class is
essentially a, an orchestrator or a facade
It's used to provide an interpreter that
reads a scripting language that can be
used to dictate what services are
configured or unconfigured, suspended,
resumed, and so on.
You can take a look at this URL for more
information about the ACE Service
Configurator Framework, which also of
course appears in some of the, the books
on ACE as well.
So let's talk a bit about the ACE service
object class.
This is a base class that the framework
uses to invoke various kinds of hook
methods to control the life cycle of the
services.
And here are some of the different types
of life cycle methods it supports.
It has a pair of methods for being able to
initialize and finalize, or terminate or
shut down a service object that's under
the control of the framework.
It also provides hook methods for being
able to suspend and resume a service.
There could be certain situations where
you don't want the service to be active.
Perhaps you're updating some of the data
it uses, or you're changing it's
implementation for some reason.
And so you can suspend it temporarily, so
events are not dispatched to it.
And after you're done, you can then go
ahead and resume it, so it can continue to
process requests that it's getting from
wherever its clients come from.
Yet another capability provided by the
ACE_Service_Object is a way to report
information about the dynamically
configured service.
You might way what its purpose is, as a
stray.
You might contain it's current status it's
load, whether it's active or inactive, the
port numbers or other addressing
information needed for clients to be able
to connect to it and so on and so forth.
By inheriting from the ACE event handler
ACE service object is also capable of
being dispatched by the ACE reactor
framework so these frameworks work
together to provide you with a number of
capabilities.
From a commonality and variability point
of view the ACE service object class
allows us to handle the variability of
life cycle operations, within a common
interface.
So we have these hook methods that may
differ but they're all managed in a common
way, a common uniform interface.
Let's now talk about the ACE service
config class.
This is a class that basically provides a
facade.
It hides all the complexity of the
internal details of the framework, and
it's used to integrate and provide certain
capabilities.
One of the capabilities it provides is it
provides a way for it to interpret a
scripting language.
That provides various directives that can
be used to do certain side effects to the
state of your application process.
One thing you can do is you can indicate
how to locate and initialize service
implementations during run time.
You could also tell it to suspend and
resume these various kinds of operations
as well.
It's also possible to use this class to
trigger reconfigurations of the services
dynamically and we'll look at some
examples a little bit later that
illustrate this in the context of our web
server.
There's a couple of different types of,
of, services that are provided by the
service configurator framework and the ACE
service config class.
The most common kind are the dynamic
services.
These are services whose implementations
can exist in DLLs or shared libraries that
are linked into the address space
dynamically as the process is running.
It's also possible to support certain
kinds of statically configured services.
These are services that are actually
linked with the initial executable.
But who's existence can come and go based
on directives that are interpreted by our
scripting language.
Once again from a common [unknown] point
of view, this particular class handles the
variability of static and dynamic service
configuration within a common set of
interfaces.
These directives are essentially commands
that can be passed to the service
configurative framework in various ways
to, to dictate or designate the way in
which behaves.
Here's a particular example that
illustrates a scripting file that shows
how to instruct the service configurator
framework.
To dynamically link in a particular DLL,
extract out a factory function that can be
used to make an instance of an HTTP
server, and then go ahead and initialize
this listening on a certain port number,
and if all goes well to register the
resulting configured object that was
dynamically linked into the service
repository, so it can be manipulated and
accessed at run time.
Ace Service Configurator Framework
supports a number of different types of
directives.
It supports dynamic linking directives,
static initialization directives.
It supports a directive for removing
something that was either linked
statically or dynamically to shut it down.
It supports directives for suspending and
resuming services.
And it also makes it possible to
dynamically configure certain hierarchy
composed services.
We won't talk about that much at all in
this example.
But it's yet a further way of being able
to integrate dynamic composition with
other capabilities that ace provides, in
terms of layered service composition.
We're going to focus primarily, primarily
on the dynamic, static, and remove
directives.
As we illustrate some of the examples
we'll talk about later on.
There's two primary ways that you can tell
the service configurator framework to, to
process directives.
One way is to give it a file named by
default as SVC conf or service conf.
This file contains a set of directives
that illustrate what needs to be done and
we'll look at a some examples in more
detail In just a moment.
You can also create strings from whatever
source you want, from some kind of editor,
you could pass them over a network, or
whatnot, and then be able to pass these
things as processing directives to the
ACE_Service_Config object in one fell
swoop.
And that way, you can have even more
fine-grained control over how you manage
configuration and reconfiguration.
So, to summarize this particular section.
The ACE service configurator framework
improves the extensibility of servers like
JAWS, by deferring the implementations of
some of their components, and objects or
services until late in the design cycle.
When they have enough information to make
an informed design choice.
These late binding capabilities provide a
number of benefits to application
developers.
One of these benefits is that the apps
themselves are composed out of very
modular services that can be developed
independently, and tested independently,
and then brought together and integrated
Into a complete solution at the
appropriate time.
When you have the right information to
make the right choice.
This also allows this, this decomposition
capability allows developers to focus on
things in isolation.
They can focus on the functionality.
They can focus on the optimization.
Without prematurely committing themselves
to a particular assembly of the different
services, which gives you more control
over how your systems will evolve over
time, because they're built in more
decomposable ways.
And then the last capability we get from
this late binding is the ability to change
our mind at installation time or run time
when he have the information we need.
As we go through the next part, we'll
discuss some examples and illustrate how
this framework can be applied more
specifically to extend and enhance the
JAWS webserver