Welcome to part 3 in the module on
patterns and frameworks for concurrency
and synchronization.
In previous parts of this module, we
started by describing the active object
pattern.
And then we talked about the ACE task
framework, which can be used to implement
this and other concurrency patterns.
Now we're going to explore yet another
path through our pattern laguage for JAWS
to illustrate how we can apply the ACE
task and acceptor connector frameworks in
the context of a web server.
This path will be our first true
multithreaded path through the design.
We'll come back and explore a number of
different multithreaded paths in later
parts of this module.
So this particular example actually builds
quite nicely on our previous version.
That we showed with acceptor connector,
which itself built nicely on top of the
reactor.
And w'e're going to add just a few very
minor tweaks in order to be able to get a
new, and more powerful, concurrent
multi-threaded design.
In particular, we're going to start first
by showing how we can use the ACE service
handler, which interits from ACE task, in
order to be able to spawn off.
Separate threads, one per connection.
And use them to service the incoming
requests concurrently.
So, to do this, we're going to define a
class called TPC for thread per
connection, HTTP handler.
And of course, this class will inherit
from ACE service handler.
And it'll use ACE SOCK stream.
So it'll be able to.
Send and receive via the socket wrappers
we've talked about before.
And then it's going to have a hook method
that will get called back by the ACE
Acceptor framework to activate this
particular object when its been connected
and created.
And unlike before where the activation
operation simply register the object back
with the reactor for a purely reactive
solution.
This time when this happens, we're going
to go ahead and activate The object to run
in a new thread of control.
As we saw before, the activate method
under the hood will spawn a thread and
then pass in the service run adapter
function that's part of the ACE task
framework.
And that will end up calling the service
hook method on tpc, HTTP Handler.
Here's the service method, keep in mind
that this method is now running in it's
own thread of control.
And it does pretty much exactly what we
we've always been doing.
It turns around and extracts out the get
request from the input stream we got from
the client, it memory maps that get
request URI.
Finding the appropriate content in the
file system.
And then we turn around and use a send
operation to send all the end bytes back
to the client in one transmission
operation.
So this particular approach runs very
efficiently, it runs in a seperate thread
of control.
And therefore, if for any reason we have
blocking.
Because of flow control other threads will
not be perturbed.
Here now we illustrate how we can go ahead
and extend the ACE acceptor in order to
provide the next piece of this particular
solution.
So we're going to implement something
called a TPC acceptor and this is going to
be an acceptor for HTTP objects and TPC of
course stands for The thread for
connection.
Here's the illustration of how to do this.
We go ahead and we instantiate the
template.
The ACE acceptor template to make a TPC,
HTTP acceptor object class.
And this of course, we instantiate with a
TPC HETP handler that we just looked at.
And the ACE_SOCK acceptor so we've got all
those pieces set up.
Now we go ahead and reuse our reactor HTP
server from our earlier acceptor connector
example to make our HTTP server demon.
And then using this, we create a main
thread of control.
Where we've got for the whole function,
for the whole program, we make ourselves
an ace reactor.
We go ahead and create an instance
dynamically allocated of HTTP server demon
and we allocate this dynamically so it
gets cleaned up properly be the reactor
when things shut down.
And then we go ahead and run the reactors
event loop.
And henceforth everything is driven by
callbacks.
And the neat part about this is, as we'll
see, there's really nothing much different
from our original solution.
Except now each incoming request is
handled in its own.
Thread of control, using a thread per
connection approach.
With http 1.0, each request is a
connection.
That's a little different with http 1.1,
where you can actually send multiple
requests on a given connection.
Note the extensive reuse of the design and
the code in this example.
It looks very much like what you looked at
before.
I didn't choose to illustrate the use of
the service configurator framework that we
talked about before.
But I could have.
That would have been another thing we
could have done to have dynamically linked
these capabilities into the address space
of the program when it started to run or
at run time.
So to summarize this particular section,
only very minor changes were aquired to
our design and to our implementation in
order to go from a reactive approach to
the active object approach using thread
per connection.
And it just went from this model we had
here where you had a reactive call factor
of an approach using handle input methods.
To approach it using active object where
we were able to create the TCP/HTTP
handler that could in its own sort of
control.
The reason why there are so few changes
required, is because of the fact that we
have designed the ACE
frameworks[INAUDIBLE] Using a very
carefully thought out variation oriented
design method.
And what that meant was is we spent quite
a long time looking for sources of
commonality and variability.
And every place where we found something
that could vary, for example
single-threaded to multi-threaded, we
would find a way to make that variation as
easy to extend and add as possible, with
as few.
Changes to the design, to the
architecture, even to the implementation.
And so that's why we're able to make these
changes quite, cleanly without have to
perturb the rest of the architecture and
the rest of the design.
This is something that typically occurs
with experience, it occurs with the
opportunity to refactor your software and
continually improve and evolve it.
As before, very little code was required
to do anything related to the application
processing.
We've seen this same application logic
repeatedly now and the frameworks, now
multiple frameworks from ACE, the reactor,
accepter-connector, and ACE task took care
of the event handling, connection
establishment.
Service initialization, concurrency and so
on.
Like I said we didn't do the service
configuration part but we easily could
have.
And it all would have fit together nicely
in a common model.
So the generic framework factors out all
this code in a common way.
And we just have to worry about
programming variability which also is
expressed In a common way as well.
There's still a role for the reactor
pattern by the way.
It's important to note that we haven't
completely gone back and erased all the
earlier parts of our design.
We just moved the reactor pattern out of
the critical performance sensitive path
through the code.
It works quite nicely when used as a way
to handle various kinds of events.
Such as accept event.
And we moved it out of the way so that the
actual data processing now takes place in
separate threads of control.