Welcome to Part 1, in the module on
Patterns and Frameworks for Concurrency
and Synchronization.
In this part of the module, we're going to
describe the active object pattern.
Let's first start by talking about why we
need other patterns for concurrency and
synchronization above and beyond what
we've talked about so far.
If you think about what we've described so
far, our main focus has been on patterns
and frameworks that make our solutions
more modular, more extensible, more
reusable, more configurable.
But we haven't really worried too much yet
about how to make things more high
performance, more scalable.
We did talk a bit about scalability issues
when we discussed the activator pattern,
and I talked about how you can use
activator to spawn a process per request
or a process per connection that's
probably okay for some environments, for a
web server it's a bit overkill to spawn a
process per request there's much better
ways to do it as we'll see here shortly.
Likewise, there's also limitations with
the purely reactive approaches we focused
on for the most part up to now.
A reactive approach is nice, it's very
simple, but there's a couple of issues you
have to be careful of with reactive
approaches having to do with some ways in
which they don't work very effectively
with certain properties of the TCP/IP
protocol, and though they also don't
effective leverage the available
parallelism in modern operating systems,
and hardware.
Let's first talk about the protocol
issues.
Tcp has a nice feature built into it
called flow control.
And the purpose of flow control is to keep
a fast sender, like a supercomputer, from
overwhelming.
The buffering and processing resources of
a slower receiver such as a smartphone.
Clearly a super computer can generate data
a lot faster than a smartphone can consume
it no matter how many cores the smartphone
has.
So TCP has this model that says don't send
more than a certain amount of data at a
time.
And if you try to send more data than the
receiver can consume, it exerts flow
control, which means the sender will block
until the flow control abates.
Well, there's obviously some problems
here.
If we were using a reactive approach and
flow control occurs on a connection, the
server that's reactive will block, waiting
for that flow control to abate, and that
will starve out any other clients from
being able to be processed, which
obviously reduces their quality of
service.
Moreover, you might block because
something is temporarily clogged, but you
could also block because a malicious
client has decided to ignore all the data
being sent to it, in a, as a way to try to
provide some kind of denial-of-service
attack on the server.
So we clearly need to have some other
approach besides a reactive approach.
There's another issue that makes reactive
approaches ineffective as well and that
is, they don't scale up.
If you have hundreds or thousands of users
in a big crowd with their smart phones, or
laptops, or other computing devices, all
pounding away at your server, then you're
simply not going to be able to get any
kind of response time if there's one, one
thread of control.
So we clearly have to find a way to
leverage the available hardware and
software much more effectively.
To do that, we're going to be talking in
this part of the module about applying the
active object pattern.
And we're going to use this active object
pattern to scale up the service
performance, the server performance, by
processing the various HGTP requests, in
separate threads of control.
In particular we're going to have a
separate thread of control for each
connection that comes in from a client.
In general the active object pattern
defines the units of concurrency to be
service requests that are run on a
component.
And it arranges to have these requests for
service work in a manner where the method
that requests the service is decoupled
from the method that executes the service
so those can run concurrently.
We're going to, to talk about a number of
different ways in which this pattern can
be implemented and we're going to start by
talking about the structural dimensions at
first.
It's also important to realize as we do
this discussion that there's many pieces
to the complete active object pattern.
Not all of which are used in practice all
the time.
And so I'll make sure to talk about those
issues as we go through this example.
But first let's talk about the structure.
One part of the structure involves the
client that runs in a thread of control
and invokes a method on the active object.
And this method as we'll see in a second
is actually invoked on a proxy, and what
happens is that proxy converts that method
call into a message called a method
request.
And that method request is passed over to
the active object where it's in queued in
some kind of activation list that the
active objects scheduler manages.
And at some later point in time that
scheduler, running in a separate thread of
control from the client, we'll DQ the
message and do something with it.
If you take a look at this URL at the
bottom of the slide, you'll see a paper
that goes into more details about the
Active Object pattern.
This pattern also is described in the
POSTA2 book in great detail.
Here's a dynamic view that gives you a
little bit more perspective of what's
happening as these various interactions
take place between the various roles in
the pattern.
We start out by having a client invoke a
method call on a proxy, and of course, we
use the proxy pattern.
That's a, that's a gang of 4 pattern as
well as a post to one pattern to be able
to decouple the way in which we invoke an
operation from where the operation
actually runs.
In our particular case, the proxy will
convert the method request.
The method call into a message called a
method request and this method request
basically contains message fields it
cooresponds to the data, it keeps track of
the name of the method.
They also have some return information as
well, and it gets bundled up into an
object that you can use to pass from the
proxy back into the active object portion.
The proxy part also creates something
called a future, and the future is going
to be used to pass back to the client
later, so it can subsequently retrieve the
results, if any that occur when the active
object invokes this request.
What happens next is that the method
request is then passed to the scheduler.
And the scheduler then incues this method
request on an activation list and it gives
back the future to the client.
And then at some point down the road and
this, this depends on a variety of
different factors, depends on scheduling
constraints that the scheduler may know
about.
It may depend on certain guard conditions
that the method request knows about.
It may simply run things in FIFO order, it
all depends on how you implement things.
The schedule will then queue the request
and then later pull it off, convert it
back into a method call on to the servant
that actually carries out the request.
And after the servant is done, the servant
will end up, as a side effect, updating
the future so the client can then get the
result.
There's a couple of ways in which clients
can get results from futures.
One way they can do it, is they can
periodically poll the future and say, is
the result ready, is the result ready, is
the result ready.
Or they might do a timed poll where
they'll say, I'll wait up to a couple
seconds for the result, and then I'll go
off and do some other things, that's one
model.
An alternative model, which is probably
more scalable in many ways, is to use
callbacks.
So what happens here is, when the future's
value is updated, when the server has
finished its processing, then a callback
takes place to deliver those results back
to the client.
So let's talk about how we can apply the
active object pattern to our JAWS web
server.
One way to do this, which is supported
quite nicely in ACE, is to implement
active objects by making a very small
number of tweaks to our existing acceptor
connector based version.
Which itself, as you recall, is based on
the a, ACE reactor.
And just extends that in certain ways.
So what we're going to do here is we're
going to create some new capabilities that
inherit from ACE_Acceptor and
ACE_Service_Handler, and they're going to
create new classes that run things as an
active object as opposed to a reactive
approach.
In particular, we create a new subclass of
service handler called TPC, for thread per
connection, HTTP handler.
And that's going to run as an active
object and it's going to receive the
request data that comes in from the client
on a per connection basis and process that
data and then send it back.
The nice particular way of doing things is
it allows us to be able to have different
threads for different connections, so we
have a thread per connection model.
And if those connections happen to block,
then or if those threads happen to block
while they're processing the data.
On the connection to the flow control or
some other condition, not a problem.
Other threads handling other requests from
other connections can proceed
concurrently.
Notice that this particular way of doing
things has a couple of interesting
variations that are above and beyond what
you might expect if you just look at the
active object pattern description in a
simple way.
One thing to note here, is that part of
the processing that's taking place here is
actually occurring inside the operating
system kernel.
So getting the data that comes in from the
network sockets and then converting it
into something that can be passed as a
method request up to the user space
thread.
That's done initially from the, from the
colonel side.
The actual active object portion is
running in the TPC, HTTP handler in a
separate thread of control.
And so that's going to be able to run
separately, but that's passing the data
between the different layers though this
socket connection.
Another thing to note here is we're only
doing a subset of the full blown active
object pattern.
We're not really handling futures.
We're not really doing servants.
We're doing more of the message passing
variant of this pattern.
And if you read the posted two book or the
other URL I sent you that and showed you
before, that will give you an idea of how
these different variants work.
It's actually very common to use the
variants for a number of reasons we'll
talk about.
So let's talk about some of the benefits
and limitations of this pattern.
Some of the benefits are you could
actually use concurrency and simplify
synchronization complexity by treating
method requests as the unit of concurrent
execution.
So this is a fairly intuitive thing for an
object oriented developer to make a method
call on an object.
And the fact that those methods turn into
these messages or method request and are
run concurrently, that's kind of icing on
the cake to be able to get things to run
better.
You can also have a schedule that can use
various kinds of sophisticated constraint
based reasoning and guards and so on, in
order to determine the order in which to
run the request.
We're not really doing that in our
particular example here, we're doing
things in a more FIFO orient.
Order, but the complete pattern can be
used more flexibly.
Another benefit of this pattern, of
course, is that if your operating system
and hardware support it, you can
transparently leverage the parallelism
that's available.
So you could have these different method
requests running in separate threads of
control.
Another benefit that you might be able to
get from this pattern is that there are
times in which the method that invokes the
operation and the order in which things
are invoked will be different from the
order in which the methods are actually
executed by the scheduler.
You might order things in a way that
satisfies scheduling constraints.
satisfies various priorities.
So higher priority users get preference
over lower priority users and so on and so
forth.
So those are some of the, the benefits of
the pattern.
As always, there are some limitations.
One of the limitations that you often run
into with these kinds of concurrency
models is that there is some overhead
incurred With respect to context
switching, synchronization, data movement,
memory allocation, deallocation, copying
and so on, needed to move things between
these different boundaries.
Between the different thread boundaries.
And if you're running long running
operations, not really an issue.
If you're running short running operations
The overhead may actually swamp the
performance benefits, if you're not
careful.
Another potential issue here is that when
you start having multiple threads of
control running, then your debugging can
be more complicated.
It may take a while to figure out how to
set break points.
Some environments don't do a very good job
of supporting concurrent debugging.
And even environments that have pretty
good support for concurrent debugging.
You may experience the condition where the
behavior you get when you're in the
debugger might not match the behavior you
get when you're running in the production
environment.
Because the scheduling order may be
different, things may be serialized and
synchronized in different ways, so certain
types of defects and faults may be hard to
identify.
The last thing I want to reemphasize here
is that in practice people often use
subsets of active object more than they
will implement the full blown pattern and
there's nothing wrong with the it's a very
useful way to think about structure your
software.
And even if you don't need to have the
complete proxy experience, the complete
server servant experience, even in
situations where you don't need
complicated schedulers with complicated
constraints, and so on.
You can still get a benefit from a design
point of view of thinking about your
program in terms of active objects.