Welcome to Part 4 in the module on
Patterns and Frameworks for Service
Configuration and Activation.
In previous parts of this module, we
described the component configurator
pattern, and we discussed the ACE Service
configurator framework that realizes this
pattern in portable ways on many different
operating system environments.
We then discussed how to apply this
particular pattern in the implementation
in ACE to make our JAWS web server more
configurable, more extensible, more
dynamically changeable and assembable at
run time.
And now we're going to talk about another
pattern that goes a little bit further to
make it possible to be able to create
server instances, dynamically in response
to incoming requests from clients.
And this will be what's called the
activator pattern.
We'll use the activator pattern to further
extend our pattern language for JAWS, so
that not only are we going to use wrapper
facade for portability, reactor for event
handling, acceptor connector for
connection establishment and service
initialization, and component configurator
for dynamically composing the
implementations of our server.
We're also going to be able to activate
our server process on the fly, when client
requests come in.
So let's first start by talking about the
motivation for why you might want to use
this pattern in the first place.
The main reason for using this pattern is
to try to minimize resource utilization.
Imagine you're in an environment that's
resource constrained, you don't have all
the memory in the world, and it may also
be somewhat dynamic, there may be periods
of time when there's lots of requests.
There may be other points of time where
there's not a lot of requests for certain
kinds of services.
So keeping processes running all the time,
even when they're not being accessed, may
not be the most effective way of utilizing
the resources.
So how can we go about trying to make this
work effectively?
Well, one thing we might want to do, is
apply the activator pattern, in order to
activate and deactivate server resources
dynamically, based on access patterns by
clients.
In our particular case, of course, we're
focusing on activating and deactivating
our JAWS web server processes, but in
other cases, of course, it could be used
for other examples as well.
The activator pattern automates scalable,
on-demand activation and deactivation of
services, that run in so-called service
execution contexts, think process in this
particular case, in order to run services
that are accessed by many clients, without
consuming resources excessively.
Another way to look at this, from a
structural point of view, is we want to
find some way to allow clients to activate
servers, to run services using an
activator as an intermediary, in order to
get the job done, in order to start things
up on demand.
This particular pattern appears very
briefly in the POSA 4 book.
A longer version of the pattern can be
found at the URL, at this particular link
and it's, it's appeared several other
places, and this is the latest incarnation
of describing this particular pattern.
This is a dynamic view of how things work.
Basically what happens is, a client comes
along and it invokes an operation that
causes a request to be send to a server.
But rather than going directly to the
server first, its actually intercepted by
an activator, and the activator checks to
figure out how to run the service, and
then it goes ahead typically and launches
a server process, and then passes the
request on to the server process to carry
out the work.
You can do these things at various
granularities, you can activate these
things on each method call, on each
transaction, you can keep them running for
a while.
There are different ways to go ahead and,
and structure the particular dynamic
activations of this approach.
So let's talk about how we might apply the
activator pattern to the JAWS web server
example.
What we're going to do, is we're going to
leverage something called lnetd, which is
a very common and popular UNIX
superserver.
There's actually implementations of Inetd
for other platforms as well.
Inetd supports two different kinds of
services.
Internal services, that run in the Inetd
process itself, and these include very
short lived services like echo or daytime.
It also supports so called external
services, these are typically longer
running operations, that run in separate
processes.
That the Inetd superserver, will go ahead
and fork and exact and do the appropriate
socket, bind, listen accept calls in order
to carry out getting these services
connected to their clients.
Examples of, of services that run this way
would be things like FTP or secure FTP,
TelNet or secure shells, or even HTTP, web
services what we are going to be doing
here.
Take a look at this link on Wikipedia, to
find out more information to find out more
information about what Inetd is, and how
it work works.
So let's talk about how this might
actually play our in practice.
So, a client would go ahead and establish
a connection on some server, at whatever
port number it thinks the web server's
running at.
Let's just use port 80 to make things more
concrete.
What would actually happen would be that
the Inetd superserver, would be listening
on that particular port.
And it would do this, because it would
read a directive out of a configuration
file, called etc inetd.conf.
And this configuration file will tell it,
to run a certain service at a particular
port number, and have a certain demon
process launchable when a connection
request on that port comes in from a
client.
When a client goes ahead and connects to
that port number, the Inetd superserver
will accept that connection, spawn the
appropriate server process, in this case
it might be running the JAWS web server
implementation.
And then once that web server
implementation is running, then when the
client send the get request to what they
think is Port 80m that is no longer being
serviced by Inetd its now being serviced
by the server that was spout on demand by
Inetd.
So that server of course receive the get
request, do the processing in the ways
we've seen before, and then send that
result back to the client.
The client doesn't really know this has
been done by a superserver, it just thinks
its been initiated, and talking directly
to the server the whole time.
Which is some of the powerful pieces of
using this particular implementation of
the activator pattern.
This design will use memory more
efficiently, because the server will only
run when it's actually being accessed by a
client.
This makes sense, of course, if you don't
have an environment where there is
continual workload.
If you had continual workload, you're
probably better off just launching the
server, and keeping it running
indefinitely.
Because there is some overhead to,
shutdown and restart the server processes
on demand, every time a client request
shows up.
So lets talk about some of the benefits
and limitations of this pattern.
Some of the benefits obviously are the
fact that we're not going to use resources
unless we absolutely need them.
We're not going to be allocating virtual
memory, we're not going to be taking up
slots in the process table.
We're not going to be doing other things
that will otherwise make the resource
utilization higher, if nobody is actually
availing themselves of our resources that
we're providing.
Another benefit we get from this, is we're
able to get a nice, easy coarse grain
concurrency model.
What we basically get here, is a process
per request, or a process per connection
like approach.
And, that will allow us to be able to get
around some of the limitations we've
talked about to this point, by using the
reactor pattern to have only one thread of
control to process the request from
clients.
Now we could have as many processes as
there are clients, that are sending us get
requests and making connections, at any
given point in time.
You have to be careful there, of course,
because you might end up having a lot of
resources tied up that could be dealt
better with other concurrency models, like
the thread pools, we'll talk about later
when we get to those sections.
Modularity, testability and reusability
can also be approved by this approach,
because we're building our components out
of more modular pieces, where we can do
them in isolation.
We can test them, and then only when we're
convinced that they are going to work
properly, do we go ahead and integrate
them in to our actual environment.
Needless to say, as with all different
patterns and all different approaches,
there are some limitations with this
approach.
So, not unlike with component
configurator, you don't necessarily know
what's going to run, until the requests
start showing up from clients.
And so, there may be some determi,
determinism issues that may take longer to
start things up.
You probably don't want to run an
implementation of this pattern in a real
time system, because things will take
different amounts of time to run.
The first time you run something may be
different from the next time, because it
may still be running the next time, and
that may be a problem for schedulability
analysis and so on.
Another problem, not unlike component
configuration and the component
configurator pattern, is what do you do
about reliability or security?
When you're starting to launch things
dynamically, you have to be careful that
people don't slip in trojan horses, that
get launched, that do malware or nefarious
things to the state of your, your system
while it's running.
For that reason, by the way, people have
begun to move away to some extent from
using the Init.D approach in some
environments, where they can't have full
trust and control over what's actually
being run.
And of course another issue, is just
potential for increased run time, overhead
and infrastructure complexity.
There are more moving parts, there are
conceivably more things to go wrong.
There's this additional latency for
launching the servers on demand.
The concurrency model we talked about,
process per connection, process per
request, may be heavier weight than you
really want to use in practice.
It turns out, as we've discussed here,
that you can easily combine these patterns
for service configuration and activation.
So, in this particular example here, we
can use the activator pattern to bring in
a server process on demand when a client
connects, and we could also use the ACE
service configurator, service
configuration framework, in order to
configure the state of the services
running in that server, when it's brought
in and started dynamically.
So this gives you a tremendous amount of
flexibility and control, over what kinds
of things are running, and when they run.
And you just have to make sure you have a
good grasp of the patterns, a good
understanding of the frameworks, and a
deep knowledge of the security
implications and reliability implications,
to make sure these approaches work
properly for the environments in which you
run.