[MUSIC]
So far we've seen that we can use
Spring to automatically configure and
launch our application.
But one of the questions we haven't answer
is,
how does Spring know how to construct our
application?
What if our video service has some
dependency on another object
that we would like to be able to configure
when we
launch the application, so that we could
provide for example an
interface to the different ways that we
store videos in memory.
Or potentially even store them on disk,
and then plug in different
classes that implement that interface into
the video service depending on our needs.
Spring supports a facility called
Dependency Injection, that we've talked
about.
That can automatically provide the
bindings between the actual implementation
of
an interface and the usage of that
interface in our various controllers.
We're other other classes, so let's take a
look in
this example of how we can use this to our
advantage.
So in this version, if you open up the
video
service again, we'll see that we've added
a new concept.
And that is rather than using a direct
list of videos that we're
going to store in memory, instead we've
created an abstraction called a video
repository.
And if you'll look down here a little
lower, we'll see
that this video repository has similar
methods to what we had before.
It has a method to add a video, and it
had, it has
a method to get the list of videos that
have currently been added.
So if we go, and actually look at this
video repository.
We'll see that it's just a simple Java
interface that provides this functionality
that we would
expect of some storage system for storing
videos
may be it in memory or somewhere else.
So once we've defined this interface, we
can plug different implementations of the
interface
into the video service and not have
to change how video service operates
directly.
Instead, if we wanted to provide an
implementation that does something
different, for example, one version might
allow duplicate videos to be stored.
Whereas, another version may not allow
duplicate videos to be stored.
It may only store one copy.
So if we want to be able to provide
those different implementations of that
interface, we can use
the interface here in the video service,
and then
add and get the videos directly using that
interface.
Now if you see this, this brings up a
question,
which is, we aren't directly instantiating
our video service object.
Instead, we are asking sprain to go and
launch a web container, and
to automatically discover our controllers
and put them into the web container.
So if we aren't directly instantiating
some implementation of
video service, and assigning it to this
member variable.
How does Spring know what should be
assigned
to this variable and how to fulfill this
dependency?
Well, to answer that, we can look at the
application class, which is where we do
the initial launch of our, our application
and tell Spring to go and configure us.
And what we'll see here is that we've
listed at
enable auto configuration and at component
scam which as we've
talked about before tells Spring to go and
look in
a particular package for all of our
controllers when other components.
And then the at enable auto
configuration says, go, and automatically
configure them.
And we talked a little bit about this
before.
So what's going to happen is, when Spring
goes and
scans our controller, in this case the
video service,
oOne of the things it's going to see is
that this member variable has an at
autowired annotation.
And what this at autowired annotation
tells Spring is, this is a dependency that
I require that I want you to automatically
provide for me when you construct me.
So Spring is going to have to figure out
how
to resolve the dependency and find some
object that
implements video service and automatically
set the value of
this member variable to a reference to
that object.
So if you go and then look in application,
what
we see is that we have a method called
video repository.
That's annotated with @being.
And what this method does, is it tells
Spring, here
is the implementation that I want you to
use for the video repository.
And so what Spring is going to do is when
it goes and looks at the video service,
it's
going to see that it needs to have a
video repository implementation to
@autowire into this member variable.
So it's then going to go look at the
application class which is the
configuration of the application
and say are there any @ being annotative
methods that return an instance of a video
repository.
And in this case, it's going to say this
method
video repository will return an instance
of a video repository.
So it's going to call this method.
It's going to get back the instance or the
specific implementation of the video
repository that we create here.
And then, it's automatically going to take
that
value and assign it to the video's member
variable
and video service, and anywhere else that
we
refer to video repository and annotate it
with auto-wired.
Spring will automatically go and find
those places
where we are expecting that video
repository to be
at autowired and it will automatically
assign those
member variables the repository
implementation that we returned here.
So the way to think about this is that
Spring is providing us a way to where
we can have an interface that is used by
multiple class.
So, let's say that these are the users,
or the class users that depend upon our
interface.
So we have a series of objects that depend
upon
an interface or some object being provided
to them.
And then our application where our
configuration object 'cause it doesn't
have to be called application provides the
actual implementation that gets used
at run time.
So, Spring goes and finds all of the users
because the users
have @Autowired member variables that
refer to the type.
So, if a particular member variable is
@Autowired annotated.
Then Spring has to go and look in the
configuration
objects that we provide to it, in this
case, application.
It's going to find a method that
returns an implementation of that
particular interface.
And then, it will automatically assign
whatever
value is returned from that method to
all of our member variables are places
where we refer to it in other classes.
So our class users have the autowire on
the place
where they need a particular dependency
like a video repository.
And then, our application provides the
implementation of
all of those used interfaces that are at
autowire.
And Spring automatically figures out how
to solve the complex dependency
graph that we have to deal with in order
to instantiate the various objects.
So it will automatically figure out what
order
things need to be instantiated in, do that
instantiation.
And then assign all of the actual
implementations of an
autowired interface to all of the places
it's referred to.
And if for some reason we have something
marked as @Autowired that doesn't show up
in
your application, then when when you try
to
startup, Spring is automatically going to
throw an exception.
So, in this example here where we are
creating the actual implementation of the
video repository.
If we want to simply change the
implementation that spring is going to
use,
all have to do is change this
to a different implementation of video
repository.
And when we start up our application,
Spring is automatically
going to take this new implementation that
we are creating here.
And bind it to all of the places where we
refer to a video repository.
So, in order to have different
configurations of your
application, you can create different
classes that implement at configuration
and provide different values for the
different dependencies that
are supposed to be at auto wired into your
application.
[BLANK_AUDIO]