[MUSIC]
Cloud services have access to huge amounts
of
storage, that allow them to aggregate
information from multiple,
mobile clients and then be able to search
that information and return it back to
mobile clients.
So one of the important functions that we
have
to learn how to build in our cloud
services for
mobile clients, is the capability to take
advantage of all
these storage resources and store data on
a clients behalf.
And then be able to search that data and
find
what a particular client needs and return
it to them.
Now this whole process looks very similar
to what
we saw when we were sending object data
over HTTP.
We would have some objects, that we were
working with, either on
the client or on the service side, we
would then marshal them,
into an HTTP body of a message.
And then, on the other side, we would have
to unmarshal that data back into objects.
So all of this would happen on the client,
and then this would happen on the server.
So we would have this whole process where
we were
taking objects, we were converting them
into HTTP messages to
send to the cloud based service, and then
on the
server side we were converting those
bodies back into objects.
And we saw that there were ways to
simplify this using
various libraries like Jackson, which can
automatically convert an object into
JSON, which can be placed into an HTTP
body, and then
automatically take that JSON and convert
it back into an object.
And we used Retrofit to do a lot of this
for us, in the earlier discussions.
Now, what we'd like to be able to do
is something similar for storing data on
the server.
So, on the server side, we also are
working with objects.
So we will have objects, just like we did
on the client side, and then what we want
to do is we want take the information in
those objects, and we want to convert it
into some format, which then gets stored
in a database.
And there are multiple formats and types
of databases that we might be storing in.
But one of the keys things that we have to
do, is we have to marshal again our
objects into, or map our objects, into the
database and the format of the database.
So down here in the database, probably,
the format is something like, rows and
columns.
So, we've got database rows and we've got
database columns and we have to
figure out how do we go from an object to
this format in the database.
And the way that we can do this, one way
to do it at least, is to always just write
our own code that goes and takes each
object and
decides how we map that object into a
database table.
So for example, we might take each object
and map each object into a row of the
database, and then we might set each
column to
a particular property or member variable
of that object.
So we can put the member variable values
in the
columns, and we can map our object
instances to different rows.
But if we go and do something like this,
we're doing a lot of work, because every
time
we save an object, we have to figure out
how to convert that object into a table
format.
And then every time we want to go and get
data back, we have to figure out
how we search these tables, and we have to
write our own code to search the tables.
And then, once we find the data that we
want in the database, then
we have to convert that data in those,
either table rows or wha, columns or
whatever part of the table it is that
we've stored our data into, we have
to convert that data back into object so
that we can do something with it.
And this whole process is normally called
object relational
mapping, at least for traditional
relational databases.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
This term still gets used, even
with non-relational databases like noSQL
databases.
We're still doing this whole process
of essentially mapping objects into the
database.
And some people call it ORM, some people
call it other things when it hits noSQL
databases.
But regardless of what it is, the, the
fundamental fact
remains that we have to take objects, and
we have
to convert them on the server side in
order to
store them into some format that the
database can understand.
And then when we want to use them, we have
to be able to find them,
convert that data back into objects, and
do
something with it, because Java operates
on objects.
And we don't really want to operate on raw
primitives and database tables which don't
make sense in the Java language or may not
be strongly typed, like we would like.