[MUSIC]
In Java, there's a tool that we can use to
help us go from objects down
to the database, search the database and
then
return that data back as objects to our
code.
In this tool is a framework called JPA, or
the Java Persistence API.
And so, the idea behind JPA is that we go
and annotate
our objects using Java annotations and
tell JPA about how to store our objects,
in a database.
So we go and we add these annotations to
our objects.
And then JPA can automatically look at our
objects and look at those annotations, and
figure out
the appropriate way to turn our objects
automatically
into rows and columns and tables within a
database.
So JPA uses this information to marshal or
map our objects down into the underlying
database.
And then whenever we want objects back, it
uses this same
information to help us get objects back
out of the database.
So JPA is an incredibly useful tool and
will allow us to write less
code and know that our mapping will
hopefully be done 100% correctly all the
time.
So we don't have to worry about making
errors and how we can convert these
objects.
And in fact, what you'll see is with a
very small amount
of code, we can begin utilizing the
database in our cloud services.
So there's not a huge amount of work or
things that
we have to learn in order to be able to
leverage JPA.
With some very simple annotations, we can
start immediately
taking our objects and storing them in a
database.
Let's take a look at JPA and how it can
help us to store information.
So, let's think about our, our video
service.
So far, we have a cloud service where
users using their mobile clients can
upload videos
to the service and then it stores objects,
video objects representing those uploaded
videos in a list.
Now, this is a very simple approach
because as long as that service
is in memory, as long as it's running, as
long as the service, the
server that it's on hasn't been turned
off, we have access to all
of those video objects and we can see what
has been uploaded so far.
But the moment somebody stops our cloud
service for accepting
these videos or the moment that the server
that it's
running on gets turned off, all of the
information was
in memory, that list of video objects, is
suddenly gone.
And the next time we start up our cloud
service, we
don't have access to those video objects
that we previously created.
So we need some way of creating instances
of an object and then telling
JPA to go and save those objects for us so
that in the future, if
the service gets turned off or the server
gets shut down, when we start
back up, they will have been persisted in
the database and still accessible to us.
So what we're going to do is create a
simple video object and show you
how easy it is to actually store instances
of an object in a database.
Now, the way that we do this is we have to
create a class and
provide annotations to JPA explaining how
instances of
that class should be stored in a database.
So let's take a look at a simple example.
So we're going to create a class to
represent the videos that we are storing.
So we'll have a simple video class.
And what we'd like to do is store
some information in the member variables
in this class.
So we might have private.
And we'll just fix that.
Long because we're going to store a whole
bunch of these things.
We're hoping our service will be like
YouTube.
ID.
So we're going to have an ID for each of
our videos.
That's going to be a numeric ID.
And then we'll store, let's just say to be
simple for the moment,
a string, which is the name of the video.
Now we could go and add a whole bunch of
other member variables
here, but this is just a simple example,
so let's start with this.
Now, what we need to do is we need to tell
JPA that
we want it to store instances of this
class in the database for us.
And the first thing we have to do is we
have to declare that this is
a type of object or a type of class that
is something that can be stored.
And the way that we do that is by
simply adding the @Entity annotation from
JPA to the class.
And what this Entity annotation does is it
says this is something that can be
persistent.
Now the second thing we need to do is
since
we want to be able to search for these
objects after
we've stored them and we need a way of
accessing
them and referencing them, we need to give
them an identity.
So normally, when we go and create
objects,
they get stored at some memory address and
we
don't have to worry so much about each one
of them having a unique in, you know, ID.
We just know that underneath the hood,
Java provides a
unique memory address where each one of
them is stored.
But we need to do something equivalent so
that we can know and address each of these
video objects once they've been stored
individually and that
we need to do that with a unique ID.
So to do that, we simply pick one of our
properties that we know is going to be
unique or we would like to be filled in
with a unique value, and we say @Id.
So this is telling JPA that this ID right
here is going to be our ID property.
Now, we could've had any member variable
with any
naming provided for the ID so long as it's
of a type like a string or a long that JPA
knows how to use as a unique identifier.
And it doesn't have to be named ID.
I just happened to name mine ID in
this purpose, in this example, but we
could have
named it, you know, video number or
anything
else as long as we have this @Id
annotation.
The @Id annotation tells JPA that this is
a
property or a member variable that we want
to use to uniquely identify this object.
But we still have the problems, we have to
make sure that every
time this member variable is set, that it
gets provided a unique ID.
Now, we could go and try to manually
figure out
how to assign these IDs to make sure
they're unique.
But it would be easier if we could just
ask JPA to create unique
IDs for us on the fly so that we don't
have to worry about it.
And so, that's what we're going to do.
We can add a second annotation, and I'm
just going to move over
here to the left, because this is going to
be a long annotation.
And don't worry if you can't remember all
of these longer annotations.
They're easy to Google or to look up in
your [INAUDIBLE]
previous code, sorry about that, to figure
out what you should add.
So we're going to add @GeneratedValue and
then
we're going to say strategy equals and
then,
I apologize if this runs off the screen
and
hopefully I'll be able to get it in the
screen.
Generation
type.auto and if
I got really lucky, all of that stayed on
the screen and hopefully I did.
But what this extra annotation that I just
added says is basically, @GeneratedValue,
meaning, this is something I'm expecting
JPA to fill in a value for.
I'm expecting it to generate a value for
this.
And then the strategy is I want it to
automatically generate the value that
should go in here.
And if you're having trouble reading this
annotation because
of my handwriting, the code samples that
are provided
along with this lecture will make this
much clearer
about what this looks like and how it
works.
But at this point, this is all we actually
have to provide in
order for JPA to be able to persist
instances of this video class.
All we have to do is construct a
video class and very importantly, just
assign the name.
Because we don't want to assign the ID
because we're asking
the JPA infrastructure to go and assign
that ID for us.
We just want to assign the name.
So we create a video object, maybe we have
some getters and setters.
We assign a value for name and then we ask
JPA to go and store this object.
And two things are going to happen.
One is JPA is automatically going to take
this object and convert
it into the tables and the rows and
columns of our
database, or depending on the actual
database implementation, maybe it does
something completely different and we
don't have to worry about that.
And two, after it's stored it and it's
figured
out its unique identifier in the database,
it's going to generate
a unique ID for us and assign it to the ID
so that we don't have to do that.
So, it's not only going to from these
three simple annotations, these are
actually two related annotations, but from
these three simple annotations, it's not
only
going to store the objects in a database
for us, but it's going to give
us a way of uniquely identifying them and
referencing them in our code.
Which we'll see is very helpful when we
want
to query and look up data that's been
previously stored.