[MUSIC]
>> When you're using configurations to
automatically construct
your application through dependency
injection in Spring, there are
a number of annotations that Spring
provides that vastly
simplify your life and work when creating
these configurations.
So let's assume that we have a
configuration, you know, again, in our
Application class.
And, we have annotated this with
@configuration.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now we could go and think of every
different
component in our application and define an
individual method
with, that's annotated with @ being to
say, here's
is how you go an construct that particular
component.
Here's the interface as the return type.
And here's the actual implementation of
that interface
that I want you to use when it's
referenced.
However, it's a lot of work, particularly
if there's only a single implementation
of an interface or you have your
implementations divided in some nice way.
For example where all of the imp-,
implementations that are related in some
way all live in the same package.
And wouldn't it be nice if you could tell
Spring to
automatically go and find all of the
implementations of the various interfaces
and automatically associate those
implementations with
the interfaces so that wherever you
@Autowired that interface in, it will use
the implementation that it's discovered.
The way that you do that in Spring is you
can say @ComponentScan
and you can provide it a series of package
names, Java package
names, or prefixes to Java package names.
So we could have com.mobile.
And
Spring is automatically going to go and
scan that package, find
all of the interfaces, look at any
annotations on any of
the interfaces or any of the classes in
that package as
well, and then based on what it discovers
it will automatically decide.
For example, if it finds an interface for
something that is @Autowired throughout
your application and then it finds an
implementer of that interface, it will
automatically associate that implemented
with that
interface and then wherever there is an
@Autowired for that interface it will take
the implementer in and insert it.
This of course is assuming that there is a
one to one mapping based on the component
scanned packages.
So if it scans this package and
there are multiple implementations of an
interface, it
can't automatically decide which one
should go went
into a particular object when it's being
autowired.
Instead, this is good for when you
have either exactly one implementation of
an interface,
or you've divided up your implementations
into packages in some way so that you can
component scan one package that will have
all of the implementations, but only a
single
implementation of each interface and
automatically allow Spring
to figure out which one should go where.
Another important annotation to know about
it
is the annotation that tells Spring to go
and look for all of the @Autowired
annotations and actually go and fill them
in.
If you don't add this particular
annotation to your
configuration, Spring won't go and look
for those@Autowired annotations.
So the annotation that we need
to add to our configuration is
@EnableAutoConfiguration.
And what this tells Spring to do is go and
look for, go look for the
@Autowired annotations.
And wherever you find one of them,
automatically fill it in with an
appropriate value.
So commonly you see
@EnableAutoConfiguration and
@ComponentScan used together.
So, you'll automatically go and find a
particular set of implementations
that you want to use that you define,
defined in some package and
then you will automatically enable auto
configuration through
@EnableAutoConfiguration so that Spring
will go and look for all the @Autowired's
and fill them in.
And using these two you can simplify your
configuration class,
because you don't have to go and
explicitly define a
bean with a @ bean and then a method to
retrieve the bean for every single
component in your application.
You can simply allow Spring to discover
them
and then to automatically autowire them
for you.
Without going to all of the work they're
defining each one individually or doing
anything else.
Now, there is a slight downside to this.
The downside is, is this that going
and actually doing something like
automatically scanning all
of the classes, and in particular package
and all of the sub-packages off of this.
So if this is com.mobile and you have
com.mobile.data as a package and
com.mobile.http as a package, all of those
sub-packages will be scanned as well.
So if you have lots and lots of classes on
your class path in all in the
sub-packages, it can take
a while at launch time to actually go and
scan
them all, read all of the autowired
instances, and configure everything.
But the important thing to note is that
this is only when you're starting up your
application.
So as long as you're running in
an environment where you're starting your
application
up infrequently, which is the case in most
environments, this isn't a big deal.
There actually are a subset of cloud
environments where the cloud service
provider may shut your application down
when it's not receiving enough requests.
And these are things like Google App
Engine.
And in those cases, if you do this it can
be a performance hit to your application
in Google App Engine.
And there's lots of information on the web
about the impact
of auto-configuration and component
scanning
on applications on Google App Engine.
So just be aware that this can simplify
your life,
but at the same time, it can also create
problems
from a performance perspective if you are
running on specific
providers and they are continually
restarting your application over and over.
But in most cases this is not a
performance set that we care about.