[MUSIC]
So far we've only talked about the server
side building cloud based services for
mobile devices.
But an important part that we have to
consider is
well, how does the mobile device
communicate with the cloud service?
So, we're going to look now, at the
Android
side of communicating and interacting with
these services.
And we're going to use an open source
library call Retrofit.
Retrofit is produced by Square, which
produces these card stripe readers
that you maybe have seen on an iPad or
another mobile device.
And what Retrofit allows you to do is to
create
a strong interface in Java to your cloud
based service.
And then Retrofit will take care of
converting any parameters that
pass into interactions with that interface
and the appropriate HTTP request.
Send those requests to the service, get
the response
back and then convert the values back into
Java types.
So it handles a lot of these complex
conversion and checking
logic that we saw in the servlet, but it
does it on the client side.
So let's take a look at what Retrofit
looks like and how we interact with it.
And it will make a lot more sense as to
what it's doing for us.
So let's say that we want to interact with
the video service that we just built in
the servlet.
First we would do is create an interface
in Java to
represent this service that we are going
to interact with.
So we'll just call our interface video
service.
The second thing we need to do, is we need
to define what are
the methods that we can invoke on this
service that lives in the cloud.
That's going to be handled and, and
implemented by this servlet that we just
created.
Well, the first method is we need to be
able to get a list of the videos.
So in this case we're just going to get
the list of
videos as a string because that's how they
were output by that servlet.
And we'll call this getVideos.
And this going to return the list of all
videos that are currently on the server.
And second, what we want to do, is we want
to add a method to
add a video.
And then we're going to need a couple
parameters for this
then we're going to need a string
parameter for the name.
We'll pass the URL as a string and
then finally we'll have a long which we
know the servlet needs for the duration.
So, we've now defined a Java interface
which tells us
about that service that we're going to be
interacting with it.
And it, with, and it provides us a strong
interface, and strong Java typing for
interacting with that service.
Now, how do we get from here to HTTP
requests that we'd like to
send to the service, we would like to have
some object that implements the video
service interface that we can call
getVideos on and it will go and send the
HTTP request, convert the response back
into a string and return it to us.
Similarly, we would like to have an object
where if it, it implements
this interface and we can call addVideo
and we can pass in name, URL
and duration and the object that
implements
this interface will automatically convert
that information
into an HTTP request, send it to our
servlet and then get the response.
And, let our, our code know that this
method has succeeded in being executed.
And this is where Retrofit fills in is it
provides the magic behind
this interface that automatically converts
this interface
into an object that implements the
interface.
And can automatically do everything we
just said.
It can, when you invoke the getVideos
method on
it, automatically send the appropriate
HTTP request to our service.
So, what we need to do for Retrofit is we
need to tell it how to
convert a method call on this into an HTTP
request on our servlet.
And the way we do that is with an
annotation.
We add the annotation get in this case
because we want to send a get request
and we know that our servlet was listening
to the path /video.
So, whenever somebody goes and invokes
getVideos, the
Retrofit library is going to look and see,
I need to send this as a request,
as a get request because we're specifying
the HTTP method, to the path/video.
And we'll see where the server and some
other information comes in in a minute.
So here we're telling it, here is how
you convert a method calling this into a
request.
It's going to be a get request on this
particular path and then take
whatever you get back and turn it into a
string and pass it back.
The addVideos gets a little bit more
interesting.
We now are passing parameters to the
servlet.
So first we need to tell it the correct
method, so we're going to say this is an
@post, and this also going to be to the
/video path, which is where the servlet
was listing.
Except we want this one to be
@formURLEncoded
so we're telling it that we
want it to go encode the, the body of this
post request using
URL encoding, so this is going to look
like your submitting a form on a web page.
We then need to tell it how these
parameters map into the parameters in the
HTTP request.
So we add @field.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Name.
We add @fieldURL
and the we add @fieldDuration.
And
so now, we've not only created the method,
but we've
annotated it, describing how you convert a
method call on this.
In this case, when you invoke addVideo,
Retrofit's going to go and
see this is supposed to be a post request,
set to /video.
The body of it should be a form URL
encoded body.
Then, each of these parameters should be
inserted in to that body in URL encoding.
In this case the name, the value of
it should be inserted into the name
parameter.
The URL should be inserted in to the URL
And the duration should be inserted, in to
the duration parameter.
So we're basically creating a URL encoded
form body, posting
it to /video and Retrofit is doing all of
this for us behind the scenes.
It's automatically figuring out, based on
our interface, how
to construct an object that can send these
HTTP requests.
So, this is the first component of
building a framework
to interact with that video service is
building the interface to describe it
and then getting Retrofit enough
information that it can go and translate
method calls in this interface into HTTP
request on the actual service.
Once we've created this interface to
describe our service in Java.
We can then use the Retrofit library to
automatically
create an object that implements the
interface and will translate
all the method calls on that interface
into the
actual HTTP request that we described with
the Retrofit annotations.
So let's look at how we go about creating
that object that we're going to use to
implement the interface and translate our
method calls into actual HTTP requests.
So to do that, what we need to do is
create a retrofit RestAdapter.
And the Retrofit library provides a nice
fluent API.
If you're not familiar with fluent APIs
you can go and look it up, but you'll
probably quickly see the API coming
forward as
I start showing you how to build a
RestAdapter.
Now we say New RestAdapter.Builder.
Then we need to tell it where the server
is by calling setEndpoint.
In this case, we're going to say something
like local host
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then we say, build, and this tells the
underlying Retrofit library
actually going build the RestAdapter that
has that particular endpoint.
Once we've got that adapter, then we can
go and actually create an object that
implements our video service interface by
doing this, we can say video
service and we'll call it service equals
and then we can say adapt.
because that's our adapter.create.
And we pass in video class.
And this will actually go and construct an
object that implements our interface but
in the background
uses Retrofit to automatically translate
our calls on that
object and those particular interface
methods into HTTP requests.
And then we could go and say something
like this.
If we wanted to actually interact with the
servlet and get the list of
videos, we can just say string videos
equals
service.getVideos, and we know, because we
understand how
HTTP works and we've seen on the server
side in particular how much work it takes.
The Retrofit is actually the, the library
is doing a huge amount of work for us.
It's going and taking this simple method
call here.
And it's turning it into an HTTP request,
sending
it across the network and then when the
response comes
back it's automatically extracting the
body of that response and
converting it into a string and returning
it to us.
Similarly, we can go and call all the
other methods on our interface, in this
case, addVideo.
We could also say service.addVideo and
we could pass in a name of our video.
We could pass in some URL and we could
pass
in a duration if we had some duration for
this video.
And again, Retrofit's going to go and see
this method call.
It's going to automatically take these
parameters, use the @field annotations
that we added to those parameters, convert
the method call into an
HTTP request, URL encode those parameters
into the body of that request,
send the request off to the server, and
we're on our way.
So, we're doing a lot of work in our
Retrofit library that helps us to send a
request
and interact with our servlets or the
other technologies
that we're going to be using to build
cloud services.
And these types of libraries help us
tremendously because up here we are
going from Java all the way to Java.
And we're not doing any conversion
ourselves, of our own.
So Retrofit, in the background, is
actually going to
HTTP, and back when we call this getVideos
method.
And it's going to HTTP and back, when we
call the addVideo method.
So it's doing a whole lot of work for us
that's very, very helpful.
And we'll talk about how it can get even
more
helpful later on after we've talked about
JSON and data marshaling.