[MUSIC]
In the past example that we used, our
implementation in the video repository was
always in memory.
It was always backed up by some simple
Java data structure.
But what if we wanted to store our videos
in an actual database?
So what if we wanted our video repository
to provide
an interface to a database, such as
MongoDB or something else.
So that we could save data into it.
Or maybe we want to connect up to a MySQL
database.
Well if we use JPA, we can actually very
easily convert
our video repository into an interface
that Spring
will automatically provide an
implementation for to connect to
our database and save our video objects
into a database.
So let's take a look at some code that
will do this.
First we need to go and look at our video
object.
If we're going to begin storing videos in
a database, we're going to have to
do a little bit of work to use JPA with
our video object.
The first one is, is that we need to tell
JPA
that this is an object that we expect to
be stored
in a database, and the way that we do that
is
by adding an at entity annotation to the
top of the class.
So as we'll see here, this @entity
annotation has been added to to the
video class, signaling to JPA that this is
something to store in a database.
The next thing that we need to do, is
because we're going to
be storing these objects, we need a way of
uniquely identifying each object.
And we do that by adding an @ID annotation
to
the property in the video that we want to
make unique.
And to be the unique identifier to a
video.
So in this case, all we've done is added
a simple long ID member variable to our
video.
So each video can be assigned a unique
number that we can refer to it by,
and if we want to go and look it up in the
database, we can specify a particular ID.
That we want JPA to go and get the video
associated with.
Now, one trick here is that, how do we
make sure that our IDs are always unique?
How when we store a new video, do we make
sure that it has a unique ID?
Now we could certainly keep track of this
ourselves.
And try to remember what our last ID was
and automatically assign a new ID.
But luckily, we don't actually have to do
that.
JPA can automatically, if we tell it to,
generate unique
IDs for each of our object instances that
we store.
So, in this example here, we're adding the
@ Generated Value.
Strategy=GenerationType.auto, and that's
telling JPA every time we
store a video for the first time in the
repository,
we want you to automatically assign a
value to its ID, so that it's unique.
So JPA is taking care of automatically
making sure
that our video ID is unique for each
individual instance.
The other thing is, all of the rest of
the class is exactly the same as it was
before.
We have member variables and getters and
setters.
Everything else is the same.
All of the logic is the same.
But adding these simple annotations of
@entity and then
ID that's auto generated, this is enough
to tell JPA
what it needs to know in order to store
our video in a variety of different types
of databases.
Now, this is the first piece which is to
tell JPA
about our entities, or the objects that we
want to store.
The second piece, is to provide, the
information that Spring Data JPA
needs to figure out how to automatically
provide this storage logic for us.
So, if you went and actually wrote code,
to use JPA,
you would see that you are writing similar
code over and over.
Just like we had when we're receiving
HTTP, requests there's boiler plate code.
When you're going to use JPA to store data
in a database you're going
to end up writing a very similar code over
and over to be
able to save objects, to be able to update
the existing objects in
the database, to be able to delete them or
to search for them.
So Spring Data actually takes all of this
boiler plate code,
and it automatically generates it for you
if you tell it to.
So, in this case, the way that we
get Spring Data to automatically generate
the code
that we need to create, read, update, and
delete the video objects that we want to
store.
Is we take our video repository and we add
the @repository annotation to it.
And then the second thing we do is we make
sure that the repository interface extends
the crud repository interface, provided by
J, not by JPA but by Spring Data JPA.
And what this does, is this crud
repository specifies a
variety of default methods like, Save to
save an object.
Find a particular object by its ID.
Checking if an object exists.
Getting all of a particular type of object
that we've saved.
Or deleting or counting the objects that
we previously saved.
So the crud repository is a super
interface that we
inherit from that provides a lot of the
default functionality.
And all we have to do is parameterize
it by the type of object we're going to
store.
So the first thing here in the crud
repository parameterization, is
the type of object we're going to store,
which is a video.
And then the type of ID that videos have.
In this case, if we go back and look at
our video, we see that their ID is a long.
So when we were parameterize it, we
parameterize the crud repository with a
long.
So what this is saying is, this video
repository is a JPA repository that Spring
is going
to create that will store videos and where
each
video has a unique long that is its
identifier.
And automatically because we inherit or
extend this super interface,
crud repository, we're going to get
methods to save, find
an existing object, find all existing
objects, delete objects, or
even go and query objects for, that meet a
specific criteria.
So in order to tell Spring to go and
instantiate a implementation
of this interface that automatically
provides the logic that we
need, we go, and in our Application class,
all we have to do is
add one new annotation, and that is
EnableJPARepositories.
And we're going to tell it where we want
it to
go and find those repository interfaces
that it should provide implementations
for.
In this case we're saying, go and look at
the package associated with the video
repository class, and any
classes that are in the video repository
classes parent
package, you should automatically go and
create implementations of them.
So, if we go here we're going to have this
simple interface and it's going
to dynamically allow us to create
implementations
of this interface that we can use.
So, if we go back to our video service.
We're still at auto wiring.
And having Spring inject the
implementation
of our video repository into this
controller.
But one of the things you'll notice is
that if we go
back to the application, we are no longer
providing the actual implementation.
Instead, because we've added this
enableJPArepositories,
Spring is going to automatically
dynamically create an implementation of
that repository that provides all of the
functionality
we need to save video objects into a
database.
And then once it's created it, it's going
to automatically go
and inject it or auto-wire it into our
video repository users.
So all of the places that we are,
at auto-wiring a video repository, Spring
will take the
JPA video repository implementation that
it dynamically generates
and attach it to all of the right
locations.
And then if we go and look down, we'll see
that even though
we didn't directly define it, we now have
a method to save videos,
we have a method to find all the videos
that have been saved
in the database, or we can even go and
search for particular videos.
Now, all of this is being provided for us,
we
don't actually have to provide an
implementation of the repository.
All we have to do is define the interface
that we are expecting for the dynamically
generated implementation.
Spring is literally going and looking at
this interface and saying, what database
is currently configured and attached, and
then
automatically figuring out how to
implement a
version of this interface that can talk to
that database and save video objects into
it, and automatically translate them into
the appropriate tables in the database.
The other interesting thing that we've
done is we've defined
a custom method here in this video
repository that's FindByName.
And what this method is is it's defining a
new way of querying for videos.
We want to find all videos where the
name parameter of the video, the member
variable
name of the video, matches a particular
value
that's provided in, in the, by the caller.
There is a naming convention that Spring
allows you to use.
So any methods on your video repository
that are find by and then the name of
a member variable, Spring will
automatically generate a
method that generates the appropriate
query in the database.
To find all objects with the member
variable
of, in this case, name, that matches the
value.
And there's a whole specification for how
you can name
methods and annotate them to generate
complex queries on your database.
In this case, we're just using a very
simple example, FindByName.
But we could also go and add methods for
other things like, if we wanted to find
all videos by duration, we could say,
findByDuration, and provide
a value for the duration that we're want,
videos that are exactly this long.
And Spring data would automatically go and
generate an implementation and an
appropriate query
to find all of the video objects that we
had stored with that duration.
Now this is all almost pure magic when you
look at it.
We're not actually providing any of the
logic, and it's
quite complex logic to go and interact
with the database.
All we're telling Spring is, here is an
interface that we would like to
have an implementation for, to store
videos,
to search for them, to delete them.
Go and automatically produce an
implementation for us.
And Spring can figure out, based on
our annotations, how to create an
implementation of
thisr repository that can do all of the
things that we need it to do.
So this vastly simplifies our work for
creating
data driven applications that are
connected to a database