[MUSIC]
When you create controllers, they're
magically instantiated by Spring.
It automatically discovers the controllers
as we've seen.
Looks at all of the annotations on those
controllers and
then figures out what requests to map to
the controller.
But often our controllers are going to
depend
upon a bunch of other objects that we
define.
And we would probably not necessarily like
to define exactly how
we instantiate and create our controller
completely in the controller itself.
We'd like to be able to configure it
different ways,
depending on the situations in, which it
is being used.
So for example, let's say we have a
controller, @controller, and
we're going to call this public class and
we'll make this our video service.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We now have a simple Spring controller,
and let's say that
we would like to have different storage
options for our videos.
So, somewhere else, we go and define an
interface called storage system.
So, we have a member variable,
called StorageSystem.
And we'll call this storage.
So we now have a member variable, that's
of type StorageSystem.
And StorageSystem is a interface that
we've defined somewhere else.
So maybe in our storage system we have
different implementations.
We might have, for example, a
implementation that stores things in
Amazon S3.
[SOUND] And we call that AmazonS3Storage.
Or maybe we have one that stores things
locally.
And
we'll call that local storage and these
will be
different classes that would implement the
storage system interface.
So we'd like our controller, our video
service controller to
be able to operate on either type of
storage system.
Now one way we could do this is we could
simply say
equals and then instantiate this specific
storage system that we wanted to use.
So we could say storage equals
AmazonS3Storage
and create a new one, or storage equals
new local storage, but then that's
going to
make it so that this video service object.
Every time we want to change the type of
storage system we're using for
it, we're going to have to go
and rewrite the code itself, recompile the
application.
And that's not what we'd like to do.
What we'd like to do is be able to, when
we start up the application in a
particular configuration, we'd like
to have this automatically paramaterized
and injected into the controller, the
appropriate storage system that we want
for that particular use case.
And Spring gives us a way to do
this, through a process known as
dependency injection.
So what dependency injection is, is we can
define, objects, that a particular class
depends on.
So, a video service depends on having a
storage system object provided to it.
That is the storage system is a dependency
that the video service needs.
And the injection part in dependency
injection
means that spring can automatically fill
in and
provide an object that implements the
storage
system interface, without us having to
construct it.
Now the way that we do this and this is
going to seem like magic at first, is we
go and we add a special annotation to this
memory variable called at AutoWired.
Whoops, dot AutoWired, and what this says
is, whenever you go and instantiate a
video service,
Spring, you must also find a storage
system
object that can be automatically wired or
injected into this variable.
So, what Spring is going to do, is
it's going to look through the
configuration that's
provided to it, and it's going to try to
find an implementation of storage system
in that configuration.
And if it can find a configuration, some,
in that configuration a implementation of
storage system.
Then it's going to automatically take and
create an instance
of that object or reuse an existing
implementation that's already
been created and inject it or
automatically set the
storage system, or the storage member
variable, to that value.
So, it automatically looks at this video
service needs an implementation of storage
system.
It automatically finds an implementation
for
it that you've defined in your
configuration.
And then it automatically sets your member
variable
to the value that was defined in your
configuration.
And so this is really nice, because we can
create
a video service that depends on any number
of other objects.
So for example, we might have another
dependent object that's you know, User
Manager, that is defined in interface
somewhere else.
And we'll call this users.
And then we can just say @AutoWired for
it.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And Spring, will automatically, for every
single one of these
dependencies that we define by adding
AutoWired, it will automatically go
and look through the configuration, find
an appropriate object that
implements the interface that we've
defined here, that we depend upon.
And then get that object and set our
member variable to it.
So it goes and automatically instantiates
and configures whole
hierarchies of objects, through dependency
injection to build our application.
And we can control how all of this done,
is done by providing different
configuration objects to spring.
To populate the different AutoWired
properties of
our objects, we need a way of
telling the dependency injection mechanism
in Spring,
how to map to these individual interfaces.
Their class is expected to be in
AutoWired.
And the way that we do that is with a
configuration object.
So in Spring, we can create a class that
defines
the mappings between the actual concrete
implementations of the different
interfaces, that our controllers and other
objects depend upon, and
the actual specific class that we want to
use for that interface.
So, to do this, we can simply create, a
class,
we'll call this VideoConf, and we annotate
it with the @Configuration annotation.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And what that tells Spring and the
dependency injection is
that go and look at this class, VideoConf,
and construct
an instance of it, and look inside of it
for
the mappings to some of these AutoWired
dependencies that we need.
And then in order to fill something like
the
storage system, we could simply add a
method, public.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Storage system, and then we’ll
call this method storage system.
And then in the method we could simply
say.
Return new LocalStorage.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, in this class, in this configuration
class, we've created
a method that's called StorageSystem, and
when you invoke it, it
gives you the actual implementation, in
this case, LocalStorage, that
we would like to use for this auto-wired
storage system dependency.
And then all we need to do is add @Beam as
an annotation to this method.
And so what'll happen is, at runtime,
Spring will
go and create an instance of your
VideoConf object.
And then it will look for all of the
methods annotated with @Beam and then it
will automatically call
them to get the appropriate class that you
want to
implement each of the interfaces defined
by the return type.
So, in this case, if we say, @beam
StorageSystem.
What that means is, is that we're going to
create an instance of LocalStorage.
And then everywhere in our code that we
have a member variable that's
of type StorageSystem that has @AutoWired,
Spring is automatically
going to go and take the value that it got
back
from this method and set the appropriate
member variable with that value.
So, we're completely decoupling how our
objects
get constructed and configured from the
configurations.
All we have to do is create a class that
has
@AutoWired on the various dependencies or
other objects that it depends on.
And we define those dependencies by having
an interface that abstracts away the
details of the different implementations
like S3 storage versus local storage.
And then in order to define for a
particular application use case, how
we map those different implementations of
storage
system, we create an @Configuration
annotated class.
And would create methods with @Beam
annotation
to define and create the actual
implementations.
Now, this may seem really complicated, and
at first, it's a
huge leap to sort of wrap your head around
what's going on.
But, once you understand how this
dependency injection mechanism works, it's
a really
powerful part of Spring that allows you to
write more modular, and reusable code.
So, what's going on at runtime is when,
Spring instantiates your
video service, it goes and it reads, and
it sees @AutoWired.
It then goes and says, what type do I
need?
And, it looks, at the type of the member
variable that's being AutoWired.
And then what it does is it goes through
and it looks in the configuration object
and it
says, is there a method that's annotated
with @Beam
that returns the appropriate type that I'm
looking for?
If yes, I need to call it and get the
return
value from it and use that to plug into
this member variable.
Now, one of the things that's really
useful to know is
by default in Spring, it's only going to
call this method once.
So it's going to call and create one
instance
of LocalStorage, and then every other
class that is
using that same storage system and has
@AutoWired, they
will all get a reference to exactly the
same object.
That's the default behavior.
Now, you can change it, so that each time
it sees @AutoWired, it will call
this method and get a new instance of that
object that should be plugged in.
But by default, and usually this is what
you want in many cases, you want every
single place where you're using a storage
system
to get a reference to the same storage
system.
And so, very quickly you can do singleton
like behavior where you have
a single object that is plugged in to a
whole bunch of different classes.
And you don't have to figure out
complicated mechanisms for passing
that object around to all of the places
that it's actually needed.
Spring can automatically figure out what
your
dependencies are based on @AutoWired, go
and look
in your configuration object and match up
the return types of the @Beam annotated
methods.
And then do all of the wiring to take this
object that's returned, and plug it in to
all the places that reference a storage
system and have @AutoWired on it.
So it's a very, very powerful mechanism in
Spring.