[MUSIC]
Once you've created a series of classes
that
are annotated with the @entity annotation
and given
them IDs, or unique IDs of some sort, to
reference them in the database, what you
need is a way to actually interact with
the database through JPA and be able to
store and find and retrieve the data or
the objects that your persisting into the
database.
The way that we do that in JPA or with
Spring is by creating a repository.
So in Spring we can create an interface to
a repository.
So let's create a video repository.
So we'll have a public interface.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we'll call this VideoRepo.
And we want it to extend, and
this is a really important part, is we're
going to extend the other interface called
CrudRepository, and we have to
parametrize the CrudRepository with the
types that we are doing.
So in this case it's going to be Video,
Long.
And I've just gone down on one line here
where I'm parametrizing CrudRepository.
So this is our class, or actually our
interface, and the reason that we do
this is all we're going to specify the
interface
to saving updating, retrieving, our
different video objects.
And the Spring framework is actually going
to fill
in the details or the implementation of
this interface.
This is one of the beautiful parts of this
approach, is we have all of this complex
work that needs to happen to save these
classes annotated with entity, these
instances, into the database.
And all we're going to do is define the
interface that we
would like to have in order to save them
and Spring
is automatically going to fill in the
object that will be
implementing this interfacing and saving
and retrieving the objects for us.
The interface just gives us a way of
interacting with that object through some
nice mechanism.
Now what CrudRepository is, is it's an
interface for a standard
repository that can save objets in the
database.
And what CRUD stands for create, read,
update, and delete.
So it's giving us the ability to create
new entities in the database.
So we can create a new video object and
store it in the database.
Read, because we can read existing stored
video objects.
Update, because we can take an existing
object, we can change
some of its properties, and update its
representation in the database.
And then finally, delete in CRUD, because
we can delete video objects.
So by default, we automatically get a
series
of methods that are inherited from this
CrudRepository.
We get save.
We can find objects we've stored by
filling in
the unique ID that we assigned to that
object.
And if you go and look
at how we're paramaterizing this
CrudRepository interface
that we're extending, the second
parameter, the
type we're providing is our ID type.
So, this is the type of our ID or our
unique ID
that we're that we've included in our
class as the ant entity annotation.
And this is the type that our repository
is operating on.
So these are the type of objects that
we're going
to be storing through the repository and
retrieving through the repository.
So by, by extending CrudRepository we get
all the basic operations to
save objects or types of videos into the
database.
We get the ability to retrieve by finding
one or all, or running a query to find
a series of, of different video objects
that meet our parameters in the database.
So, immediately we get a lot of work done
for us by Spring.
One of the most important functions that
we
typically need above save or delete of the
video
objects that we're going to be storing is
the
ability to find video objects that meet
some criteria.
So for example we might want to go and
search
for all the videos that have a particular
name.
Or all of the videos that have a
particular category,
if we had added a category member variable
to our video.
And so, to inde-,
be able to do that, we can't do that
with the default methods that are provided
by CRUD.
We have to have something beyond simply
search by the unique
id of a video, or something beyond, give
me all videos.
We want to be able to search based on
different
member variable values of the objects that
we've stored.
So the way that we do that with the
repository is by defining
in our interface new methods that provide
the type of searches that we want.
So for example, we could go and add a new
search like public list, because we're
going to a series of them, video
findByName.
And then we could have a String for the
name.
And this simple method that we've just
added to our interface is
going to tell Spring that it needs to go
and create a way of querying
the data by the name member variables of
all the objects that have been stored.
So, what it will see is, I'm going to have
to create a method
of querying that's going to return more
than one video object from the database.
The find here and by is telling Spring
that this
is going to be a query that it needs to
run.
And the name is telling it the criteria of
that query.
Basically this is saying, find every video
object where
video.name equals the value that's passed
in here, n.
So, behind the scenes, Spring is
automatically constructing an
implementation of this interface method
that can query all of your
videos and return any stored object, if
you had a
member variable name equal to the value
that's passed in.
So we're actually running a query,
defining a query across the member
variables in our stored objects based on
the naming of the method.
Similarly, we can go and add additional
fields that we'd like to query by.
So, for example, we could say, public
lists
video, and we could say, find by name.
And if we had, let's say, a category
member variable.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then we can define our parameters to
this
thing to be string name, and string
category.
And Spring will automatically realize it
needs to go and find all objects where
video, and that's what this is telling us
again, is this is defining our query.
Video.name equals the name that was passed
in.
And we also have, at the same time,
video.category if we had
a category member variable equals the
category value that we passed in.
So, simply by going and adding and
defining new methods on our interface that
start with find, and then provide a series
of query parameters.
So in this case we're saying we're
going to query across name
and category, and then providing method
parameters for each of those things.
Spring can automatically go and figure out
how to
construct a query and find all of those
objects.
So you can very quickly add all kinds of
complex search
mechanisms simply by defining new methods
and giving them the appropriate naming.
And there are many more things that you
can do
with the method naming to do more advanced
querying capabilities.
And if you go and look at the spring data
JPA documentation or
a repository documentation, you'll see all
of those different capabilities that are
provided.
But for our case, these are going to be
sufficient for the
things that we need to do to create our
video upload service.