[MUSIC]
>> So let's take a look at an example
of an SQL injection attack in the Video
Service class.
Let's assume that we've written a method
that is vulnerable to an SQL injection
attack.
And see what that looks like.
And one thing to note is that
although we're talking about SQL injection
attacks, other
query languages that are operating on
databases
are also vulnerable to this type of
attack.
It's important to remember it's not just
isolated to SQL, but it's
anything where you're going to execute
logic on data that's in a database.
So let's assume that we've created a
method to
allow users to go and search their own
private videos.
So we've got a method called myVideos that
takes in a
string for a name of a video that they're
searching for.
And so the goal is, we're going to return
all
the videos to a user that have a
particular name.
Now, let's also assume that, the way that
our service is set up,
users want to be able to have some private
videos as well as public videos.
And this is going to go and search all of
the videos that only belong to a user,
so it may include both private and public
videos
in the results that we're returning back
to that user.
So we've got our @controller, and request
mapping annotations on this, we
don't see them here because we want to
focus on just this code.
And the first thing we do is using some
mechanism like Spring Security which we'll
talk about later, we go and get access to
the current user that sent the request.
So somebody has logged in and we can get
information about their user account.
So the next thing we do, is we decide to
go and construct a query to search
the database for all of the videos that
that
particular user has uploaded that meet the
search criteria.
So we say, select star from video where
owner equals, and we have a quote.
And we are doing this as a string.
And we are going to append with plus, the
user
name, because we want to go and search for
a particular user.
And then we say plus and we have another
closing quote and our apostrophe.
And name equals, and then we're going to
put
in the name and then we're going to close
that.
Now, if you look at this code and
you think that this is secure code because
we've
got the quotation marks here, that are
going
to be indicating that this thing is a
string.
So therefore anything that gets passed in
here will
be interpreted as a string and there's no
problem.
You'd been unfortunately very wrong.
This is a very insecure method.
Any time you see code like this, you
should immediately try to get it fixed.
You don't ever want to write your own
code like this that directly takes data
from the
client and then puts it into something
that's
going to be logic, that's going to get
executed.
You always have to be very very careful
that the data that you are taking
from the client and mixing it with your
logic absolutely cannot be turned into
logic itself.
So in this case, is there a way that we
can take the name
data that the user or client is providing
and cause it to change this logic?
The answer is yes, absolutely it's
possible.
So let's take a look at how the client
could provide data that
would change the logic that's being
expressed
in this query that's being built up.
So, assume that the user provides a value
that's not malicious.
And the user provides a value like, the
owner is Coursera.
What we're going to end up with is a query
string
that looks like select star from videos,
or video, where owner equals Coursera,
because let's assume it's Coursera.
And name.
And let's assume they're looking for SQL
videos.
Now, in this case if they provided, the
user name happened
to be up here was Coursera, and they
provided the value SQL.
Everything should be fine.
It's going to only search through
Coursera's videos
and it's going to search through name
equals SQL.
Now, you can see in here how we're
substituting, we're substituting
name in here, and we're substituting the
user name in right here.
But, assume that the client provides
the value, foo, or, a equals a.
Now this looks like a strange string, so
what happens if the client provides that?
Well, if you go and substitute
this in here, and let's assume,
let's say the owner is foo,
we get select star from video
where owner equals foo.
Now, things start to get more interesting
and we say and.
Now, we need to go, and substitute in the
rest of the strings.
We see and name equals, it has an
apostrophe here.
Now we're going to add on this value right
here.
And what we get is foo, or, a equals a.
And then we've got the closing quotation
mark, or apostrophe.
Now, suddenly, the value that the attacker
has provided
has changed this query and added
additional logic.
This is new logic on this query.
And this is suddenly a serious problem.
Because, the designer of this query that's
being
built up on the string is assuming that
the only logic that's being executed is
the
select from video where owner equal and
name equals.
They were not assuming that any additional
logic
could be tacked onto the end of this
query.
But because this is just simple string
manipulation, there's nothing to prevent
the attacker
from taking additional data and using it
to append logic to this SQL statement.
So suddenly we've got a big problem.
And the reason is, is because the a equals
a part is always true.
And so what this means is, is when this
database goes and interprets this it's
going to say I want to find any video
where, owner equals foo and name equals
foo.
So this would actually be safe and would
only search the
videos of that particular user that was
sending in the data.
Or new logic here, a equals a.
So that means if a video matches this or
a video matches this second part, it
should return it.
And in this case, a equals a will always
be true.
So the attacker will get access to every
video, regardless if
it's public or private and who owns it,
and get it returned.
That entire list of videos will be
returned.
And you can imagine that if you can insert
new logic here, you
can insert arbitrary logic here that could
do all kinds of bad things.
Like changing the data in the database, or
deleting data in the database,
or getting access to sensitive data, or
adding users, or all kinds of things.
So if you'd, aren't careful and you begin
mixing logic with data in
an unsafe way, particularly with SQL
statements, it's possible
to end up in a situation where the
attacker can inject
new logic or do a SQL injection attack in
this case.
And suddenly the code that you are running
in your server isn't just your own
anymore.
It's your code plus the attacker's code.
The attacker's logic and commands are
being executed
right beside yours, and beside your
sensitive data.
So you need to be very, very careful
that when you are building queries, or
you're building
any type of mechanism that's going to mix
some type of client data in with
executable logic.
That you don't end up in a situation where
the
client controls the logic that you're
executing to some degree.
So, luckily, if you're building on top of
Spring data or Spring data rest, and
you're just using the findBy methods or
the
findAll or, or save or those other
methods.
It's automatically constructing the
queries for you, and
the SQL statements for you, and it's doing
it
in a safe way that will guarantee that you
are immune to these types of SQL injection
attacks.
However, if you drop down to the lower
level and you begin manually creating
your queries as strings, you must be aware
that this type of thing is possible.
And if you ever go in, and you're
reviewing older code that
has these type of string based SQL
statements in it, you should
be very, very careful and make sure that
they are built in
a way that protects the application from
having additional logic injected into it.