[MUSIC]
In the last servlet example that we saw,
we were using the
HTTP client library to send POST and GET
requests to the server.
But, if you've noticed it took a lot of
work, just like with the servlet, to be
able to turn our logic into something we
can send an HTTP POST request with.
So we had to go and create a HTTP POST, we
had to create a bunch of named value
pairs, and then URL encode them, and
attach them
to this body, and send it off to the
server.
And it really took a lot of work and there
was a big
disconnect from the code that we were
trying to write, which was at a
video or get a list of the videos, and
what we actually had to
do in order to invoke that on the server
and get the result back.
Now, just like with Spring, there are ways
to simplify that
interaction, significantly so that we
don't have to write all of the
low-level code to translate our desires in
terms of method
invocations and, on the services that are
in the cloud into HTTP methods.
So, right now what we're having to do is
when we want to send a message to
our server our client is having to go
through
and use a library to manually create the
HTTP request.
So, the interface that we're working with
is the Apache HTTP client.
Which means that we're having to be
exposed to all of the
information related to, how do you go and
translate something like
add video into HTTP.
What we would really like to do is just
directly call add video.
And then have whatever library we're
using, this black box, automatically
translate that into the appropriate HTTP
calls that need to go to the server.
Just like on the server we can
automatically
see what parameters a method is expecting,
extract
them, create objects, invoke the method,
and then
convert the return type back into a HTTP
response.
We want to be able to do something similar
on the client side so that
we can do things in a more
Java object-oriented way where we're just
invoking methods.
And because they have the right
information,
HTTP requests are being sent from them.
And there's a number of reasons to do
this, one of which is, when
we're dealing with the low-level details
of
like HTTP client we can easily make
mistakes.
We can make typos in the strings that
we're using for keys.
We can easily have all kinds of situations
where we are
looking at the different response codes to
figure out what to do.
We'd really like to make it simpler and
look like this so that
we can have simple, easy invocations that
look object oriented to our code.
Now we still have to account for the fact
that these invocations are going to be
slow because they're going across a
network, but
we would like to have the automatic
translation.
And that's what retrofit is going to
provide us in this
code example is retrofit can
automatically, if we give it
the right annotations, translate our
method calls into HTTP requests
on our server that will be interpreted
correctly by Sprint.
So let's take a look at how this works.
So, if you open up the video controller in
retrofit
project again and look at
the client package,
the org.magnum.mobilecloud.video.client
package.
Let's look at this video service API that
we didn't look at before.
Now, what you'll see is, is we're
actually using retrofit with this video
service API.
So we've created an interface, a Java
interface, to
describe the operations that can be
invoked on our controller.
In this case, we can invoke getVideoList
and get a list of videos returned to us.
Or we can invoke addVideo, and provide a
video object.
And we'll get a boolean back if it's
successful.
And if you'll go and look, and we can open
up and look at our controller class that
we created.
We'll see that our controller class
actually implements this video service
API.
So, we've created an interface that
provides a strong
contract between our controller, which is
the server side.
And our client, which is going to be
the the video service API side created by
retrofit.
So, we're going to use retrofit to
automatically
create an implementation of an object that
can,
when these methods are invoked, send the
appropriate
HTTP request to the server, in order to,
and automatically translate the response
body back into
a list of videos or automatically
translate a
video into a request body so that we
can invoke the correct methods on our
controller.
So what we've got in this video service
API.
Is the get video list method has been
annotated with
the at get annotation that is provided by
the retrofit library.
So all we have to do is tell it to, that
whenever you invoke this you should a GET
request, and here is the actual path to
the request that you should be sending.
So when you send a get request it's
going to send a request to /video, which
we also know is what our video service
controller is bound to, the various
request mappings.
So you can see that the various request
mappings are also bound to video service
path.
So we know both our client and our
server are going to be working with the
same paths.
Also added an at body annotation so that
retrofit knows that the video parameter
that we're providing should automatically
be converted into the body of the
request that we're sending, and in this
case retrofit's going to be converting
that video into JSON and putting it in the
body of the request.
On the other side, we know that Spring is
going to look at the
body of the request and interpret it as
JSON and read a video back out.
So we've got a nice contractor interface
that we can use to
allow us to automatically send requests in
an object-oriented way to our server.
Now if we open up the
VideoServiceClientAPITest, in the Source
Test Java
package, we can see how we use retrofit
and this interface together.
First, at the top of the test we create an
implementation of this interface
dynamically, or we ask retrofit to create
a dynamic implementation of this interface
that will send HTTP
requests in response to the methods on
this interface being invoked.
And the way that we do that is we create a
new rest adapter builder.
And then we set the endpoint to be our
server, which is then case is local host
8080.
We set up some logging so we can see
what's actually being sent to the server.
And then we build and create a new
implementation of the
video service API that's bound and
attached to this particular server.
So what is actually happening behind the
scenes here is
retrofit is creating an object that
implements the video service API.
And it's dynamically creating this object
such that whenever you invoke
one of the methods on the video service
API, it's going
to generate the appropriate request based
on your annotations on that
method and send it to the server that
we've specified up here.
So, if we look a little farther down, what
we see
is we have a example where we are creating
a URL,
a title, and a duration for a video, just
like we
did before with our test that was using
the HTTP client library.
But rather than having to go into the
low-level details of
constructing a HTTP POST request and using
the client to send it,
instead we just create a video object with
those details and then
ask the video service API implementation,
called videoService, to add the video.
Now a huge amount of work is happening
behind the scenes to make this happen.
What retrofit is doing is our addVideoCall
is being taken and translated by retrofit
into a HTTP POST request.
And the way it's doing this, is the
interface
that we're using up here, the video
service API,
is annotated with the various at post and
at get annotations.
And so when you invoke addVideo Retrofit
looks
at addVideo and says, what annotation is
on it?
And it sees at post.
So it says, I know I'm supposed to create
a POST request for addVideo.
It then looks at the value that you
provide inside the annotation, which in
case, in
this case is /video and says, I know I
need to send that request to /video.
It then looks at the annotation inside the
parameters and says, I know I need to
take.
This parameter video and encode it in to
the body of this HTTP POST request.
So, the video that's in here is going to
be inserted as
JSON in to the body of this request.
And then on the other side, Spring and
your controller is receiving this JSON.
Enable to do its own magic to extract that
JSON into a video object and process it.
Similarly, if the controller sends a
response back,
the retrofit library can see the return
type
of' addVideo and know that I need to
take whatever is in the response body,
interpret
it as that particular return type so I can
read it out of the response body
as JSON and then convert it to whatever
return type of the addVideo method we
have.
So, all of this complicated work allows us
to have
this simple call that we see right here to
videoService.addVideo.
And all of the details of how this method
call goes and
actually turns our video into an HTTP POST
request is hidden from us.
And instead, we can operate it using
an object-orientated, nice, clean
interface to our server.
And then we can also go and similarly, get
a list of videos that's from the server.
This is going to end up sending a get
request to the server
to /video based on the annotations that we
provided in our interface.
So, through some simple annotations we're
getting
really powerful simplification of the work
that
we have to do in order to interact and
send HTTP methods to the server.
Not only that, but it's hard for us to
mess up
these requests, because atVideo, addVideo
is a strongly typed Java method.
So if we don't pass a video object in,
this method would not compile.
This method call would not compile.
So if we try to pass something else in.
So we're not only getting a simple
interface to go and invoke those methods,
but we're getting type safety because our
interface has strong Java typing on it.
So we can't just go and involve methods
with the wrong parameter types or
expect that the parameter coming back from
the return value is of the wrong type.
So you can see how retrofit is doing a lot
of the same type
of work that Spring is doing, but it's
doing it on the client side.
It's making it easier for us to generate
the HTTP
requests from method calls that are going
to the server.
And take the responses that we're getting
back and convert
the response bodies back into objects that
we can operate on.
So it's substantially simplifying and
improving the
type safety of our interaction with the
server.